<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatise of the Holy Trinunity [sic]. In two parts. The first, asserting the deity of Jesus Christ and the Holy Spirit, in the unity of essence with God the father. The second, in defence of the former, containeth answers to the chiefest objections made against this doctrine. By Isaac Marlow.</title>
            <author>Marlow, Isaac.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 235 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 100 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51999</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M696</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R216280</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99828018</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99828018</idno>
            <idno type="VID">32445</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51999)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 32445)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1855:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatise of the Holy Trinunity [sic]. In two parts. The first, asserting the deity of Jesus Christ and the Holy Spirit, in the unity of essence with God the father. The second, in defence of the former, containeth answers to the chiefest objections made against this doctrine. By Isaac Marlow.</title>
                  <author>Marlow, Isaac.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 186, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for the author, and are to be sold by Richard Baldwin in the Old-Baily,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With a final contents leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Trinity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Theological, Doctrinal --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:32445:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TREATISE OF THE HOLY TRINUNITY. <hi>In Two Parts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THE FIRST, Aſſerting the Deity of Jeſus Chriſt and the Holy Spirit, in the Unity of Eſſence with God the Father.</p>
            <p>THE SECOND, In Defence of the former, containeth Anſwers to the chiefeſt Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons made againſt this Doctrine.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Iſaac Marlow.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>John 1.1, 2, 3.</hi>
               </bibl> In the Beginning was the Word, and the Word was with God, and the Word was God: The ſame was in the Beginning with God: All things were made by him; and without him was not any thing made, that was made.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for the Author, and are to be ſold by <hi>Richard Baldwin</hi> in the <hi>Old-Baily,</hi> 1690.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:32445:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:32445:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:32445:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:32445:3"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HAving met with ſome oppoſition to the Doctrine of the Holy Trinunity, it occaſioned my more than ordinary Meditations on this Subject, wherein I received great ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of Mind. And notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the <hi>Socinians</hi> have taken great pains to find out Arguments to ſupport their Error, yet I found they had no Foundation in the Holy Scriptures: And nothing is more the Duty of every Chriſtian than to inform himſelf of the Truth as it is in Jeſus, both in the Doctrinal and Practical Parts of the Chriſtian Faith: And tho the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of every ſacred Truth is worth the treaſuring up in our Hearts, yet there are ſome more than others conducing to the Glory of God, and the mutual Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip of Chriſtians.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:32445:4"/>
            <p>Among which the bleſſed Doctrine of the Holy Trin-unity is the chiefeſt: for to deny the Deity of Jeſus Chriſt, and the Holy Ghoſt, is a great deprivation not only of the Glory of theſe two Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Subſiſtencies, but alſo of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: For <hi>he that honoureth not the Son, honoureth not the Father,</hi> Joh. <hi>5.23.</hi> And unleſs we ſee the Divine Rays of the Son, we cannot ſee the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>chap. 14.9. And if we have not the ſame Light, we cannot walk in the ſame Fellowſhip: for what Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion hath Light with Darkneſs, 1</hi> Joh. <hi>1.7. 2</hi> Cor. <hi>6.14.</hi> Moreover, ſeeing that the <hi>Fear of the Lord is the beginning of Wiſdom: and [the Knowledg of the Holy is Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding,]</hi> Prov. <hi>9.10.</hi> and that the Welfare of our Souls depends on our knowledg of God, and true Faith in him, as he is revealed to us in the Holy Scriptures to be our Saviour, it is high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly neceſſary, and the duty of every Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian to have a true diſtinct Knowledg
<pb facs="tcp:32445:4"/>of God, ſubſiſting in the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt. For as neither an implicit Faith can ſecure us from being turned aſide by every wind of Doctrine, and cunning Craftineſs of them that lie in wait to deceive: ſo unleſs we have true Notions of the Holy Trinity, we cannot worſhip God aright.</p>
            <p>To the end therefore that thoſe who have not a good underſtanding of this Doctrine, may be inlightned, and more eſtabliſh'd therein, and may have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what to anſwer, and ſtop the mouths of Gainſayers; and that others may be convinced of their Error, and confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in the Truth, I have preſented this ſmall Treatiſe to publick view.</p>
            <p>And tho I am ſenſible of my own Weakneſs, and Incapacity to manage this Inconceivable Myſtery, ſo as to ſuit and correſpond with the Grandure and Perfection of it; yet there is ſuch Evidence and clear Demonſtration gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven from the Word of Truth, of the Deity of our Bleſſed Lord and the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:32445:5"/>Spirit, as might eaſily gain it credence in the Minds of thoſe that do oppoſe it, if their Imbecillity were not ſuch as to limit the myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and tranſcendent manner of God's Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their finite Reaſon; and make the Scriptures ſubſervient to it: And therefore to thoſe it is my humble Requeſt:</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> That with a ſtudious and intentive Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit they will peruſe this little Treatiſe.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> That no former Prepoſſeſſions may hinder their full adherence to what hath Divine Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority ſtamp'd upon it, and then I doubt not of ſome good Effects of my Labour. For this Fundamental Truth hath ſo firm a Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the Holy Scriptures, as will ſtand the ſhock of all the <hi>Socinian</hi> Arguments: And tho I have not here undertaken to anſwer the multitude of them, or of their Objections made againſt this Doctrine, or any particular Author on this Subject; yet I have taken hold, as I conceive, of the chiefeſt Pillars on which their Fabrick depends; and thoſe being taken away, their whole Building will fall. Which that it wholly may, and that every Chriſtian may be eſtabliſh'd in the Truth of God, Is the Prayer of him, who deſires to be a true Worſhipper of the Trinune God, and is a Well-wiſher to all Men.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:32445:5"/>
            <head>The CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. I.</hi> THE Caſe is briefly ſtated. <hi>Pag.</hi> 1.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. II.</hi> Sheweth that there is but one God, the Creator of all things. <hi>Pag.</hi> 6.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. III.</hi> Aſſerteth a Plurality of Divine Subſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtences. <hi>Pag.</hi> 8.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. IV.</hi> Proveth the Deity of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. 1. By his Names. <hi>Pag.</hi> 11. 2. That God in the Old Teſtament in divers Places, is Chriſt in the New. <hi>Pag.</hi> 13. 3. By ſeven particular Texts of Scriptures. <hi>Pag.</hi> 16. 4. That Chriſt preexiſted his Incarnation in his Divine Nature. <hi>Pag.</hi> 26. And is no Angel incarnate, <hi>Pag.</hi> 30. but is eternal. <hi>Pag.</hi> 32. 5. By his Works. <hi>Pag.</hi> 35.6. By Divine Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip given to him. <hi>Pag.</hi> 38.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. V.</hi> Proveth the Deity of the Holy Ghoſt. 1. That he is a Divine Perſon. <hi>Pag.</hi> 43. 2. His Deity is aſſerted from ſeveral Scriptures. <hi>Pag.</hi> 45. 3. By his Works. <hi>Pag.</hi> 48. 4. By Divine Worſhip. <hi>Pag.</hi> 52.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. VI.</hi> Proveth the Unity of the Holy Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. <hi>Pag.</hi> 54.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. VII.</hi> Containeth ſome Explications of the Holy Trinuility. 1. Of the eſſential Being of God. <hi>Pag.</hi> 64. 2. Of a Divine Perſon. <hi>Pag.</hi> 64. 3. Of the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit. <hi>Pag.</hi> 65, 66. 4. Of the Unity of the Holy Trinity. <hi>Pag.</hi> 66. 5. Of the Diſtinctions between the Divine Nature and the Perſons, and ſome Shadows by way of Compariſon. <hi>Pag.</hi> 67. 6. Of the Union of Chriſt's two Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. <hi>Pag.</hi> 74.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:32445:6"/>
               <head>PART II.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. I.</hi> Anſwereth Objections againſt the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Proofs of Chriſt's Deity. <hi>Page</hi> 76.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. II.</hi> Anſwers to Objections drawn from ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Texts of Scripture. <hi>Pag.</hi> 123.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. III.</hi> Anſwers to ſeveral Arguments againſt the Deity of Chriſt. <hi>Pag.</hi> 128.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. IV.</hi> Anſwers to ſeveral Objections againſt the Scriptures that prove the Deity of the Holy Ghoſt. <hi>Pag.</hi> 132.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. V.</hi> Anſwers to ſome Objections drawn from divers Scriptures to diſprove the Deity of the Holy Spirit. <hi>Pag.</hi> 157.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. VI.</hi> Anſwers to ſome Scriptures from whence our Adverſaries aſſert that the Father only is the true God. With a general Anſwer and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion. <hi>Pag.</hi> 169.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:32445:6"/>
            <head>A TREATISE OF THE Holy Trinunity. In Two Parts.</head>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>PART I.</head>
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. I.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>In which after a ſhort Introduction, the Caſe is briefly ſtated.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>GOD who at ſundry Times, and in divers Manners, ſpake in Times paſt unto the Fathers by the Prophets; hath in theſe laſt Days ſpoken unto us by his Son: Who firſt in his own Perſon declared the Father's Will, and then by his Holy Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:32445:7"/>through the Spirit, more fully open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Myſteries (that had been hid from Ages and Generations) unto his Saints, and left them upon Sacred Record for fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Ages. By which means we come to the knowledg not only of the Grace, Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice and Operations of the Father, Son and Holy Spirit, but of the great Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of theſe Three, for ever bleſſed, holy, and divine Perſons, ſubſiſting in the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Godhead from all Eternity. But no ſooner did the Glory of the Holy Trinity begin to ſhine in the Miniſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt: But Satan the Prince of Darkneſs (leſt Men ſhould imbrace the Truth, and ſo his Kingdom ſhould fall) did what he could to hinder the Progreſs of the Goſpel in its primitive Purity, and in Enmity to the weal of Mankind, ſuggeſted many pernicious Errours into their Minds, as we may find in the Writings of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles of our Bleſſed Lord, which I for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear here to mention.</p>
                  <p>And throughout every ſucceſſive Age he hath not wanted ſome Inſtruments, to diſturb the Peace of the Church with falſe and erronious Doctrines, thereby to weaken the true Intereſt of Jeſus Chriſt,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:32445:7"/>as well as to ruin the Souls of Men.</p>
                  <p>And among others that have been broached in the World, this is one, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Son of God, and the Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, are not one infinite and eternal God, Coeſſential with the Father, but are ſo much inferiour in Nature to him, as to be but Creatures only.</p>
                  <p>But to ſpeak more particularly, Some affirm that Jeſus Chriſt is only humane, or nothing but Man: And though the Racovian Catechiſm, doth acknowledg he is more than a meer Man; yet they do not allow Chriſt to have a divine Nature, as we may ſee in <hi>Pag.</hi> 27, 28. of that Catechiſm: Where by way of Queſtion, they ſay, Is the Lord Jeſus then a meer Man? The Anſwer is, by no means; For he was conceived of the Holy Spirit, and born of the Virgin <hi>Mary;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is, from his very Conception and Birth, the Son of God, as we read <hi>Luke</hi> 1.30. and the Anſwer is cloſed with theſe Words, That the Lord Jeſus ought by no means to be reputed a meer Man.</p>
                  <p>Yet the next Queſtion being put, Hath he not alſo a Divine Nature? The An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer is, At no Hand; for that is repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:32445:8"/>not only to ſound Reaſon, but alſo to the Holy Scriptures.</p>
                  <p>Now if they will not allow Jeſus Chriſt to have a Divine Nature, and yet do ſay he is more than a meer Man; what can he then be? unleſs we ſuppoſe either (as <hi>Biddle</hi> ſaith Article 6. of his Confeſſion of Faith) that the Holy Spirit is an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel, and ſo by Conception he may be ſaid to participate of their Nature; or elſe that His viſible and external Exerciſe of the Power of God, is his Divine Nature. From the firſt <hi>Socinus</hi> (whom <hi>Biddle</hi> repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth for it) and <hi>Crellius</hi> do diſſent, for they deny the Spirit to be a Perſon, but the Power and Efficacy of God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
                  <p>So that according to their opinion Chriſt cannot be of the Nature of Angels by conception. Nay, <hi>Biddle</hi> himſelf, though he aſſerts the Holy Ghoſt to be an Angel, and Chriſt to be conceived by him, yet he ſaith that Chriſt hath no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than a humane Nature. Article the 3d.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> If his external and viſible Exerciſe of the Divine Power of God, be the external and viſible Exerciſe of his own Nature; it is what we are plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:32445:8"/>for, and if this were but granted, the main Controverſy would quickly ceaſe, for the Power of God as it is in God, is his Nature: ſo it muſt be in Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>But it's hard to conclude from what theſe Men do ſay, what Chriſt and the Holy Spirit are; for ſome are for having Chriſt nothing but Humane: and others, that He is more than a Man, <hi>viz.</hi> the Son of God by Conception, and yet that he is not God by Nature: So likewiſe <hi>Bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle</hi> is for having the Holy Ghoſt to be an Angel; others ſay, That he is the Power and Efficacy of God the Father: And what they will hammer forth at laſt, or where they will ſettle, who can tell? However, in this they all agree, That neither the Son nor the Holy Ghoſt, are God by Nature, or have the ſupream Divine Nature of God for their own Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: And therefore, foraſmuch as there hath been great endeavours uſed to ſuppreſs the Doctrine of the Holy Trin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unity; and to raze out, or ſo beſmear the written Word of God, that we ſhould not diſcern the Beauty and Excellency of the Nature of Chriſt, and the Holy Spirit; I ſhall endeavour to demonſtrate the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:32445:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>Truth of their Deity; and in order there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto,</p>
                  <p>Firſt, I ſhall note, that on all Hands it is agreed among Chriſtians, that the Scriptures do diſtinguiſh and make a difference between the Father, the Son, and the Holy Ghoſt; and that there is but one that is perſonally called the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and but one other Chief and only Son of that Father, and alſo a third diſtinguiſhed from both, and called the Holy Ghoſt, beſides which there is not another that is ſo called, as may be col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected from the following Scriptures, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.4, 5, 6. 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.9. <hi>chap.</hi> 5.7. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.16, 17. <hi>John</hi> 6.27. <hi>ch.</hi> 14.26.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. II.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Wherein is proved that there is but One God, the Creator and Former of all Things.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>TO ſhew this, I ſhall only give a bare Citation of ſeveral Texts of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and not take up our time, in that which is ſo generally believed by all Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</p>
                  <p>Deut. 6.4. <hi>Hear O Iſrael, the Lord our
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:32445:9"/>God is one Lord.</hi> 1 Sam. 2.2. <hi>There is none Holy as the Lord, for there is none beſides thee,</hi> &amp;c. Iſa. 46.9. <hi>Remember the former Things of old, for I am God, and there is none elſe; I am God, and there is none like me.</hi> 1 Cor. 4.6. <hi>There is none other God but One: but to us there is but one God the Father, of whom are all things.</hi> 1 Tim. 2.5. <hi>For there is but one God,</hi> &amp;c. Jam. 2.19. <hi>Thou believeſt there is but one God, thou doſt well.</hi> Nehem. 9.6. <hi>Thou, even thou, art Lord alone; Thou haſt made Heaven, the Heaven of Heavens with all their Hoſts, the Earth and all Things that are therein, the Sea and all that is therein, and thou preſerveſt them all, and the Hoſt of Heaven worſhippeth thee.</hi> Pſal. 86.9, 10. <hi>All Nations whom thou haſt made, ſhall come and worſhip before thee, O Lord, and ſhall glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy thy Name: For thou art great, and doeſt wondrous Things, thou art God alone.</hi> Iſa. 44.6. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord, the King of</hi> Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, <hi>and his Redeemer the Lord of Hoſts, I am the firſt, and I am the laſt, and beſides me there is no God.</hi> Ver. 24. <hi>I am the Lord that maketh all Things.</hi> Iſa. 45.18. <hi>For thus ſaith the Lord, that created the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, God himſelf that formed the Earth and made it: He hath eſtabliſhed it, He created
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:32445:10"/>it not in vain, He formed it to be inhabited, I am the Lord, and there is none elſe.</hi> There are many other Scriptures of like import, but theſe are plain and ſufficient Teſtimonies to prove that there is but one God the Creatour and Former of all Things.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. III.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Sheweth that there is a Plurality of Divine Subſiſtences.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>FIrſt, from <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.1. <hi>In the Beginning God created the Heaven and the Earth.</hi> The word in the Hebrew is <hi>[Elohim]</hi> Gods, or Almighties, in the Plural Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber: I find an Expoſition of this Text by Mr. <hi>William Streat,</hi> which becauſe it gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth much Light, I ſhall preſent the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der with the material part of it.</p>
                  <q>
                     <p>The Author reads [<gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>] the Almighties, and in <hi>Page</hi> 2.
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>In</hi> Mr. William Streat's <hi>Book cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, The dividing of the Hoof.</hi> Pag. 1.</note> ſpeaking of the oppoſition of <hi>Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>him,</hi> Almighties, which is a Noun Plural to the word <hi>Bara,</hi> he created, ſays thus; God's
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:32445:10"/>Phraſe, in a Dialect of his own, tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cending all humane Arts, purpoſely to amaze them in the Myſtery of the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, is one Thing.</p>
                     <p>Mans ordinary means of diſcovering earthly Things by Grammatical Rules in humane Learning, is another.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <q>This Hebraiſm is not uſed by <hi>Moſes</hi> (the Almighties Secretary) <hi>Penman</hi> of ſacred Truth, joyning a Verb Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular to a Noun Plural, for Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, but for Interpretation. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the word <hi>Bara</hi> [he created] is moſt fittingly and ſignificantly joyned to a Noun Plural, <hi>Elohim,</hi> Almighties; becauſe titling himſelf in a Plural Number, he might give us to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand a Plurality of Perſons, which are the three Perſons in the Trinity, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Son, and Holy Ghoſt; who wrought together in the Work of Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation.</q> And the Author further adds (<hi>Page</hi> 3.) that the Holy Trinity is here to be underſtood; and that becauſe the word <hi>God</hi> is not to be found in the Singular Number <hi>El,</hi> nor in the Dual as <hi>Elohaim,</hi> but in the Plural <hi>Elohim,</hi> as comprehending the three Perſons in the Deity. But ſome may ſay that the word
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:32445:11"/>
                     <hi>Elohim,</hi> proves rather three Gods, than three Divine Perſons in one Godhead. But note, that this is corrected by the Verb Singular, which betokens the Three to be One in Eſſence. And ſurely there is ſomething in this Hebraiſm, becauſe it anſwers ſo well to that which follows, <hi>ver.</hi> 26. <hi>And God ſaid, Let <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s make Man in Our Image, after Our Likeneſs,</hi> &amp;c: Mark the words [Us] and [Our] ſignify more than One Perſon: And though ſome may object that the Angels are here to be underſtood; yet this cannot be, for the Works of Creation were never attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to any Creatures. And as there are other Texts, <hi>Gen.</hi> 20.13. and <hi>ch.</hi> 35.7. <hi>Joſh.</hi> 24.19. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.23. ſee the Dutch-Annotations, in which the Hebrew word (<hi>Elohim</hi>) Almighties is found in the Plural Number, as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the word [Makers] <hi>Job</hi> 35.10. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12.1. So alſo in our Engliſh Tranſlation, there is a Concurrence in ſeveral other places of Scripture, with this of <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.26. as in <hi>ch.</hi> 11.7. where the Lord ſaid, <hi>Go to, let us go down, and there confound their Language.</hi> And <hi>Iſa.</hi> 6.8. <hi>The Lord ſaid, Whom ſhall I ſend, and who will go for us? &amp;c.</hi> Which pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:32445:11"/>denote a Plurality of Perſons in the Godhead.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Aſſerteth the Deity of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt by his Names.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>THAT the Father is God, is univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally owned by all Chriſtians. And therefore,</p>
                  <p>Having made ſome little Preparation, I now come to prove the Deity of the Son of God. That our Lord Jeſus Chriſt is not only Humane; but that he is alſo of the very ſame Spiritual Eſſence, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Subſtance of God the Father. And,</p>
                  <p>Firſt, I ſhall take notice of thoſe Names or Appellations, which are given to our Lord Jeſus Chriſt in the Holy Scriptures; for he is frequently called by thoſe Names which are properly applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to none but God; As, <hi>Mighty God, Iſa.</hi> 9.6, 7. applied to Chriſt, <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.31, 32, 33. <hi>Moſt Mighty, Pſal.</hi> 45.1 to 8. applied to Chriſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.8. <hi>Almighty, Rev.</hi> 1.8. with <hi>ver.</hi> 17, 18. <hi>Jehovah, Jer.</hi>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:32445:12"/>23.5, 6. Theſe are proper Names of God, and are applied to Jeſus Chriſt, who is often called God in the Holy Scriptures, as <hi>John</hi> 20.28. <hi>My Lord, and my God:</hi> and <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.8. <hi>But unto the Son he ſaith, Thy Throne, O God, is for ever and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</hi> Rom. 9.5. <hi>Whoſe are the Fathers, and of whom, as concerning the Fleſh, Chriſt came; who is over all, God bleſſed for ever.</hi> Amen. And though others may be called Gods, Yet <hi>unto us there is but one God,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.6. And what ever ſome may think (that would turn the current of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture another way) yet I cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that Jeſus Chriſt ſhould be ſo fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently called, by the higheſt Appellati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons God hath, in a relative Senſe only, and not as proper Names belonging to him, as a Perſon ſubſiſting in the ſame Nature; nor do I believe that his Name <hi>Immanuel,</hi> which is, God with us, <hi>Matth.</hi> 1.23. was given to him but as a ſuitable and deſcriptive Name, of both his Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, as real God in our Nature; He took Fleſh upon him, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.16. and <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.6, 7. <hi>He thought it not robbery to be equal with God: But made himſelf of no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, and took upon him the form of a Servant, &amp;c.</hi> Here are the two Natures of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:32445:12"/>Chriſt aſſerted, his Divine Nature, which only can be equal with God, and his Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane, both which do appropriate his Name <hi>Immanuel</hi> to him: and if his Names are proper to the Nature of God, we muſt then either admit of Jeſus Chriſt to be of the ſame Nature, or deny his Names to be proper to him.</p>
                  <p>Secondly; I ſhall prove the Deity of the Son of God, by three particular Scriptures, that relate to God in the Old Teſtament, and which are applied to Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt in the New: whereby it may appear, that (reſpecting his Divine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) he is one and the ſame with God.</p>
                  <p>Firſt Scripture is <hi>Zech.</hi> 14.3. <hi>Then ſhall the Lord go forth, and fight againſt thoſe Nations, as when he fought in the day of Battel.</hi> Ver. 4. <hi>And his Feet ſhall ſtand in that day upon the Mount of</hi> Olives, <hi>which is before</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>on the Eaſt,</hi> &amp;c. Ver. 5. <hi>And the Lord my God ſhall come, and all the Saints with thee.</hi> This Text, for its na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Affinity with the reſt of the Chapter, cannot be allegorized without groſs Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdity; but muſt be taken in a literal Senſe, of the coming of Chriſt with all his Saints. And it well agrees with what the Angel told the Diſciples, ſaying, <hi>that
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:32445:13"/>this ſame Jeſus which is taken up from you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Heaven, ſhall ſo come in like manner as you have ſeen him go into Heaven. Then returned they to</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>from the Mount called</hi> Olivet. This ſheweth that Chriſt aſcended into Heaven from the Mount of <hi>Olives,</hi> and that thither he ſhall deſcend again; and ſo it agrees with the Prophet. And as to the coming of the Saints, with the Lord, or <hi>Jehovah</hi> God, this alſo is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to Jeſus Chriſt. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.14. <hi>For if we believe that Jeſus died, and roſe again: even ſo them alſo which ſleep in Jeſus, ſhall God bring with him.</hi> chap. 3.13. <hi>At the coming of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt with all his Saints.</hi> So that he who is by the Prophet <hi>Zechariah</hi> called the Lord God, is by the Apoſtles called Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>Second Scripture is <hi>Zech.</hi> 12.10. <hi>And I will pour upon the Houſe of</hi> David, <hi>and upon the Inhabitants of</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>the Spirit of Grace and of Supplication, and they ſhall look upon me whom they have pierced, and they ſhall mourn for him,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, The Holy Ghoſt ſpeaketh of Chriſt in different Perſons, <hi>viz. [Me]</hi> and <hi>[Him]</hi> to betoken his different Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of God and Man, who being both, may be differently ſpoken of as a Perſon relating to either Nature.</p>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:32445:13"/>
                  <p>Secondly, This is confirmed by <hi>John, Rev.</hi> 1.7. in apylying the ſame to Chriſt only. And our Lord himſelf ſpeaks of this great Mourning; <hi>When they ſhall ſee the ſign of the Son of Man in Heaven, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with Power and great Glory.</hi> Mat. 24.30. So then (as it is apparent that the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Zechariah</hi>'s <hi>Jehovah,</hi> or Lord, in <hi>ver.</hi> 1. <hi>which ſtretcheth forth the Heavens, and layeth the Foundation of the Earth, and formeth the Spirit of Man within him,</hi> is that <hi>[Me] whom they have pierced, and Him they ſhall look upon and mourn for,</hi> viz. <hi>Jeſus Chriſt in the New Teſtament.</hi>) we muſt either admit Chriſt to be of the Divine Eſſence, or elſe confound the two Teſtaments.</p>
                  <p>Third Scripture is <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.13. <hi>Sanctify the Lord of Hoſts himſelf, and let him be your Fear, and let him be your Dread.</hi> Ver. 14. <hi>And He ſhall be for a Sanctuary; but for a Stone of Stumbling, and for a Rock of Offence to both the Houſes of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>for a Gin, and for a Snare to the Inhabitants of</hi> Jeruſalem.</p>
                  <p>This Text is applyed to Jeſus Chriſt in 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.6. <hi>Wherefore alſo it is contained in the Scriptures, Behold, I lay in</hi> Sion <hi>a chief Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner-Stone, elect, precious; and he that believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:32445:14"/>on him ſhall not be confounded.</hi> And this Corner Stone, which is Jeſus Chriſt, as the preceding Verſes ſhew, <hi>is a Stone of Stumbling, and a Rock of Offence,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ver.</hi> 8. So that comparing theſe two Scriptures together, they demonſtrate Jeſus Chriſt the Metaphorical Stone of Stumbling, and Rock of Offence, in the New Teſtament, to be the Lord of Hoſts <hi>[Himſelf]</hi> in the Old, <hi>viz. Jehovah,</hi> for ſo is the Word Lord in the Hebrew, in all the aforeſaid places in the Old Teſtament; which is an Eſſential Name of God, <hi>Whoſe Name alone is Jehovah,</hi> Pſal. 83.18. And therefore the Son of God is Co-eſſential with the Father.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, I ſhall prove the Deity of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt by ſeven particular Scriptures.</p>
                  <p>Firſt is, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.6. <hi>And the Lord God of the Holy Prophets, ſent his Angel to ſhew unto his Servants the things which muſt ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be done.</hi> Ver. 16. <hi>I Jeſus have ſent mine Angel, to teſtify unto you theſe things in the Churches.</hi> With <hi>Chap.</hi> 1.1. <hi>The Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Jeſus Chriſt, which God gave unto him, to ſhew unto his Servants things which muſt ſhortly come to paſs; and he ſent and ſignified it by his Angel unto his Servant</hi> John.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:32445:14"/>
                     <hi>God,</hi> viz. <hi>the Father,</hi> Rev. chap. 4. and chap. 1.5, 6, 7. with chap. 3.21. <hi>gave the Revelation to Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> and its ſaid, <hi>He,</hi> not the Father, <hi>ſent his Angel, to ſignify it unto his Servant</hi> John; and this Jeſus Chriſt is <hi>the Lord God of the Holy Prophets.</hi> And therefore he is the true Supream God by Nature.</p>
                  <p>The Second Scripture is <hi>Acts</hi> 20.28. <hi>Take heed therefore unto your ſelves, to feed the Church of God, which he hath purchaſed with his own Blood.</hi> 1st. The Blood that purchaſed or redeemed us, is the precious Blood of Jeſus Chriſt, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.18, 19. 2dly. If Jeſus Chriſt were but a Man, tho only made of a Woman, yet being the Seed, the Off-ſpring of the Fleſh of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid, Acts</hi> 2.30. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.16. the Perſon of a Man, his Blood would be the own proper Blood of that Perſon; and ſo it could not have ſuch a ſpecial Relation un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God: but as he was no Perſon, but by the aſſumption of the Divine Nature; ſo his Blood hath a ſpecial Relation (tho not natural) unto that Nature as it is part of Chriſt's Perſon, and without which he did not exiſt. Now this Blood, which is the Blood of Chriſt, being the own Blood of God, ſhews the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:32445:15"/>aſſumption of Humanity by his own Nature; and the like may be ſaid of the Life which God laid down for us, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.16.</p>
                  <p>Third Scripture is <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.5, 6, 7, 8. <hi>Let this Mind be in you, which was alſo in Christ Jeſus: who being in the form of God, thought it not robbery to be equal with God: But made himſelf of no Reputation, and took upon him the form of a Servant, and was made in the likeneſs of Men. And being found in faſhion as a Man, he humbled himſelf, and became obedient unto Death, even the Death of the Croſs.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Firſt; In this Scripture Chriſt is ſaid to be in the form of God, which is not only as Man by Creation, who beareth ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of his Image in the natural Qualities of the Soul, but in equality with God; ſo that in Nature he is not inferior to him, and therefore he can be no Creature: For there is no Creature that hath its being from God, can be equal to God.</p>
                  <p>Secondly; the Divine Nature of Jeſus Chriſt muſt be underſtood by his being in the Form of God: becauſe he did pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exiſt his Incarnation in that Form: his Condeſcention of mind, and his Power in that form, to take the form of a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:32445:15"/>went before his actual Condeſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in taking our Nature. <hi>Let this Mind be in you, which was alſo in Chriſt Jeſus. Who being in the form of God — made Himſelf of no Reputation.</hi> Which muſt be underſtood of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt's ſubſiſting in his Divine Nature before his Incarnation, in the form of God, and equal to Him.</p>
                  <p>4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Scripture, is <hi>John</hi> 5.26. <hi>For as the Father hath Life in Himſelf, ſo hath he gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the Son to have Life in Himſelf.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Firſt, For the Son to have Life in Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, is not to receive it from an higher Nature, for then he would have it in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, as Fellow-Creature with us, whoſe Nature and Perſonality have their Life and Being in God: But to have Life in Himſelf, is to have it in his own Nature, which cannot be if he were only Humane. <hi>Acts</hi> 17.28.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, For the Son to have Life in Himſelf, given or communicated to Him by the Father, denoteth the great Myſtery of his eternal Generation in the Divine Nature; for elſe the manner of Speech would be abſurd, and contradictory in it ſelf; for if it were given Him as a Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, he could not have it in Himſelf, and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:32445:16"/>if he have it in Himſelf, though it be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of the Father, he cannot be a Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; for that Nature which hath Life in it ſelf, muſt needs be the Nature of God, and this is the Nature of the Son.</p>
                  <p>Fifthly; <hi>John</hi> 10.30. <hi>I and my Father are One.</hi> This Text cannot ſimply be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, as if Chriſt and the Father were One only, even as we are one in Them: for Chriſt, ſpeaking of his Sheep in the 27, 28, and 29, <hi>Verſes,</hi> ſays, <hi>My Father which gave them me is greater than all, and none is able to pluck them out of my Father's Hand.</hi> Here Chriſt aſſerteth the greatneſs of his Father's Power, that he was greater than All, but yet ſaith, <hi>I and my Father are One;</hi> as if Chriſt ſhould ſay, As my Father is greater than all, So alſo I am greater than all; and his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing One in Power, ſhews him to be One in Nature with him. And thus the Jews underſtood our Lord, when they took up Stones to ſtone him, <hi>ver.</hi> 31. that he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Man, made himſelf God, <hi>v.</hi> 34, 35, 36. But Chriſt reproves their raſhneſs in charging him with Blaſphemy, looking on it as great Indignity, not to allow him any Supremacy above others they called Gods; in that they ſaid of him, whom
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:32445:16"/>the Father had ſanctified, — <hi>Thou blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemeſt, becauſe he ſaid, I am the Son of God.</hi> I queſtion not but 'the Jews would have born it well enough, though he ſhould have aſſumed the Name of God, ſo it were in the Senſe of their Law, like o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Men, <hi>ver.</hi> 34, 35. or of a Son of God, as they themſelves being Children of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,</hi> claimed God to be their Father: But their great quarrel with Chriſt was, that he ſo affirmed Himſelf to be the Son of God, as one and the ſame with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, equal to him in Power; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he is of the ſame Nature.</p>
                  <p>Sixth Scripture is 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.20. <hi>And we know that the Son of God is come, and hath given us an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, that we may know him that is True: And we are in him that is True, even in his Son Jeſus Chriſt. This is the true God, and eternal Life.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>What can be more plain to prove that the Son of God is the true God, than to have it ſo aſſerted of him? and can he be the true God, and not ſo by Nature, the very God, and but a Creature? If ſo, we muſt then acknowledg two Gods, the One the true God the Creator, the other the true God a Creature, which is repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to the Scripture: for there is none
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:32445:17"/>other God but One; <hi>for though there be that are called Gods, whether in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven or in Earth (as there be Gods many, and Lords many) But to us there is but one God,</hi> as before was ſhewed, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.4, 5, 6. And <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.8. there is an Exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of all from Divine Worſhip that are not God by Nature; and therefore if our Lord Jeſus Chriſt be the true God, he muſt then be of the One true Natural Godhead.</p>
                  <p>Seventh Scripture is <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 2.9. <hi>For in him dwelleth all the fulneſs of the Godhead Bodily.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Firſt; To imagine from this, or any other Scripture, that the Humane Nature of Chriſt comprehends the Deity, is to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive in our Minds, that of God which is inconſiſtent with his Immenſity and Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of Nature. Or,</p>
                  <p>Secondly, To ſay that the three Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Perſons in the Godhead, do perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally and equally after the ſame manner tabernacle in the Humane Nature of Chriſt, makes it common to all the three Subſiſtencies; ſo that the Father and the Holy Spirit, as well as the Son, would be incarnate: But this is contrary to the written Word of God, which declares to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:32445:17"/>us, the Son of God who is the brightneſs of his Glory, and the expreſs Image of his Perſon, that laid the Foundation of the Earth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That He it is that took Fleſh upon him. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.1, 2, 3, 8, 10. and <hi>ch.</hi> 2.14, 16. And all that Chriſt did by way of Atonement for us, and Reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation of God to us, is aſcribed to him as the Perſon of the Son of God only, and not as the Father, or the Holy Ghoſt, though in the Unity of Nature they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be excluded. But,</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, If we are neither to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand this Scripture, as if the Godhead were comprehended in Chriſt's humane Nature; nor that the three Divine Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons were equally incarnate, what then can be further propoſed as the meaning of it? But that the Perſon of the Son, or the Divine Nature of Chriſt ſubſiſting in the one whole Nature of God, hath all the fulneſs of that Nature dwelling in him, for there is no Diviſion of the whole Nature of God, with all its Eſſential Properties and Perfections from the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Perſons: for then neither the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture nor the Perſons could be Infinite or Immenſurable, but limited and ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed; and therefore there is a neceſſity
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:32445:18"/>that every Divine Perſon ſhould have the whole Divine Nature with all the Eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Attributes and Perfections of it, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be Omnipotency, Omnipreſency, Omniſciency, Immenſity, Eternity, Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the fulneſs of all is in every Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Perſon: they differ not in Nature, but in perſonal Properties: as the Father is not begotten like the Son, neither did the Son beget like the Father, nor alſo did either of them proceed like the Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; and ſo alſo in Office they differ the one from the other; but in Nature they are the ſame, and have all the ſame Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential Properties and Perfections, as was ſaid before.</p>
                  <p>So then all the fulneſs of the Godhead dwells bodily or ſubſtantially in the Perſon of the Son, that is, he hath the whole Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Subſtance or Eſſence of the Divine Nature, and by his hypoſtatical Union with the Humane Nature, the fulneſs of the Godhead may be ſaid alſo to dwell Bodily in the Humane Nature of Chriſt. So then, if all the Attributes and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of the Nature of God in their fulneſs dwell in our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, it is a ſufficient and undeniable Evidence of his Deity.</p>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:32445:18"/>
                  <p>But ſome may ſay that the Godhead dwells in Chriſt, after the ſame manner it dwells in us.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Tho it's ſaid, that <hi>we are the Temple of the Living God,</hi> and <hi>of the Holy Ghoſt that dwelleth in us,</hi> and <hi>that Jeſus Chriſt is alſo in us,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.19. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.16. <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.23. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.9, 10. Yet what is this to that Fulneſs which dwels in him? We indeed have Communion with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and the Son, <hi>through the Spirit,</hi> and are made <hi>partakers of the Divine Nature, Eph.</hi> 2.22. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4. but not after the ſame manner as Chriſt is: For the Holy Spirit hath his Union with us, by way of Fellowſhip with our Spirits, and unites himſelf in Communion with us. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.1. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.14. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.12. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.20. whereby we are guided by the teachings of him into all Truth, <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.13. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.18. But we have not our exiſtence in the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, as the Human Nature of Chriſt in the Divine Perſon of the Son; for we are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct human Perſons before, and after we are regenerated. But Chriſt did not exiſt but by Conception in the Divine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, in which he had his Being, and thereby a relation, by virtue of the Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtatical Union of the Son of God with
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:32445:19"/>his Human Nature, to all the Attributes and Perfections of the Divine Nature. And tho it's ſaid, that God the Father, and Chriſt, and the Holy Spirit dwelleth in us; yet I cannot find it was ever ſaid, that the fullneſs of the Godhead, or of the Nature of God, dwelleth in us: So that this Objection is of no force, to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw the ſufficiency of this Scripture to prove the Deity of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly; the Deity of our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, is proved by his Eternity; and as a Preparative hereunto, I ſhall firſt ſhew that he preexiſted his Incarnation.</p>
                  <p>And, Firſt, from <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.16. <hi>For verily he took not on him the Nature of Angels; but he took on him the Seed of</hi> Abraham. In the Margent of ſome of our Engliſh Bibles, it is read, <hi>He taketh not hold of Angels, but of the Seed of</hi> Abraham <hi>taketh he hold.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Firſt; This could not reſpect the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Seed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> for they were not ſuch when he firſt took hold of them.</p>
                  <p>Secondly; Nor is this <hi>taking hold</hi> to be underſtood only of the Poſterity of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> or literal People of the Jews; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:32445:19"/>this is but a light thing to the Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Gentiles, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.6. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, it is put in oppoſition to the nature of Angels, to that of ours; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his <hi>taking hold,</hi> or <hi>taking on him the Seed of</hi> Abraham, is a taking his Fleſh up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, <hi>ver.</hi> 14. <hi>Foraſmuch then as the Children are partakers of Fleſh and Blood, he alſo himſelf likewiſe took part of the ſame.</hi> So that this Text of Scripture hath a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial relation to his Incarnation; and in that he took on him the Seed or Fleſh of <hi>Abraham,</hi> it ſheweth that he not only came forth of his Loins, but that he did preexiſt the taking hold of that Seed; for he that taketh hold of a thing muſt needs preexiſt that act of taking hold.</p>
                  <p>The Second Scripture to prove the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exiſtency of Jeſus Chriſt to his Incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.17. <hi>Now therefore, O our God, hear the Prayer of thy Servant, and cauſe thy Face to ſhine upon thy Sanctuary that is deſolate, for the Lord's ſake.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As we cannot reaſonably imagine that this Lord ſhould be any other than <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi>'s Lord, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.11. with <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.42, 43, 44. <hi>viz.</hi> the Son of God: So alſo there is as little ground to believe, that the Prophet ſhould implore the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:32445:20"/>of God, for the ſake of one not in being: Becauſe it would have been more proper for him to have prayed to God for the ſake of his own gracious Promiſe of Mercy, than for his ſake, who was fore-appointed of God to make an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonement for our Sins, if he were not then exiſting in his Divine Nature. For as there could be no Promiſe on Chriſt's part, to undertake and perform the work of Atonement for us, whereby to ingage the Father to ſhew us Mercy; ſo neither could God be engaged for the ſake of one that was not then in being, to do or promiſe the performance of any Mercy. And therefore I humbly conceive, that from the Prophet's Prayer to God for the Lord's ſake, we may conclude that the Son of God (for whoſe ſake alone our Sins are forgiven) did then exiſt.</p>
                  <p>Third Scripture is, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.6, 7. <hi>Who being in the form of God, thought it not robbery to be equal with God: But made him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of no Reputation, and took upon him the form of a Servant, and was made in the like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Men.</hi> Theſe Words do ſhew, that Jeſus Chriſt was not made of no reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by another, but that he made him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſo. Whence note, he did preexiſt
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:32445:20"/>his Diſreputation, and that in the form of God, and equal to him: For if he was not (before he took the form of a Servant) in greater Dignity, how then could he make himſelf of no Reputation? So that it's evident our Lord Jeſus Chriſt did preexiſt his Incarnation.</p>
                  <p>Fourth Scripture is <hi>John</hi> 1.30. where the Evangeliſt ſaith, <hi>This is he of whom I ſaid, After me cometh a Man which is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred before me, for he was before me.</hi> As <hi>John</hi> was conceived at leaſt ſix Months before Chriſt; ſo alſo he began his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry before him: for Chriſt was Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed by him, and he did not preach the Goſpel, till after <hi>John</hi> was put in Priſon, <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.35, 36. <hi>Mark</hi> 19.14. <hi>Mat.</hi> 4.12, 18. And therefore ſeeing that <hi>John</hi> was before Chriſt, both in his Conception, and Miniſtry, wherein then was Chriſt before him but in his Divine Nature?</p>
                  <p>But if it ſhould be ſaid, that Chriſt was before <hi>John</hi> in the Purpoſe and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of God? It may be anſwered; That the Purpoſes and Decrees of God are as eternal as God Himſelf: and to admit of any real or abſolute Precedency of any thing in God, is repugnant to his infinite, eternal, and immutable Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:32445:21"/>and makes Him ſubject to Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents. So that it's undeniable our Lord Jeſus Chriſt did preexiſt his Incarnation. But not in the Nature of Angels.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, For though the Nature of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels is more excellent than Mans, yet nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for their excellency of Nature, nor any work it is capable of, could the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Works, Attributes and Perfections of God be aſcribed to it: for no Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture can be equal to the Creator, or have equal Attributes and Perfections to him: and therefore whatſoever is or may be applied to Chriſt, from the Word of God that is proper to the Holy Deity, could not be applied to him, if his Nature were not better and more excellent than the Angels.</p>
                  <p>Secondly; The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> in the firſt and ſecond Chapters to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> largely diſcourſes this Matter, and ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently proves that Chriſt is no Angel. Firſt, from <hi>chap.</hi> 1.4. <hi>Being made ſo much better than the Angels, as he hath by Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance obtained a more excellent Name than they.</hi> This Text doth not import, that only Chriſt's Name, obtained by the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance of his Kingly or Prieſtly Office, is more excellent than the Angels, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:32445:21"/>that his Nature is different from theirs: for the Apoſtle ſpeaks not of Chriſt and the Angels, in ſuch words or form of Speech, as might any ways inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate both Him and Them to be of the ſame Nature: as if he ſhould ſay, that Chriſt had obtained a more excellent Name than the <hi>reſt</hi> of the Angels had; but ſo as to demonſtrate that Chriſt is no Angel: for his Speech is comprehenſive of all the Angels, of their whole Nature; and excludes the Son of God from their Number. And this the Apoſtle inſiſts far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther upon, in the 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> and 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
                     <hi>Verſes</hi> of this Chapter: For after he had told us what the Son of God is, <hi>viz.</hi> That he is the brightneſs of his Father's Glory, and the expreſs Image of his Perſon, <hi>ver.</hi> 3. and that he is made better than the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, <hi>ver.</hi> 4. he moreover ſaith, <hi>For unto which of the Angels ſaid he at any time, Thou art my Son, this Day have I begotten Thee?</hi> And again, To which of the Angels ſaid he at any time, <hi>Sit on my Right Hand until I make thine Enemies thy Footſtool?</hi> No, it was to no Angel, but to the Son; who for his excellent Nature, above that of the Angels, is called God, <hi>ver.</hi> 8.</p>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:32445:22"/>
                  <p>Secondly; From <hi>chap.</hi> 2.16. <hi>For veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he took not on Him the Nature of Angels, but He took on Him the Seed of</hi> Abraham. This is meant of his Incarnation, as the 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Verſe (which relates to this) more fully ſhews; and then if His aſſuming our Nature, is put in oppoſition to his ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king on Him the Nature of Angels, it is a clear Demonſtration, that he preexiſted his Incarnation, in ſome other Nature than either of theſe. And to imagine that the Holy Apoſtle, who wrote by the Holy Ghoſt, ſhould affirm, that the Son of God did not aſſume the Nature of Angels, if he had before exiſted in it, would be an Imputation of Abſurdity to him, yea to the Holy Ghoſt, which is Blaſphemy. From all which it is appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, that Chriſt did not preexiſt his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation in the Nature of Angels, but, as it muſt follow, in the Divine Nature of God.</p>
                  <p>Secondly; I come to prove the Deity of the Son of God by his Eternity.</p>
                  <p>Firſt Scripture is, <hi>John</hi> 1.1. <hi>In the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning was the Word.</hi> Firſt, this Text is not to be underſtood of the preaching of the Goſpel by Jeſus Chriſt, or <hi>John</hi>
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:32445:22"/>the Baptiſt, for this was not a Myſtery fit to be ſet as a frontice-piece to <hi>John</hi>'s Book, nor is there any ſuch Intimation in the Words; and therefore it preceded that beginning. Secondly; He ſpeaks of that Beginning in which all Things were created, <hi>ver.</hi> 3. which ſhews that he did not only precede the preaching of the Goſpel, but the beginning of the Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and therefore he was from all Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</p>
                  <p>Second Scripture is, Iſa. 9.6. <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto us a Child is born, unto us a Son is given, and his Name ſhall be called — Everlaſting Father,</hi> or Father of Eternity, as is confeſſed by our Adverſaries:
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>See</hi> Biddle's <hi>Confeſſ.</hi> Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle 3.</note> If we read <hi>ver.</hi> 7. and compare it with <hi>Luke</hi> 1.31, 32, 33. we may ſee, that this Text is applied to our Lord Jeſus Chriſt; and if he be the Author of Eternity, he muſt Himſelf be Eternal.</p>
                  <p>Third Scripture is, Col. 1.17. <hi>And he is before all things.</hi> And ſo as that (in <hi>ver.</hi> 16.) <hi>All things were created by Him in Heaven and Earth, viſible and inviſible;</hi> which could not be ſaid of Chriſt, unleſs he were the Eternal God, exiſting from all Eternity.</p>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:32445:23"/>
                  <p>Fourth Scripture is, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.17, 18. <hi>Fear not, I am the firſt and the laſt; I am He that liveth, and was dead, and behold I am alive for evermore.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This Scripture cannot be applied unto any other but Jeſus Chriſt, who was dead, and is alive again; for though it was the Angel that ſpake, yet it was as repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting the Perſon of Jeſus Chriſt; and therefore whatſoever he ſaith in his own Perſon, muſt be applied to him; and this is manifeſted in <hi>ver.</hi> 8. <hi>I am</hi> Alpha <hi>and</hi> Omega, <hi>the Beginning and the Ending, ſaith the Lord, which is, and which was, and which is to come, the Almighty.</hi> And in <hi>ch.</hi> 2.8. where the Angel ſpeaks the ſame words, but not in the ſame Perſon he did before, ſaying, <hi>And unto the Angel of the Church in</hi> Smyrna, <hi>write, Theſe Things ſaith the Firſt and the Laſt, which was dead, and is alive again.</hi> Yea and in all the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtles to the Seven Churches of <hi>Aſia,</hi> he doth not only dictate them as from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother; but alſo, the ſame Deſcription that <hi>John</hi> gives of the Angel, the Angel applies to the Son of God, <hi>ch.</hi> 2.18. So that theſe Words, <hi>I am the Firſt and the Laſt,</hi> do relate unto Jeſus Chriſt: and as nothing can be firſt or preexiſt the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:32445:23"/>but the Divine Nature; So our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, as being the firſt, muſt preexiſt all things in the Nature of God.</p>
                  <p>Fifth Scripture to prove the Eternity of the Son of God is, <hi>John</hi> 17.5. <hi>And now, O Father, glorify Thou me with thy own Self, with the Glory which I had with Thee before the World was.</hi> If the Son were in Glory with the Father, before the World was, he was then exiſting before Time, and therefore from all Eternity, Coeſſential with the Father.</p>
                  <p>Fifthly; The Divinity of our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt is proved by his Works.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, from <hi>John</hi> 2.19, 21. <hi>Deſtroy this Temple, and in three days I will raiſe it up —But he ſpake of the Temple of his Body.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>We read of many mighty Works that were wrought by the Holy Apoſtles, but not in their own Names, or by their own Power: ſaith <hi>Peter, Acts</hi> 3.12. <hi>Why look you ſo earneſtly on us, as though by our own Power or Holineſs, we had made this Man to walk?</hi> And <hi>Moſes,</hi> for ſaying, <hi>Muſt we fetch Water out of this Rock?</hi> was ſhut out of the Land of <hi>Canaan, Num.</hi> 20.12, 19. For though God had given
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:32445:24"/>ſuch power to Men; yet he expected the Glory ſhould be given to him alone, as the Apoſtles did to Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>ver.</hi> 16. And ſurely if our Lord Jeſus had not been God equal with the Father in Nature, he had offended in aſſuming that Power to Himſelf, which is to be aſcribed to none but God; Who is ſaid <hi>to have raiſed him the third Day,</hi> Acts 10.40. So that the ſame Power which is aſcribed to God, the ſame doth our Lord Jeſus aſſume unto himſelf, and this demonſtrates him to be of the ſame Nature.</p>
                  <p>Second Scripture is, <hi>John</hi> 1.3. <hi>All things were made by Him; and without Him was not any thing made, that was made.</hi> And therefore the Word, or Son of God, <hi>ver.</hi> 14, 18. is the Eternal God and Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator of all Things.</p>
                  <p>Third Scripture is, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.16, 17. <hi>For by Him were all things created that are in Heaven, and that are in Earth, viſible and inviſible, whether they be Thrones or Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or Principalities, or Powers; all things were created by Him, and for Him: And he is before all things, and by Him all things conſiſt.</hi> It is not, neither could it be ſaid, that all things were renewed by the Son of God; for the good Angels had no
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:32445:24"/>need of it; and the Devils were not, neither were Men, ſave only a ſelect Number in part, but not wholly renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; for this cannot be until our Bodies are raiſed up from the Grave, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>united unto our Souls. Nay, the whole Creation was never yet renewed, but is groaning under the bondage of Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and waiting to be delivered into the glorious Liberty of the Sons of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.19, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And therefore this Scripture as it muſt of neceſſity be taken in its literal Senſe, ſo fully aſſerts the eternal Power and Godhead of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that I know not how its Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority can be evaded: for if all things were created and are upheld by him, and that becauſe (as the Apoſtle gives the reaſon) that he was before all things; then he muſt be the eternal God, Co-cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator with the Father.</p>
                  <p>Fourth Scripture is, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.10. <hi>And thou, Lord, in the Beginning haſt laid the Foundation of the Earth, and the Heavens were the Works of thy Hands:</hi> The word <hi>[And]</hi> connexes this Verſe with the preceding Words, and makes it relate to <hi>ver.</hi> 8. as if we ſhould read it thus, <hi>But unto the Son he ſaith, Thy Throne, O God,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:32445:25"/>is for ever and ever. And</hi> (to the Son he ſaith) <hi>thou, Lord, in the beginning haſt laid the Foundation of the Earth,</hi> &amp;c. And therefore he cannot be a Creature, but the Creator of all things.</p>
                  <p>Sixthly, The Deity of Jeſus Chriſt is proved by that Divine Worſhip and Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration given to him. None but God is to be worſhipped with Divine Worſhip; But the Son of God is to be worſhipped with Divine Worſhip; therefore he is God.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, to prove the <hi>Major</hi> in <hi>Matth.</hi> 4.10. <hi>It is written, Thou ſhalt worſhip the Lord thy God, and him only ſhalt thou ſerve.</hi> And <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.10. <hi>ch.</hi> 20.8. In both which places, when <hi>John</hi> fell down to worſhip the Holy Angel, he was forbidden, ſaying, <hi>See thou do it not; for I am thy fellow-Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant: worſhip God.</hi> And <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.8. <hi>How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit then when ye knew not God, ye did Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice unto them which by nature are no Gods.</hi> And <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42.8. <hi>I am the Lord, that is my Name; and my Glory will I not give to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> &amp;c. And <hi>chap.</hi> 48.11. <hi>For my own ſake, even for my own ſake will I do it, for how ſhould my Name be polluted? and I will not give my Glory unto another.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:32445:25"/>
                  <p>Now from theſe Scriptures, there is an Excluſion from Divine Worſhip of all that are not God by nature; and none is to be glorified, or worſhipped with the ſame Glory or Worſhip which belongs to God, but Himſelf only.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, to prove the <hi>Minor;</hi> That the Son of God is to be worſhipped with Divine Worſhip, <hi>Matth.</hi> 14.33. <hi>Then they that were in the Ship, came and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped him, ſaying, Of a truth thou art the Son of God.</hi> So in <hi>ch.</hi> 2.11. <hi>The wiſe Men worſhipped him:</hi> In <hi>chap.</hi> 8.2. <hi>The Leper worſhipped him:</hi> And in <hi>ch.</hi> 28.17. <hi>The Diſciples worſhipped him:</hi> and in many other places he was worſhipped, and he never forbad any. And therefore we have good reaſon to believe that it was due unto him as God: For when <hi>Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> fell down to worſhip <hi>Peter,</hi> he took him up and ſaid, <hi>Stand up, I my ſelf alſo am a Man.</hi> And ſo alſo in <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.10. and <hi>ch.</hi> 20.8. when <hi>John</hi> fell down to worſhip the Holy Angel, he was forbidden ſaying, <hi>See thou do it not; for I am thy fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-Servant, and of thy Brethren: worſhip God.</hi> So likewiſe if Chriſt had not been God by nature, he would not have ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Diſciples and others to have wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:32445:26"/>him, without rebuke for it. But to proceed.</p>
                  <p>There are other Scriptures of greater force, to prove that the Son of God is to be worſhipped with Divine Worſhip; as <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.6. <hi>And again, when he bringeth the firſt-begotten into the World, he ſaith, And let all the Angels of God worſhip him.</hi> And <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.8, 9. <hi>The four Beaſts,</hi> (or rather four living Creatures,) <hi>and four and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Elders, fell down before the Lamb</hi> (<hi>viz.</hi> Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 1.29.) <hi>having every one of them Harps and golden Vials full of Odours, which are the Prayers of Saints. And they ſang a new Song, ſaying, Thou art worthy to take the Book, and to open the Seals there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: For thou waſt ſlain, and haſt redeemed us to God by thy Blood,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Ver.</hi> 13. <hi>And every Creature which is in Heaven, and on the Earth, and under the Earth, and ſuch as are in the Sea, and all that are in them heard I ſaying, Bleſſing and Honour, and Glory and Power, be unto him that ſitteth up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Throne, and unto the Lamb for ever and ever.</hi> Ver. 14. <hi>And the four Beaſts</hi> (or living Creatures) <hi>ſaid, Amen, even ſo, Amen.</hi> Ch. 7.9. <hi>After this I beheld, and lo, a great number which no Man could num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of all Nations, and Kindreds, and People,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:32445:26"/>and Tongues, ſtood before the Throne, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lamb, and cryed with a loud Voice, ſaying, Salvation to our God which ſitteth upon the Throne, and unto the Lamb.</hi> So that our Lord Jeſus Chriſt is counted worthy of the ſame Divine Worſhip by all Creatures in Heaven and Earth, as God the Father, and hath the ſame Power as well as Honour and Glory aſcribed to him.</p>
                  <p>Thus I have proved both the <hi>Major</hi> and the <hi>Minor; viz.</hi> that none but God is to be worſhipped with Divine Worſhip.</p>
                  <p>That the Son of God is to be worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped with Divine Worſhip, and the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion follows, therefore he is God.</p>
                  <p>To what I have ſaid, by way of poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive proof, touching the Deity of Chriſt, I ſhall not further add, for there hath been given plentiful and ſufficient Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences from the Word of God, that our Lord Jeſus Chriſt has undeniable marks of the Divine Nature upon him; ſo that his Deity cannot be denied without ſubvert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Holy Scripture, which gives him the ſame Names, proves his Eternity, renders the ſame Worſhip, attributes the ſame Works, and aſſerts him the ſame as God the Father. And if we cannot know
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:32445:27"/>him as God by theſe Marks, by what can we know him then? And if theſe be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficient, how ſhall we know God the Father? For if the chiefeſt Marks of the Divine Nature that are found on our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, be no proof of his exiſting in the ſame Nature; we may then queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Deity of God the Father, who is only known and diſtinguiſhed from all Creatures by theſe and the like Attributes given to him, and Deſcriptions of him. So that I ſee no way to eſcape the power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful convincing Teſtimonies of this Truth, if there be but a ſearching after it, unleſs we deny the Authority of the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. V.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Wherein is proved the Deity of the Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>AS the Scriptures have given a clear Teſtimony to the Deity of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt; ſo alſo they will afford us ſufficient Evidence of the Deity of the Holy Spirit, which I intend to demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate in this Chapter. And,</p>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:32445:27"/>
                  <p>Firſt, I ſhall prove that the Holy Spirit is a Divine Perſon, and not a Quality in God.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, Our Lord Jeſus Chriſt ſpeaks of the Holy Ghoſt as a Perſon, <hi>John</hi> 14.16, 17. <hi>And I will pray the Father, and he ſhall give you another Comforter, that he may abide with you for ever: Even the Spirit of Truth, whom the World cannot receive, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it ſeeth him not, neither knoweth him: But ye know him, for he dwelleth with you, and ſhall be in you.</hi> Chap. 16.8. <hi>And when he is come, he will reprove the World of Sin.</hi> Ver. 13. <hi>Howbeit when he the Spirit of Truth is come, he will guide you into all Truth: for he ſhall not ſpeak of himſelf, but whatſoever he ſhall hear, that ſhall he ſpeak: and he will ſhew you things to come.</hi> In theſe Scriptures the words [<hi>He, Him,</hi> and <hi>Himſelf</hi>] are uſed to the Holy Spirit, and theſe all do note him to be a Perſon, and not a Quality.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, He is called <hi>the Comforter, John</hi> 16.7. which is a perſonal Name.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, He is put in the ſame rank with other Divine Perſons, as a Perſon, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19. <hi>Baptizing them in the Name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:32445:28"/>Holy Ghoſt.</hi> 1 John. 5.7. <hi>For there are Three that bear Record in Heaven, The Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the Word, and the Holy Ghoſt; and theſe three are one.</hi> Now from theſe Texts of Scripture, I ſhall make theſe three Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, That we may as well ſay, that the Father, and the Son are Qualities, as the Holy Spirit. And,</p>
                  <p>Secondly, The baptizing in the Name of the Spirit, denotes him to be a Perſon, as well as the Name of the Father and the Son, by their Names are ſo denoted.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, He cannot be a Quality; for if the Word and the Holy Ghoſt be Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, and the Father only a Perſon; or elſe the Father and Word Perſons, and only the Holy Ghoſt a Quality, yet the three can neither be one Perſon, nor one Quality.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, The Holy Ghoſt is a Perſon, and is ſo far from being a Quality in God, that he hath in himſelf the Quality of Knowing and Underſtanding: 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.11. <hi>Even ſo the things of God knoweth no Man, but the Spirit of God;</hi> and alſo of wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, <hi>John</hi> 16.7, 8. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.11. <hi>But all theſe worketh that one and the ſelf-ſame Spirit, dividing to every Man ſeverally as he
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:32445:28"/>will.</hi> And therefore the Holy Spirit having perſonal Qualities, is denoted to be a Perſon; and there is not the leaſt reaſon to believe but that the Holy Ghoſt is a Perſon, who is ſo generally treated of as a Perſon.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, The Holy Spirit is God from the Teſtimony of four ſeveral Scriptures.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, is <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19. <hi>Go ye therefore, and teach all Nations, baptizing them in the Name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> If the Holy Ghoſt were not God, why ſhould we be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized into his Name, and aſcribe unto him a ſhare in the Work of Man's Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? But that as the Father was pleaſed to elect and ordain the Son to lay our Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities upon him, and accept us in him; and as the Son was willing (as it were) to diſrobe himſelf of the Glory he had before the World was, to bear the Wrath of God, that was due to us for our Sins, that we might be delivered from it; and to reconcile him to us by the precious Blood of his Croſs: So the Holy Spirit changes our Hearts, and reconciles them to God, by infuſing into us a new Nature
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:32445:29"/>with Holy Diſpoſitions and Power againſt Sin, which the good Angels could never do: for though they have great Power to communicate to our Spirits, and influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence our Souls with good things; yet the evil Angels having the ſame Power of Nature, and being firſt in Poſſeſſion, may keep our Souls in Bondage, till one that is ſtronger, caſts them out, <hi>Luke</hi> 11.22. 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.4. And therefore the Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, having ſo great a hand in this glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Work, may rightly receive a ſhare with other Divine Perſons of our Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment of it, which demonſtrates that the Holy Ghoſt is God; for other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe we ſhould aſcribe that Work unto the Creature which is above the Power of its Nature, and is only poſſible for God himſelf.</p>
                  <p>Second Scripture is 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.16. <hi>Know ye not that ye are the Temple of God, and that the Spirit of God dwelleth in you?</hi> To have the Spirit of God dwelling in us, is to have our Bodies the Temple of the Holy Ghoſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.19. And the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Holy Ghoſt is the ſame as the Temple of God; and to ſay that the Temple of God is the Temple of a Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or to give it the Name of a Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:32445:29"/>is a Diſhonour to it, as not ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto God: And therefore the ſame Spirit or Holy Ghoſt that dwelleth in us, is God that dwelleth in us.</p>
                  <p>Third Scripture is 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.7. <hi>For there are three that bear Record in Heaven, the Father, the Word, and the Holy Ghoſt, and theſe three are one.</hi> This Scripture is ſo clear an Evidence for the Truth I am pleading for, that there have been ſome who would blot it out, denying its Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to be equal with other Scriptures, which I ſhall anſwer unto in its proper place.</p>
                  <p>But whereas it is ſaid, <hi>[and theſe three are one</hi>] it muſt be underſtood that they are one in Eſſence; for in <hi>ver.</hi> 8. where the Eſſences differ, the manner of ſpeaking alſo differs, <hi>[as agree in one] viz.</hi> in Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony; but in the Text it is <hi>[are one] viz.</hi> in Eſſence, as the Father, the Son, and the Holy Ghoſt, are not only one in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement of their Teſtimony, as the Blood, the Water, and the Spirit are, but are one in Eſſence. And this Diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was made in the two Verſes, that we might not miſs of the Truth of God in them.</p>
                  <p>Fourth Scripture is, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.17. <hi>Now
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:32445:30"/>the Lord is that Spirit: and where the Spirit of the Lord is, there is Liberty.</hi> Ver. 18. We <hi>are changed into the ſame Image from Glory to Glory, even as by the Spirit of the Lord,</hi> or (as it is in the Margent) <hi>Of the Lord the Spirit.</hi> Now if the Holy Spirit were not of the ſame Divine Eſſence, it could not be ſaid, the Lord is that Spirit.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly; I ſhall ſhew that the Holy Spirit is God by the Works of Creation that are aſcribed to him.</p>
                  <p n="1">1ſt. Job 33.4. <hi>The Spirit of God hath made me, and the Breath of the Almighty hath given me Life.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2dly. Job 26.13. <hi>By his Spirit he hath gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed the Heavens, his Hand hath formed the crooked Serpent.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3dly. Pſalm 104.30. <hi>Thou ſendeſt forth thy Spirit, they are Created,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p n="4">4thly. Gen. 1.1. <hi>And the Spirit of God moved upon the face of the Waters.</hi> The Spirit did co-create with other Divine Perſons, or Subſiſtences in the Deity: And therefore it is ſaid, <hi>That in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Gods</hi> (or the Almighties) <hi>created the Heavens and the Earth:</hi> Which Words, being incluſive of more than one Perſon, and the Spirit of God being ſaid to move
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:32445:30"/>upon the Face of the Waters; I think we may ſafely ſay, that the Holy Spirit did co-work with other Divine Perſons in the work of Creation, and was one of thoſe Perſons of whom it's ſaid, <hi>Let us make Man in our Image, after our Likeneſs,</hi> &amp;c. So that from theſe Scriptures it is clear, that the Holy Spirit did create, and therefore we cannot deny his Deity.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly; The Deity of the Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit is demonſtrated by what is aſcribed to him in the Conception of our Lord Jeſus, and by the Works that he accompliſhed, through the Power received from him.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, Jeſus Chriſt was conceived by the Holy Ghoſt. <hi>Luke</hi> 1.34. <hi>Then ſaid</hi> Mary <hi>unto the Angel, How ſhall this be, ſeeing I know not a Man?</hi> Verſ. 35. <hi>And the Angel anſwered, and ſaid unto her, The Holy Ghoſt ſhall come upon thee, and the Power of the Higheſt ſhall over-ſhadow thee: Therefore alſo that Holy Thing which ſhall be born of thee, ſhall be called the Son of God.</hi> And Matth. 1.18. <hi>Mary was found with Child of the Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>From both theſe Scriptures it appears that our Lord Jeſus was conceived by the Holy Ghoſt, the Power of the Higheſt,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:32445:31"/>which is God. Not that any ſhould ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine from hence, that every particular attribute in God are ſo many Perſons in the Godhead, but eſſential Properties of the One moſt high God, and, as ſuch, cannot be ſeparated from him: And therefore to aſcribe the Conception of Chriſt to the immediate Power of God, is to attribute it unto God, for all his Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes are ſo many deſcriptive Appellati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of him. And therefore ſeeing that the Power of the Higheſt is the Higheſt himſelf, and that the Holy Ghoſt is this Power which came upon <hi>Mary,</hi> and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhadowed her, then the Holy Ghoſt muſt be God. And he cannot be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe underſtood: for no created Spirit could produce a Child in the Womb of the Virgin <hi>Mary.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, It appears that the Holy Ghoſt is God, by the Works that our Lord Jeſus accompliſhed by him.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, He was anointed with the Holy Ghoſt to preach the Goſpel, <hi>Luk.</hi> 4.18. <hi>The Spirit of the Lord is upon me, becauſe he hath anointed me to preach the Goſpel to the poor,</hi> &amp;c. — <hi>With the Oyl of Gladneſs above his Fellows — for God giveth not the Spirit by meaſure unto him,</hi> Heb. 1.9. John 3.34.</p>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:32445:31"/>
                  <p>Secondly; Jeſus Chriſt caſt out Devils by the Spirit of God, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.28. <hi>But if I caſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Devils by the Spirit of God, then the Kingdom of God is come unto you.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thirdly; Our Lord Jeſus offered up himſelf unto God through the Spirit. Heb. 9.14. <hi>How much more ſhall the Blood of Chriſt, who through the eternal Spirit of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered himſelf without ſpot to God, purge your Conſciences from dead Works to ſerve the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now if our Lord Jeſus Chriſt have the ſame Nature in the Unity of Eſſence with God the Father, why ſhould he then at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute that Power, by which he caſt out Devils, and performed his Miniſterial Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice in preaching the Goſpel, and offering himſelf a Sacrifice to God for us, unto the Spirit, if he were but a Creature? For thus to exalt the Creature, would much eclipſe his own Power and Glorious Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. And therefore I cannot think, that all thoſe glorious Things ſhould be attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to the Holy Spirit, unleſs he were a Divine Perſon ſubſiſting in the Nature of God.</p>
                  <p>And foraſmuch as God hath ſaid, that <hi>He will not give his Glory to another,</hi> there cannot be any Colour of reaſon to deny
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:32445:32"/>the Deity of the Holy Ghoſt, unleſs we deny the Deity of Jeſus Chriſt. And ſeeing that his Deity is ſo plainly proved, that none can deny it, if they open their Eyes to the Light of the Holy Scriptures; and that the Deity of the Holy Ghoſt doth ſo naturally flow from it, that none can reject the one without the other; there is ground from hence, as well as from the preceding Evidence of the Holy Spirit's Deity, to believe that he is a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Perſon in the ſame Nature and Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, together equal with God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and the Son.</p>
                  <p>Fifthly; The Deity of the Holy Ghoſt is proved by the Divine Worſhip that is given to him.</p>
                  <p>As the Scriptures do demonſtrate the Holy Spirit to be a Divine Perſon ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting in the Nature of God; ſo to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God adequately aright, we muſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the Holy Spirit: for whether we worſhip God indefinitely, yet as the one Nature and Spiritual Subſtance of God, is the Nature and Subſtance of each Perſon, we therein do worſhip each Perſon; or whether we worſhip a Perſon by peculiar Attributions, proper to that Perſon; yet
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:32445:32"/>as the one Nature and Subſtance of the Deity, is the Nature and Subſtance of that Perſon, we therein do worſhip the Deity: So that we can neither exclude any one Perſon in the worſhipping of the Deity, or the Deity in the worſhipping of any one Divine Perſon, if we know what we worſhip. <hi>John</hi> 4.22. <hi>ch.</hi> 8.19. <hi>ch.</hi> 14.7, 8, 9. But,</p>
                  <p n="1">1ſt. To prove that the Holy Ghoſt is to be worſhipped with Divine Worſhip, I ſhall cite <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19. <hi>Baptizing them in the Name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> What is our being Baptized in the Name of the Holy Ghoſt, but our Acknowledgment of our Faith in him, and our yielding of due Obedience and Worſhip to him, as well as to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and the Son?</p>
                  <p n="2">2dly. The Holy Ghoſt is worſhipped with Divine Worſhip. Iſa. 6.1, 2, 3, 8, 9, 10. compared with <hi>Acts</hi> 28.25, 26, 27. The Prophet <hi>ſaw the Lord ſitting upon his Throne, high and lifted up, and his Train filled the Temple.</hi> Ver. 2. <hi>About it ſtood the</hi> Seraphims. Ver. 3. <hi>And one cryed unto ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſaid, Holy, Holy, Holy is the Lord of Hoſts, the whole Earth is full of his Glory.</hi> And the Lord bad the Prophet,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:32445:33"/>
                     <hi>ver.</hi> 9. <hi>Go and tell this People, Hear ye indeed, but underſtand not; and ſee ye in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, but perceive not.</hi> Now the ſame Lord that ſpake to the Prophet, and was worſhipped by the Seraphims, is ſaid to be the Holy Ghoſt in <hi>Acts</hi> 28. and from thence it appears, that the Holy Ghoſt is to be worſhipped with Divine Worſhip, and therefore he is God.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Wherein is proved the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Holy Trinity.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>FOraſmuch as it is manifeſtly declared in the Holy Scriptures of Truth, that there is but one God, and that the Father is God, the Son is God, and the Holy Ghoſt is God, it muſt then conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly follow, that theſe three are but one God.</p>
                  <p>And firſt, this is farther ſhewed, and declared to us by our being Baptized in the Name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19. for as theſe three are ranked together as Divine Perſons, ſo there is no reaſon to
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:32445:33"/>think that they ſhould differ in their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſeeing we aſcribe the great work of Salvation to all of them: And ſurely if Chriſt and the Holy Spirit were inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental in our Salvation, only as Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures under God the Father, they would not be ranked together with him as the efficient Cauſe: For the Holy Angels, though they are all Miniſtring Spirits ſent forth to miniſter for them, who ſhall be Heirs of Salvation; yet are we not required in any Church-Ordinance to acknowledg their Service in honour to them, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.14. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.10. For though we are exhorted to ſuch a Holy Behaviour, as that we might not prevent, or diſturb them in their Miniſterial Work and Office, yet the Glory of all is to be given to God alone, <hi>viz.</hi> to Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Son, and Holy Ghoſt: and the reaſon to me is plain, becauſe the Angels are of a lower Nature; otherwiſe it were not irrational to believe, that if the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels were equal in Nature to Chriſt and the Holy Spirit, though lower in Office, they ſhould have a ſhare proportionable in the Attributions of Protection and Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. Beſides, the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit are ranked together,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:32445:34"/>becauſe theſe three only are Omniſcient and Omnipreſent: <hi>Do not I fill Heaven and Earth, ſaith the Lord?</hi> not only the Father, but alſo the Son and the Holy Spirit. For they created all things, as hath been ſhewed, and therefore they know all things. <hi>He that teacheth Man Knowledg, ſhall not he know?</hi> And, <hi>whither ſhall I go from thy Spirit,</hi> &amp;c. Or, <hi>whither ſhall I flee from thy Preſence,</hi> &amp;c. And Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Where two or three are ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together in my Name, there am I in the midſt of them;</hi> And, <hi>Lo, I am with you always, even unto the end of the World. Jer.</hi> 23.24. <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.20. chap. 28.20. <hi>Pſalm</hi> 139.7 to 14. <hi>Pſalm</hi> 94.10, 11. If any ſay, that Chriſt means only, that his Doctrine ſhall continue among the Faithful that congregate in his Name; or, as <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.17. To <hi>dwell in our Hearts by Faith, viz.</hi> in his Doctrine. It is anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, That not ſimply his Doctrine as it is mixt with Faith, in its abſtract from inward feeling, is here to be underſtood; but ſome other preſence of Chriſt with his People; for he ſaith, John 14.23. <hi>If a Man love me, he will keep my Words, and my Father will love him, and we will come unto him, and make our abode with him.</hi>
                     <pb n="57" facs="tcp:32445:34"/>Where note, that to ſuch as have already received his Word by Faith in the love of it, and keep it, he hath promiſed a further Preſence: And what can it be, but the inward ſenſation or feeling of his Love? as ſometimes we have, <hi>Rom</hi> 5.1 to 6. tho at other times we have not, <hi>Job</hi> 13.15. ch. 23.8 to 11. But they may further ſay, If this be the Preſence of Chriſt you ſpeak of, it is not his perſonal Preſence, but by the Spirit, which is called the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Faith, that ſheddeth the Love of God abroad in our Hearts. To this I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, True, it is not the perſonal Preſence of Chriſt, either as God-Man, or of the Divine Perſon of the Son, but as in and through the Spirit; which will prove what is denied by them, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Holy Spirit is God, yea, and the Son alſo. For the Office of the Spirit is uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal to all Saints, throughout the World, at the ſame inſtant time, which is beyond the power of any finite Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; indeed Satan deceives the World, but not by an infinite Preſence, at the ſame time in every place, but by a finite perſonal going to and fro, and walking up and down in it, ſeeking whom he may devour, being aſſiſted by his evil Angels,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:32445:35"/>
                     <hi>Job</hi> 1.7. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.8. And as the Holy Spirit by his Office muſt be Omnipreſent; So alſo the Son as well as the Father is Omnipreſent, in and through the Spirit with the Saints in all places, and in and with all Perſons, Places and Things what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever; though not by the ſame Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations or Operations, yet at the ſame inſtant Seaſon: and as the Father is Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipreſent in and through the Spirit, ſo I ſee not the leaſt reaſon why we ſhould deny it to the Son; but underſtand his Preſence in the ſame ſenſe, ſeeing both are preſent in the Unity of the ſame Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. For, <hi>know ye not that ye are the Temple of God, and that the Spirit of God dwelleth in you?</hi> As God hath ſaid, <hi>I will dwell in them, and walk in them:</hi> And <hi>he that is joined to the Lord, is one Spirit</hi> with the Father, and the Son, for the Holy Ghoſt is called, <hi>The Spirit of our Father — that ſpeaketh in us, and the Spirit of the Son, ſent forth into our Hearts, crying, Abba, Father:</hi> And the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit which is upon Chriſt ſhall not depart out of his Mouth, nor out of the Mouth of his Seed — nor of his Seed's Seed, from henceforth, and for ever: and if any Man have not the Spirit of Chriſt, he is none of his, and by our Communion
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:32445:35"/>with the Holy Ghoſt, we have Fellowſhip with the Father, and his Son Jeſus Chriſt, and are one in them, and they will come and make their abode with us, through that one Spirit, whereby we are joyned unto the Lord. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.16. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.16. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17. <hi>Mark</hi> 13.11. <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.20. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.6. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59.21. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.14. 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.3. <hi>John</hi> 17.21. <hi>chap.</hi> 14.23. And it is comfortable for us to believe, that greater is he that is in us, than he that is in the World, 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.4. Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe what may the Soul ſay when he is in trouble: Surely, I fear, that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the fulneſs of the precious Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, and the great Engagements of Chriſt to me, that Chriſt and the Holy Spirit are far from me, and are buſied with other Saints, and know not my Diſtreſs; and therefore I may periſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they come to help me. But bleſſed be God, that hath laid help upon one that is Mighty, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.19. who is able to ſave to the uttermoſt all that come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God by him, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.15. that knoweth all our open and ſecret Wants, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.23. and makes Interceſſion for us: And as for the Holy Spirit, our Bodies are the Temple of the Holy Ghoſt that dwelleth
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:32445:36"/>in us, that abides with us for ever; though his Operations may ſometimes ceaſe, when he is grieved by us; 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.19. <hi>John</hi> 14.16. So that the Holy Ghoſt is not as one that cometh but now and then to viſit our Souls, but he makes his conſtant a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bode in us, and ſo is always ready to mortify and ſanctify our vile Natures, and make them meet to have Fellowſhip with the Father, and with his Son Jeſus Chriſt, 1 <hi>Jo.</hi> 1.3. And this is a Chriſtian's Mercy, that as none is able to pluck him out of Chriſt's Hands, ſo the greateſt Corruptions are not able to withſtand the powerful Sanctifyings of the Holy Spirit. Satan may withſtand an Holy Angel of God; for his Fall doth not deprive him of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Power of an Angel: but yet he cannot withſtand Chriſt nor the Holy Spirit, becauſe of the Potency of their Nature, <hi>John</hi> 10.28, and 30. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.13. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.4 to 7. <hi>Dan.</hi> 10.13. <hi>Jude</hi> 9. and we may ſay in this caſe, as <hi>John</hi> did concerning the ſealed Book, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5. That none in Heaven nor on Earth, nor under the Earth, was found worthy beſides the Son and the Holy Spirit, to redeem and ſanctify the fallen Sons of <hi>Adam:</hi> The An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels could not do it, for they are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holden
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:32445:36"/>to Chriſt for their ſtanding, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.26. But bleſſed be God our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, for in him <hi>ſhall all the Seed of</hi> Iſrael <hi>be juſtified, and ſhall glory,</hi> Tit. 2.10. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.25. To whom be Glory and Praiſe now and for evermore, <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>So then if we aſcribe and acknowledg the Work of Mans Salvation to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the Son, and the Holy Ghoſt, which are ranked together, as the effici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Cauſe, and therefore receive the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of it: and ſeeing both the Father and the Son dwells in us, in and through the Holy Spirit, whoſe Office in his Omnipre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence beſpeaks his unlimited and infinite Nature; I cannot conceive but that the great Unity of theſe three Subſiſtencies ſhould be in Eſſence.</p>
                  <p>Secondly; The Unity of the Holy Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity is manifeſt from <hi>Iſa.</hi> 6.23. where the Seraphims cried one unto another and ſaid, <hi>Holy, Holy, Holy is the Lord of Hoſts;</hi> agreeable to <hi>Rev.</hi> 4.8. Now here are three Holies, <hi>viz.</hi> Holy Father, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Son, and Holy Ghoſt: and though I do not lay the ſtreſs of the proof on the bare repetition of the word Holy; yet doubtleſs it ecchoes to the Truth that is couched in this Chapter, and which I hope
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:32445:37"/>to demonſtrate by the help of other places referring to it. And in order thereunto I ſhall note who the Prophet ſaw upon his Throne, high and lifted up, whoſe Train filled the Temple: And this was <hi>Jehovah</hi> (an incommunicable Name of God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 83.19.) the Lord of Hoſts, who filleth the whole Earth with his Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, but this was not only the Father, but alſo the Son and the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
                  <p n="1">1ſt, That it was the Father, needs no proof, becauſe it is not denied, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed by our Adverſaries in oppoſition to the other two Divine Perſons.</p>
                  <p n="2">2dly, That this Viſion is applied to the Son, we have the Words of the Apoſtle for it, <hi>John</hi> 12.41. who ſpeaking of Chriſt from verſe 37 to 40. and citing the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah's Meſſage,</hi> when he ſaw this Viſion, ſaith, <hi>Theſe things ſaid I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaias, when he ſaw his Glory, and ſpake of him, viz.</hi> of Chriſt, whom <hi>John</hi> was ſpeaking of.</p>
                  <p n="3">3dly, This Scripture is alſo applied to the Holy Ghoſt in <hi>Acts</hi> 28.25, 26. as hath been ſaid already, and will be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended in its proper place. So that if we will credit the Holy Apoſtles, who were doubtieſs the beſt Expounders and Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:32445:37"/>of dark Prophecies; and have unfold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Myſtery of the Holy Trinity which lay hid in the Words, <hi>Holy, Holy, Holy,</hi> and couched in the Plurality of Perſons, hinted to us in theſe Words, <hi>Who ſhall go for us?</hi> ver. 8. Then ſurely we muſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg that ſeeing the Prophets <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hovah,</hi> and the Apoſtles <hi>Son</hi> and <hi>Holy Spirit,</hi> are one and the ſame; that theſe two are Divine Subſiſtencies as well as the Father, ſubſiſting in the ſupream Nature of God.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, If we couple together <hi>John</hi> 10.30. and 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.17. <hi>I and my Father are one.—The Lord is that Spirit;</hi> we may ſee that the Father, the Son, and the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit, are but one God.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, <hi>John</hi> gives ſo clear a Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony to the Unity of the Holy Trinity, that I know not how it can be denied, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.7. <hi>For there are three that bear Record in Heaven, the Father, the Word, and the Holy Ghoſt, and theſe three are one</hi> in Eſſence, as was ſhewed before.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:32445:38"/>
                  <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Containeth ſome Explications of the Holy Trinunity.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>FIrſt,</hi> Of the eſſential Being of God.</p>
                  <p>God is one ſingle, infinite, eternal, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſe, perfect, ſpiritual Being, no Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound, for Compounds muſt be either fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite or infinite; not of Finites, for Finites are imperfect, temporal and menſurable, and ſo cannot make one infinite perfect Being; not of Infinites, for more than one infinite Being cannot ſubſiſt, for one infinite Immenſity cannot admit of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther infinite Immenſity, nor is infinite Perfection excluſive, but comprehenſive of all Perfection.</p>
                  <p>Hence it is that we muſt not imagine God to have any ſhape, becauſe an Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Being cannot be any ways limited or ſubſcribed. <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.12, 15. <hi>John</hi> 4.24. <hi>Deut.</hi> 33.27. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 147.5. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 90.2.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> Of a Divine Perſon.</p>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Chynel</hi> in his Divine Trinunity, <hi>Page</hi> 96. deſcribes a Divine Perſon. <q>A
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:32445:38"/>Divine Perſon is a ſpiritual and infinite Subſiſtent, related indeed to theſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther uncreated Perſons, which ſubſiſt in the ſame Divine Nature with it, but diſtinguiſhed from thoſe co-eſſential Perſons, by its peculiar manner of Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence, Order of ſubſiſting, ſingular Relation and incommunicable Proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Of the Divine Perſon of the Father.</p>
                  <p>The Divine Perſon of the Father is unbegotten, and ſubſiſts of himſelf in the Divine Eſſence, and hath the Divine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of none.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Of the Divine Perſon of the Son.</p>
                  <p>The Divine Perſon of the Son is natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally and neceſſarily begotten of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, by eternal Generation, for he is E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal, as hath been ſhewed, and is of the Father, <hi>John</hi> 5.26. by eternal Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and he ſubſiſts in the unbegotten Nature of God; for the Father did not beget the Divine Nature of the Son, but the Son is begotten in the Divine Nature.</p>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:32445:39"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fifthly,</hi> Of the Divine Perſon of the Spirit.</p>
                  <p>The Divine Perſon of the Spirit hath his Subſiſtence, naturally and neceſſarily both from the Father and the Son, by eternal Spiration or Emanation, <hi>Job</hi> 33.4. and therefore the Holy Ghoſt is called the Spirit of Chriſt, who breathed on his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples, and bid them receive the Holy Ghoſt, to ſhew that the Spirit was breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed forth by him as well as from the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>John</hi> 20.22. <hi>John</hi> 15.26. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.11. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.21. not from the Father alone, or the Son alone, for then he might be ſaid to be the Son of the Father, or of the Son, but by the Father and the Son, and not being ſeparated or divided from either, he ſubſiſts in the ſame Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and is co-eſſential with them both.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sixthly,</hi> Of the Unity of the Holy Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</p>
                  <p>The Divine Nature is common to all three Subſiſtencies, and the whole Divine Nature is the Subſtance of every Perſon which diſtinctly ſubſiſts in it; and all its eſſential Properties pertain unto each of them, and the Divine Nature, becauſe it
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:32445:39"/>is infinite in Perfection, it contains all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative as well as abſolute Perfections.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Seventhly,</hi> Of the Diſtinction between the Divine Nature and the Perſons.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall cite Mr. <hi>Chynel</hi> in his Divine Trinunity; Page 105, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <p>Firſt, The Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, do all three <hi>really, poſitively, truly,</hi> ſubſiſt in the Divine Eſſence; and yet theſe three Subſiſtencies, and the Divine Eſſence, do not make <hi>four,</hi> no nor two <hi>things really diſtinct;</hi> even as Entity, Truth, Goodneſs, and Unity, do not make four things really diſtinct, as you heard but now, but are one real thing, and no more.</p>
                     <p>Secondly, <hi>Ens</hi> is not compounded of Entity, and its three Affections; nor is God compounded of the Godhead, and three Subſiſtencies; nor is any one Perſon compounded of the Divine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Subſiſtence.</p>
                     <p>Thirdly, As Truth is not Goodneſs, nor Goodneſs Truth, nor either of them Unity, and yet all three are En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity: So the Father is not the Son, nor is the Son the Father, nor is either of them the Holy Ghoſt, and yet all three
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:32445:40"/>are God; <hi>for they are all three but one God, ſubſiſting with all abſolute and rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Perfection,</hi> as hath been ſhewed.</p>
                     <p>Fourthly, Every one of the three Affections of <hi>Ens,</hi> doth connote Enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: every one of the three Subſiſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies doth connote the Godhead, the Divine Nature, as hath been proved at large.</p>
                     <p>Fifthly, Not any one of the three Affections of <hi>Ens,</hi> doth, nor do all three together, ſuperadd a new Enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; not any one of the three Subſiſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies doth, nor do all three together ſuperadd a new Deity, a new Divine Nature, or Godhead: for <hi>Ens</hi> is one; <hi>Ens eſt trinum, non triplex, trinum &amp; unum, Ens trin-unum, Deus eſt trinus, non triplex, trinus &amp; unus, Deus trin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unus;</hi> this inſtance doth in ſome Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure reſemble the Myſtery of the Trin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unity.</p>
                     <p>Sixthly, No Affection of <hi>Ens</hi> can be really ſeparated from <hi>Ens,</hi> nor can one of the Divine Perſons be ſeparated from the Divine Nature, or the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Nature from any one of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Perſons, or any one of the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons from either of the other two.</p>
                     <pb n="69" facs="tcp:32445:40"/>
                     <p>Seventhly, All the Affections of <hi>Ens</hi> are diſtinguiſhed, but none divided: all the three Subſiſtencies are <hi>diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> but they cannot be <hi>divided.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Eighthly, Truth and Goodneſs, which are two of the Affections of <hi>Ens,</hi> are diſtinguiſhed by their peculiar and ſeveral Relations; Truth hath Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Underſtanding, and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to the Will: The Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt are <hi>known</hi> to be diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed by their ſeveral and peculiar Relations; and if it be not unreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſay, that there is in Entity three Affections, and two Relations in <hi>Ente ſimpliſſimo,</hi> without any Compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition in, or Multiplication of the Entity, why ſhould it ſeem unreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, or at leaſt why ſhould it ſeem in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible, <hi>that there are three Subſiſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and ſeveral Relations in the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head without any Compoſition in, or Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplication of the Godhead?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Ninthly, One Affection, nay all the Affections <hi>in abſtracto,</hi> do but inade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quately repreſent <hi>Ens,</hi> unleſs you take notice of the Entity it ſelf, as well as the three Affections. One ſingle Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence, nay all three Subſiſtencies <hi>in
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:32445:41"/>abſtracto,</hi> do but inadequately repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent God, unleſs you take notice of the Godhead in which they ſubſiſt; and therefore this <hi>preciſive Abſtraction of the Subſiſtencies from the Divine Nature, is but an inadequate Conceit of God,</hi> as hath been demonſtrated above in this very Chapter; for we muſt not dream of a <hi>Trinity of Modes,</hi> but aſſert and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the glorious and <hi>co-eſſential Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</hi> The Father is truly God, that God who is the only true God; but the <hi>Father alone doth not adequately re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent God to us, as he is deſcribed in the Holy Scriptures.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>It is true that the Divine Eſſence is by the Subſiſtence of the Father, <hi>ade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quately the Father;</hi> but as God is repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented by that Divine Subſiſtence <hi>only,</hi> he is not <hi>Deus Trinunus,</hi> he is not the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt; <hi>The Father alone, is not all theſe three Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes who are one God.</hi> And therefore the acute Socinians, with their preciſe Abſtractions, do but ſuggeſt an <hi>inade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quate Conceit</hi> of God: That only true God, whom we worſhip, doth not ſubſiſt <hi>only</hi> in the Perſon of the Father. <hi>We worſhip God, ſubſiſting with all abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:32445:41"/>and relative Perfection in Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt;</hi> for theſe three are that one God, who is the only true God bleſſed for ever. <hi>This is the ade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quate Repreſentation of God in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of Truth.</hi> And we are reſolved to regulate all our Metaphyſical Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons by the Holy Scriptures, that we may make the higheſt of Sciences to acknowledg the Supremacy of that Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Science which is no where to be learnt but in the Word of God; for the pureſt Reaſon muſt be elevated by the Word and Spirit of God, for the diſcovery of this Myſtery.</p>
                     <p>Tenthly; Theſe Affections of <hi>Ens</hi> repreſent the manner of that Being, which <hi>Ens</hi> hath as it is tranſcendently conſidered; and the three Divine Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtencies do repreſent that manner of Being, which God hath as he is moſt tranſcendently conſidered, namely as ſubſiſting, after the moſt glorious Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, with all abſolute and relative Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection.</p>
                     <p>It is the manner of a tranſcendent Entity to be one, and true, and good, and <hi>it is the manner of God's Being, to be one God in three Subſiſtencies;</hi> theſe three
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:32445:42"/>are one ſingle God, there is no Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, or Multiplication imaginable, in this ſingle and infinite Being.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>When I read this Similitude, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Light it gave into this Myſtery, I thought it worth my time to convey it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to others out of this learned Author; and I doubt not, but (if well conſidered) theſe rare Diſtinctions of the Divine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and the Perſons, will be profitable. For as the Author ſaith, <q>When Divine Revelation hath gone before, and we have built upon that as the Ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>work and Foundation, by a ſerious Faith, theſe Metaphyſical Notions may be ſubſervient helps in a ſubordinate way. And if there might be ſo great Simplicity or Singleneſs in a created and finite Entity, notwithſtanding there are three Affections, and two Relations which do affect that Entity; it ſeemeth to me ſomewhat eaſy to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve <hi>that there are three Subſiſtencies in one infinite Godhead, without any Compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition in, or Multiplication of the ſingle Godhead.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Eſtwick</hi> in his Confutation of <hi>Biddle</hi>'s Confeſſion of Faith, <hi>Pag.</hi> 17. doth give (among other Reſemblances of the Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty)
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:32445:42"/>an inſtance of the Soul and its Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, ſaying, <q>If they are (as <hi>Scotus</hi> and his Followers, <hi>Zanchius</hi> and <hi>Scali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,</hi> and others do maintain) one thing, for then there is not a real Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition betwixt the Soul and the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties of it.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <q>Memory in the Soul is the beginning of the Knowledg begotten in it, and ſo it repreſents the Father. By Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence is repreſented the Son, becauſe he is as Knowledg begotten of his Father. By Memory, and the Will, is repreſented the Holy Ghoſt.</q> (This is ſome over-ſight in the Author, or Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror in the Printer: for it ſhould be thus,) <q>Of Memory and Intelligence proceeds the Will, which repreſents the Holy Spirit,</q> (and ſo it agrees with what follows;) <q>becauſe he is alone pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced of the Father and the Son; theſe are diſtinct, yet one in Eſſence. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt. lib.</hi> 15. <hi>de Trinitate,</hi> cap. 20. <hi>Radu.</hi> pag. 2. <hi>Controv.</hi> 13. <hi>Art.</hi> 2. This Compariſon (ſaith he) I confeſs is too ſhort, for neither are the Facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Soul Perſons, nor doth there appear in them ſuch a ſtrange and wonderful manner of Production, as in
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:32445:43"/>the glorious Perſons of the Bleſſed Trinity: This doth our Faith with Admiration apprehend, which our Knowledg cannot attain unto.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <q>To conclude (ſaith he) the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſes ſhew that this great Myſtery is not againſt Reaſon, though it be above Reaſon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Eighthly; Of the Union of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of God, and of Man, in one Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
                  <p>Of this I ſhall cite <hi>Eſtwick</hi> in his Confutation of <hi>Biddle</hi>'s Confeſſion of Faith, <hi>pag.</hi> 115. <q>Suppoſe an Apple-Tree grow up, into which the Branch of another Tree is ingrafted, which makes not the Tree to be of a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound or middle Nature, but cauſing the Branch, which being ſet into the Ground, might have proved an intire Tree of it ſelf, to pertain to the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Tree into which it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted, and yet retains its own Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and bears its own Fruit; and as you may truly ſay, this Harvy-Tree is a Pippin-Tree, and this Pippin-Tree is a Harvy-Tree; and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently this Harvy-Tree beareth Pip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pins,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:32445:43"/>and this Pippin-Tree brings forth Harvies. So may we ſay of the Perſon of Chriſt, conſiſting of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of God and Man: The Son of God, who was a compleat and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Perſon, hath added to it the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature in the Unity of the ſame Perſon; as the Divine Nature of our Saviour, notwithſtanding the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal Union, is not capable of any hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Imperfections, no more is the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature (in that reſpect a finite Creature) capable of any Divine and infinite Perfection; the weakneſs and infirmity of Man was not ſwallowed up in the Majeſty of God, nor was God's Majeſty in the leaſt diminiſhed really by the Aſſumption of Man. The Union of the Word, in regard of the Perſons ſubſiſtence, graciouſly beſtowed on the humane Nature, is not finite, nor the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature infinite: and as the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named Tree is but one, and yet has two different Natures in it, and beareth two kinds of Fruits; ſo the Holy Son of God is but one Perſon, and yet hath two different Natures, and by them performeth the diſtinct Operations pertaining to either of them.</q>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:32445:44"/>
               <head>PART. II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Wherein the Proof of the Holy Trinunity, in the former part of this Treatiſe, is defended againſt the chiefeſt Objections and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments of the Adverſaries.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THERE are many Objections made, and of divers kinds, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this Doctrine; ſome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt its Scriptural Proofs; and others inferred from divers Texts of Scripture, beſides thoſe which are offered againſt it as inconſiſtent to Reaſon. To which I ſhall make replies in order.</p>
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:32445:44"/>
                  <head>CHAP. I.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>In which I ſhall anſwer thoſe Objections I find againſt the Scriptural Proofs of the Deity of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>FIRST Objection unto <hi>Gen</hi> 1.26. and to other Places alſo, which are cited to prove a Plurality of Divine Perſons in the Godhead: We might by the ſame kind of arguing conclude, that becauſe Chriſt in <hi>Mark</hi> 4.30. ſaith, <hi>Whereunto ſhall we liken the Kingdom of God? or with what compariſon ſhall we compare it?</hi> and <hi>John</hi> 3.11. <hi>Verily, verily, I ſay unto thee, We ſpeak that we do know, and teſtify that we have ſeen, and ye receive not our Witneſs:</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there are ſeveral Perſons in Chriſt. And alſo in <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.1, 2. The utmoſt that can be concluded from this paſſage in <hi>Geneſis,</hi> is, That there was ſome other Perſon with God whom he employed in the Creation, which Perſon had been before mentioned by <hi>Moſes,</hi> Ver. 2. with <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104.30. <hi>Job</hi> 26.13. <hi>ch.</hi> 33.4. Theſe Scriptures do plainly intimate, that the Spirit was but the Inſtrument of
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:32445:45"/>God in creating Things, it was he only (<hi>which he ſaith is an Angel:</hi>) For had the Son of God, Chriſt Jeſus, been alſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in creating of <hi>Adam,</hi> would he not have been likewiſe mentioned in the Hiſtory of the Creation?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Firſt, It doth not from hence follow, that becauſe Chriſt and <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeak of themſelves, and others with them in the plural Number, that there is the ſame Reaſon to conclude, that there are ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Perſons in Chriſt, and in <hi>Paul,</hi> as there is for a Plurality of Perſons in the Godhead; for thoſe Texts do only ſhew a Plurality of Perſons, not in Chriſt nor in <hi>Paul,</hi> but of Perſonalities abſtracted from their Nature: for no created Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons as ſuch, do ſubſiſt in their common Nature. Chriſt was a humane Subſtance abſtracted from the humane Nature, in Conjunction with the Divine Perſon of the Son, and ſo he became the one Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Chriſt, and might ſpeak of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and others, as Equals of the Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature, not taking notice of the different Subſiſtence of their Nature.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, This doth not oppoſe a Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality of Divine Perſons in the Deity, but rather confirm it, for it being confeſſed
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:32445:45"/>that <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.26, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> doth ſignify a Plura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of Perſons, it muſt alſo be of Equals of the ſame Nature.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, The Omiſſion of the ſecond Perſon (the Son of God) by Name, is no Excluſion of him from co-operating with the Father and the Holy Spirit in the Creation of the Word; becauſe O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion is not always an Excluſion: if it were, then God the Father would be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, when only Chriſt or the Holy Spirit is mentioned, as <hi>Job.</hi> 33.4. and <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 1.16. and in the Text, where the Father is as well omitted by Name as the Son; and the Holy Spirit is only named, becauſe he is the great Agent which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth from the Father and the Son, in whom they work; ſo that when it is ſaid, <hi>In the beginning</hi> God (a common Name to all three Subſiſtencies) or Almighties (which includes all three Perſons) cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated, we muſt not limit it only to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Son, or Spirit, but underſtand it of all three Subſiſtencies. And in <hi>ver.</hi> 2. where the Perſon of the Spirit is mentioned, we muſt include the other two Divine Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtencies, working in and by him. So that notwithſtanding theſe Exceptions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe Scriptures that are brought
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:32445:46"/>to prove a Plurality of Divine Perſons in the Deity, yet they abide as ſufficient Teſtimonies thereof. And as for his aſſerting the Holy Spirit to be an Angel, we have but his Word for it, which needs no farther Anſwer.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Second Objection.</hi> The Appellations of Chriſt are no Proof of his Deity, becauſe other Perſons and Things have the ſame Names aſcribed to them.</p>
                  <p n="1">1ſt. Perſons; <hi>Exod.</hi> 4.16. <hi>chap.</hi> 7.1. <hi>Jer.</hi> 33.16.</p>
                  <p n="2">2dly. Things; <hi>Gen.</hi> 22.14. <hi>Exod.</hi> 17.15. <hi>Judg.</hi> 6.24. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 48.35.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Firſt to <hi>Exod.</hi> 7.1. with <hi>chap.</hi> 4.16. we ſay, That there is not the ſame Reaſon to prove the Deity of <hi>Moſes,</hi> as there is of Chriſt, from thoſe peculiar and incommunicable Names of God that are given to him. 1ſt. Becauſe that <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> is not abſolutely called by this Name, as Chriſt is in ſome of the aforeſaid Places, and in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.13. <hi>Zech.</hi> 12.1, 10. <hi>chap.</hi> 14.3, 4. but it's only ſaid to him, I have made thee a God to <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> that is, <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> was inſpired with Wiſdom, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived Commiſſion from God, to do Wonders in the Sight of <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and all
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:32445:46"/>his People, in his ſtead: The Lord not working ſo immediately from himſelf, as he did by the Hand of <hi>Moſes;</hi> like as <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> was inſtead of God to <hi>Aaron</hi> his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to put Words into his Mouth, <hi>chap.</hi> 4.15, 16. which place doth much open and confirm this Expoſition.</p>
                  <p n="2">2dly. To <hi>Jer.</hi> 33.16. <hi>And this is the Name wherewith ſhe ſhall be called, The Lord our Righteouſneſs.</hi> Mr. <hi>Eſtwick</hi> in his Anſwer to <hi>Biddle</hi>'s Catechiſm, page 422. gives us this account of the Words: <q>The word <hi>Name</hi> is not in the Original; and to hint this to the Reader, it is printed in leſſer Letters than the reſt, which is the ſacred Text; nor is there any Pronoun in the Hebrew which ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies <hi>[ſhe];</hi> nor is there any Neceſſity to read the word in the paſſive Signifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, to tranſlate it thus, <hi>She ſhall be called;</hi> but in the Holy Tongue it is word for word, as <hi>Arius Montanus</hi> doth turn it; <hi>And he that ſhall call her, is the Lord our Righteouſneſs:</hi> And then the Name is given to Chriſt; And this is confirmed by the Dutch Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, after the ſame ſenſe.</q> And it is moſt likely to be the true Interpretation of it; for as the aforeſaid Author ſaith,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:32445:47"/>who can ſay of the Church, She is the Lord our Righteouſneſs?</p>
                  <p n="3">3dly. To Gen. 22.14. <hi>And</hi> Abraham <hi>called the Name of that Place Jehovah jireh:</hi> that is, the Lord will ſee or provide: This place was called ſo in reſpect to God (who had there provided a Ram for a Burnt-offering inſtead of <hi>Iſaac</hi>) as a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morial of what he had done there.</p>
                  <p n="4">4thly. To <hi>Exod.</hi> 17.15. <hi>And</hi> Moſes <hi>built an Altar, and called the Name of it Jehova-Niſſi,</hi> that is, the Lord my Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; which was in remembrance of God's appearing for his People againſt the <hi>Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lekites.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5thly. To <hi>Judg.</hi> 6.24. <hi>Then</hi> Gideon <hi>built an Altar there unto the Lord, and called it</hi> Jehovah-Shalom: The Lord ſend Peace as a Token of the Promiſe of Peace, which God had made in <hi>ver.</hi> 23.</p>
                  <p n="6">6thly. To <hi>Ezck.</hi> 48.35. <hi>And the Name of the City from that Day ſhall be, The Lord is there:</hi> Which Scripture, as well as thoſe foregoing, relates to the Preſence and Appearance of God in ſome extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry manner in thoſe places; and therefore as the Name <hi>Jehovah</hi> hath no proper Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to them, ſo it hinders not the Proof of Chriſt's Deity, by thoſe ſeveral
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:32445:47"/>incommunicable Names of God, that are poſitively given to him as proper Names.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Objection.</hi> To thoſe Scriptures that are brought to prove the Deity of the Son of God, being ſuch as relate to God in the Old Teſtament, and are applied to Jeſus Chriſt in the New.</p>
                  <p>What things are ſpoken of God under the Law, may for another reaſon be ſpoken of Chriſt under the Goſpel, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the great and intimate Conjunction between God and Chriſt, in reſpect of Dominion, Power and Office, that Chriſt hath obtained by the Donation of God. Now if the Scriptures deliver the very ſame things of <hi>Moſes, Exod.</hi> 32.7. <hi>Acts</hi> 7.35. and of others that are elſewhere written of God himſelf, when as neither <hi>Moſes</hi> nor thoſe others had ſo great Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction with God, as intervened be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween him and Chriſt, much more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervedly may thoſe things which are pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marily ſpoken of God, be accommodated to Chriſt, by reaſon of that moſt ſingular and ſtrict Conjunction that is between them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Firſt, It's true, that that which is primarily ſpoken of God, to have brought
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:32445:48"/>up <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> or to be their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverer, is alſo ſpoken of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and of the Angel, <hi>Acts</hi> 7.35. the ſame did God ſend to be a Ruler and a Deliverer by the Hands of the Angel which appeared to him in the Buſh. Yet how remote this is to the caſe in hand, let the Reader judg; for <hi>Moſes</hi> we ſee plainly by the Text, is put as the third cauſe of <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> as only an Inſtrument in the Hand of God through the Miniſtry of the Angel. And this agrees with the Old Teſtament, <hi>Exod.</hi> 33.1, 2. <hi>And the Lord ſaid unto</hi> Moſes, <hi>Depart and go up hence, thou and the People that thou haſt brought up out of the Land of</hi> Egypt — <hi>And I will ſend an Angel before thee.</hi> And <hi>Pſal.</hi> 77.20. <hi>Thou leddeſt thy People like a Flock by the Hand of</hi> Moſes <hi>and</hi> Aaron. But the Caſe is far different with reſpect to the Son of God; for, as in the Old Teſtament it is abſolutely ſpoken of God, ſo in the New it is poſitively applied to Jeſus Chriſt, without ſuch Reſtrictions as it is to <hi>Moſes, &amp;c.</hi> And though Chriſt hath Preheminence of Dominion and Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> above others, by Donation; yet reſpecting only the Giſt of God to him, there is no reaſon that thoſe things that
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:32445:48"/>are abſolutely ſpoken of God in the Old Teſtament ſhould be ſo poſitively ſpoken of Chriſt in the New, unleſs Regard were had to his Divine Eſſence.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, Foraſmuch as thoſe things that are primarily ſpoken of God in the Old Teſtament, are referred to Chriſt in the New, as the proper Subject to whom they belong; it is a plain Demonſtration of Chriſt's Divine Eſſence; for otherwiſe they could not be equally applied to each of them.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, If Chriſt's Supremacy in Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion and Power were only by Gift of Deputation from God, he ſhould not bear the ſupream Glory equal with him: for as it cannot conſiſt with common Right, ſo God will not part with his own Glory to inveſt a Creature with it equally with himſelf, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42.8. This may ſuffice here in Anſwer to thoſe Objections, as to the Dominion and Power of Chriſt, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by Donation from the Father. I ſhall ſpeak more diſtinctly to it elſewhere.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Objection.</hi> To <hi>Acts</hi> 20.28. — <hi>To feed the Church of God, which he hath pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed with his own Blood.</hi> The Blood which is called [the own Blood of God]
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:32445:49"/>is in ſuch a way of ſpeaking, and for ſuch a Cauſe, as the Prophet ſaith, that he which toucheth the People of God, toucheth the Apple of God's Eye; and it is ſo called for the exceeding great Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction that is between them, and as he is the Lamb of God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwer.</hi> I cannot perceive wherefore either of theſe Scriptures that are brought as Examples, ſhould be an Impediment to the Text, that it ſhould not be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of the Union of both Natures in the Perſon of Chriſt, ſeeing there is not the word <hi>[Own]</hi> conjoyned with them, which intimates the ſpecial Affinity and Relation of the Blood of Chriſt unto God; but that the Blood of Chriſt is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led [the own Blood of God,] for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding great Conjunction that is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them, not as the Adverſaries mean, as I ſuppoſe, of the official Power and Dignity of Chriſt in ſubordination unto God, but as the Aſſumption of the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature by the Divine Perſon of the Son did relate that Nature to the Divine Nature of God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Objection.</hi> To <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.6. <hi>Who being in the form of God, thought it not Robbery to be
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:32445:49"/>equal with God: but made himſelf of no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, and took upon him the form of a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, and was made in the Likeneſs of Men.</hi> This Equality of Chriſt with God, is to be extended no further than as he was in the form of God. But the form of a Thing (as appeareth by the common Acceptation of the Word, and by that following Clauſe, <hi>He took upon him the form of a Servant;</hi> and alſo from theſe words, <hi>Mark</hi> 16.12. <hi>After that he appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in another form unto two of them</hi>) is ſomething viſibly and outwardly appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, ſuch as is neither the Eſſence nor Power of any Thing, but only the Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe and Demonſtration of Power: In the Exerciſe thereof and Demonſtration of Divine Power, whereby he did Miracles, was Chriſt in the form of God, and equal to God; And when it is ſaid, <hi>But emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tied himſelf,</hi> (or, as our Engliſh Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hath it, <hi>made himſelf of no Reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi>) this implieth that if Chriſt had not emptied himſelf of that Divine Form, he had thought it a Prey to be equal with God: Which cannot without the Impli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of a Contradiction, or what is worſe, of Blaſpemy, be affirmed of God. But Chriſt had thought it Robbery, or a
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:32445:50"/>prey to have been equal with God, in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Miracles, if he had not laid aſide the Exerciſe and Demonſtration of Divine Power, and fallen into the Hands of his Adverſaries, as a weak and vulgar Man: For unleſs he had done ſo, he had diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed the Commandment of God, and conſequently thought his Divine Form to be a Prey, not a Gift of God, and that it was to be kept on for his own Glory, and not put off for the Glory of God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Firſt, It's true, that this Equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of Chriſt with God is to be extended no further than as he was in the form of God, but yet I do not hold with theſe Men: That his being in the form of God, is only the viſible, outward and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent Exerciſe and Demonſtration of Divine Power, and not the Divine Eſſence or Power it ſelf; for the common Accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the word <hi>[Form]</hi> cannot be li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited to denote only the Exerciſe and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration of Power without the Eſſence, as they would have it; or only an artiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Figure, Draught or Shadow of any thing whereby its Likeneſs is repreſented, but alſo the Likeneſs of one Perſon or thing to another of the ſame Nature, which may have the like natural Power
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:32445:50"/>and Properties in its own Eſſence; as <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> who <hi>begat a Son in his own Likeneſs, after his Image,</hi> Gen. 5.3. And, as Chriſt is ſaid to be in the Form of a Servant, which was not only in outward Appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, but in Nature and Subſtance, having the ſame natural Properties. So that if the word <hi>[Form, Likeneſs,</hi> or <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage]</hi> (which are equivalent in their Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifications) are uſed to expreſs the Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Eſſence of one created Perſon or Nature, to the Eſſence of another created Perſon; why may it not ſignify the Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of uncreated Perſons in their eſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Being and Power? For though the one is a Perſonal Likeneſs in their perſonal abſtracted Being, or only natural, and the other is different to it, in that it is not in perſonal Properties (becauſe the Divine Perſons are not alike in Proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties) but eſſential, as ſubſiſting in the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of the ſame Eſſence; yet this hinders not the word <hi>[Form]</hi> of its proper Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification, when it is uſed to either of them; becauſe it is extenſive to repreſent any manner of Likeneſs whatſoever: And therefore as viſible outward and apparent things have ſuch forms; ſo the Subſiſtence of any one Divine Perſon in the Godhead
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:32445:51"/>can only be likened to another ſubſiſting in the ſame Nature.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, To <hi>Mark</hi> 16.12. Where Chriſt is ſaid to <hi>appear in another Form.</hi> I reply, That it ſhews the Power of the Divine Nature, in repreſenting Chriſt in another Form than what he was in before; but there is no reaſon wherefore this out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward form ſhould limit the Form of Chriſt in the other Text, to be only outward and viſible, ſeeing the Word is common to ſignify any Form, and that the two Texts have no Relation to each other.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, We cannot conclude from thoſe Words, <hi>He made himſelf of no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation,</hi> That if Chriſt had not emptied himſelf of that Divine Form, he had thought it Robbery or a Prey to be equal with God; becauſe the Apoſtle neither in this, nor in any other place of Scripture, aſſigns it as the Reaſon: And therefore, ſeeing their Expoſition of theſe Words hath no other Foundation than what is imaginary in their own Conceit, we are not obliged to hearken to it.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, Chriſt's emptying himſelf of that Divine Form, or making himſelf of no Reputation, was not his laying aſide of the Exerciſe and Demonſtration of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:32445:51"/>Power, which he had by Donation as Man: 1ſt, Becauſe, as Man, Chriſt was not in the Exerciſe of it, when firſt he <hi>made himſelf of no Reputation;</hi> but was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards inveſted with it, when he took upon him his miniſterial Office, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore could not lay aſide the Demonſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Divine Power, before he was in the Exerciſe of it. 2dly, Nor can it be meant of his Sufferings as a vulgar Man, becauſe his making <hi>himſelf of no Reputation</hi> in aſſuming our Nature, and taking on him the Form of a Servant, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceded his Sufferings. 3dly, Nor did he properly empty himſelf of the Divine Nature, as God, or as the Son of God, the ſecond Perſon in the Trinity; for this could not be without his Annihila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: And therefore we muſt inquire af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſome other ſenſe that may better ſuit with this and other Scriptures.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. In this ſenſe the Son of God may be ſaid to empty himſelf, or make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of no Reputation: to wit, in dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gating from his own Glory, by his won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful and inexpreſſible Condeſcenſion, in ſtooping ſo low to ſave Man, as to take our Nature into ſuch an extraordinary Relation and Conjunction with himſelf,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:32445:52"/>and that in the former Habit of a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant. This was that which made Chriſt pray unto the Father, ſaying, <hi>Glorify thou me with thine own ſelf, with the Glory which I had with thee before the World was.</hi> It was ſo beneath the infinite and glorious God, to take our Nature into Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty with his Nature, that his very Aſſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of it was, as it were, a debaſing of his Divine Nature.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Chriſt may be ſaid to make himſelf of no Reputation, or to empty himſelf in reſpect to that Manifeſtation which he made of himſelf to the Sons of Men by his Works. The Son of God did not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to us in the eſſential Glory of his Divine Nature; for ſo he dwelleth in the Light which no Man can approach un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, whom no Man hath ſeen, nor can ſee, but in the Vail of Fleſh, through which he was emptied to our Appearance from thoſe Divine Rays, that would have da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zled the Sons of Men, and have made them afraid to look upon him, leſt they ſhould be conſumed; <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.19. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.16.</p>
                  <p>But yet there is ſomething further ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected againſt this Text of Scripture, <hi>ver.</hi> 6. <hi>He thought it not Robbery to be equal with
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:32445:52"/>God.</hi> That which is equal, hath always a different Eſſence from that which it is equal unto, otherwiſe the ſame thing would be equal unto it ſelf: Equals are Relatives, and conſequently Oppoſites; If therefore Chriſt be equal to God, in reſpect of Eſſence and eſſential Properties, the Eſſence of Chriſt muſt of neceſſity be different from the Eſſence of God; wherefore they muſt either hold two Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine independent Eſſences, or two moſt high Gods, or that Chriſt is not the moſt high God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Firſt, If it's meant, that E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quals have always a different Eſſence, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecting their Singularity or Perſonality, as being abſtracted from their common Nature: This I do readily grant of cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated perſonal Beings: becauſe ſuch Singu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larities or Perſonalities cannot exiſt, but by Abſtraction from their common Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and ſo muſt have different, ſingular and perſonal Eſſences, the one to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and (as Relates of the ſame Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) are Equals. But what is this to the Deity of the Son of God? muſt we limit Divine Perſons in the uncreated Nature, and confine them to the Parallel of created Beings? Surely the Scriptures teach us
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:32445:53"/>otherwiſe, that the Divine Perſons are not abſtracted from the Divine Nature, but are coeſſential, yet differing in perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Properties. Chriſt is equal to God, (<hi>viz.</hi> the Father) not reſpecting the ſame perſonal Properties, as to beget, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But eſſentially conſidered, as ſubſiſting in the Unity of the ſame Nature, and having all the eſſential Properties of that Nature coequal with him. And thus there is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther two Divine independent Eſſences, nor moſt high Gods, but one only, ſubſiſting in three Divine Perſons, each of which ſubſiſting in the Divine Nature, and mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually in one another, is the moſt high God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Objection.</hi> To 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.20. <hi>And we know that the Son of God is come, and hath given us an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, that we may know him that is true; and we are in him that is true, even in his Son Jeſus Chriſt: this is the true God, and eternal Life.</hi> Theſe Words <hi>[This is the true God]</hi> cannot be referred unto Chriſt, not as if he were not [true God] but becauſe he is not [the true God] that is here ſpoken of, as the Article added in the Greek doth intimate. Neither doth it any whit advantage the Adverſaries Cauſe, who will have theſe
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:32445:53"/>Words, <hi>[This is the true God]</hi> referred unto Chriſt, that was mentioned imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately before. For Relatives are not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways referred to the Antecedent imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately going before, but oftentimes to that which is chiefly ſpoken of; as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth from theſe places, <hi>Acts</hi> 7.18, 19. chap. 10.6. 2 <hi>John</hi> 6.7. <hi>Many De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivers are entred into the World, who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs not that Jeſus Chriſt is come in the Fleſh. This is a Deceiver, and an Antichriſt.</hi> Wherefore the meaning of thoſe words is thus: This, whereof I have laſt ſpoken, is the true God, (namely he that for <hi>(or [ſent] it being, as I ſuppoſe the Printers Miſtake)</hi> his Son Jeſus Chriſt) and it is alſo eternal Life, (namely to know Thee, the true God, and to be in him by his Son Jeſus Chriſt) with this accordeth, <hi>John</hi> 7.3.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Firſt, As to the Article in the Greek, it no ways hinders our Senſe, or Expoſition of the Words, but is rather a ſtrengthning of it; for is it not more emphatical to ſay? <hi>This is [the] true God,</hi> than to leave out the Article, and read it, <hi>This is true God, and Eternal Life.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. Thoſe Words, <hi>This is the true God,</hi> are not to be referred unto Chriſt, becauſe
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:32445:54"/>Relatives always are not referred to the Antecedent immediately going before, as <hi>Acts</hi> 10.6. <hi>chap.</hi> 7.18, 19. 2 <hi>Joh.</hi> 7.</p>
                  <p>To this I anſwer, 1ſt, That theſe words 2 <hi>John</hi> 7. <hi>This is a Deceiver, and an Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt,</hi> are no Relative either to Chriſt, or to the many Deceivers entred into the World, but as they are connexed to the deſcription of the many Deceivers, and of the Antichriſt. 2dly. To thoſe two Texts <hi>Acts</hi> 7.18, 19. <hi>chap.</hi> 10.6. It is one thing to ſay, that ſuch a one, that knew not ſuch a Perſon, did ſuch a thing, and that lodgeth with ſuch a Man, ſhall tell thee what thou oughteſt to do, which points at the Perſon, and is a Deſcription of him, and therefore referreth the Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive higher than the immediate Antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent; and another thing to divide and refer the Relative, <hi>This is the true God,</hi> from the immediate Antecedent, <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> 1. Becauſe the matter of the verſe plainly relateth to the Son of God. 2dly. The Relative, <hi>This is the true God,</hi> muſt of neceſſity be referred to <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> becauſe it is ſtrongly fixed to the immediate Antecedent <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> by the Words <hi>[Him] that is true, [Him] that we are in,</hi> as if it were ſaid, <hi>The Son of God,</hi>
                     <pb n="97" facs="tcp:32445:54"/>this <hi>Him</hi> that is true, this <hi>Him</hi> that we are in, (viz. <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi>) <hi>is the true God, and Eternal Life.</hi> So that notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their Oppoſition to the Evidence of this Scripture, it is not weakened, but ſtill remains a firm proof of the true God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Objection</hi> to <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 2.9. <hi>For in him dwelleth all the Fulneſs of the Godhead bodily.</hi> This word <hi>Godhead</hi> may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>note the Divine Will, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.19. and foraſmuch as the Apoſtle doth oppoſe that Speech, not to Perſons, but to Philoſophy and legal Ceremonies, it is evident, it is meant of the Doctrine of Chriſt, not of his Perſon. But ſhould we take the words as they ſound, yet could not ſuch a divine Nature, as the Adverſaries have imagined, be thence collected. For it is true and manifeſt that the fulneſs of the Deity or Godhead doth now dwell in Chriſt even bodily, in that his very Body is altogether Divine, as being made both of Divine and Spiritual Matter, namely that of the Heavens, ſee 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.45, 47, 48. and being endowed with divine Life and divine Splendor, and divine Strength.</p>
                  <pb n="98" facs="tcp:32445:55"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Firſt the words <hi>[Godhead bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily]</hi> cannot be limited, as only denoting the Divine Will of God; becauſe the Signification of the Word, will not allow of it. Godhead is the Nature of God, which is not only his Will, but his Power, Immenſity, yea, all his eſſential Properties and Perfections.</p>
                  <p>Secondly; Nor can we confine this Text to the parallel of <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.19. <hi>And to know the Love of Chriſt which paſſeth Knowledg, that ye might be filled with all the fulneſs of God,</hi> viz. of his Love in all its parts; becauſe there wants the words <hi>[Godhead bodily]</hi> to be filled with all the fulneſs of the Godhead bodily, is to have all the fulneſs of the Nature and Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of God dwelling really, perfectly and ſolidly in him, or the whole Spiritual Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of God.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly; It is apparently clear, that the Perſon of Chriſt, and not his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, muſt be underſtood to have all the fulneſs of the Godhead dwelling in him: For it is ſaid, <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 2.8. <hi>Beware leſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Man ſpoil you through Philoſophy and vain Deceit, after the Traditions of Men, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Rudiments of the World, and not after Chriſt: For in him</hi> (viz. in Chriſt) <hi>dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:32445:55"/>all the fulneſs of the Godhead</hi> (or Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of God) <hi>bodily.</hi> They ſay indeed that by <hi>Him</hi> is meant the Doctrine, and not the Perſon of Chriſt, and that by <hi>Godhead</hi> is meant his Divine Will, and ſo that the fulneſs of his Divine Will, (<hi>viz.</hi> the revealed Will of God, otherwiſe it is incommunicable to the humane Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) dwelleth in the Doctrine of Chriſt. But certain and plain it is that by <hi>Him,</hi> which betokens a Perſon, muſt be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood the Perſon it relateth to, <hi>viz.</hi> Chriſt; and the revealed Will of God is the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Jeſus Chriſt, which (their meaning is) muſt dwell in the Doctrine of Chriſt: but how abſurd and fooliſh this is, let the Reader judg.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly; Thoſe words are not ſimply oppoſed to Philoſophy, but with ſome reſpect to the Perſons in whom it dwelt, that we ſhould <hi>beware leſt any Man ſpoil us through Philoſophy and Vain De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit — and not after Chriſt, (viz.</hi> his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine in oppoſition to their Doctrine, and his Perſon in oppoſition to their Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and his Fountain, (<hi>viz.</hi> the fulneſs of the Godhead) in oppoſition to their Fountain, <hi>viz.</hi> the Traditions of Men) <hi>and the Rudiments of the World:</hi> So
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:32445:56"/>that theſe words, <hi>In him dwelleth all the fulneſs of the Godhead bodily,</hi> muſt of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity be underſtood of the fulneſs of the Divine Nature of God in the Perſon of Jeſus Chriſt through the Union of both his Natures.</p>
                  <p>Fifthly; For them to ſay that this ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Godhead in Jeſus Chriſt, is not of that ſupream Divine Nature of God, as we are treating of, but of an inferiour Divine Nature, floweth only from the Notions of their own Brains: for there is no ſuch thing in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. nor in any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther part of the Holy Scripture: for though Chriſt as Man, and others by way of Gift, have had ſomething of Divine Power and Splendor inveſted in them; yet this is not properly another different Godhead, but a Demonſtration of the ſame Supream Deity, through their Offici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Miniſtration; and in all thoſe 3 Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.29. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.20. and <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 2.9. wherein Godhead is mentioned, it muſt of neceſſity be underſtood of the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream and Eternal Godhead only. So that I ſee not the leaſt reaſon why the corrupt Notions of our Adverſaries ſhould weaken our Faith in this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, which is ſo clearly aſſerted,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:32445:56"/>in this as well as in many other Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Objection</hi> to <hi>John</hi> 1.1, 2, 3, 10. <hi>In the Beginning was the Word.</hi> Nothing is here concerning Chriſt's being from Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, ſince mention is here made of the beginning, whereas a Beginning is oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to Eternity.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. If Chriſt were in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Creation, and ſo as that all Things were made by him, <hi>ver.</hi> 3. then he did preexiſt the Creation, and it is not ſaid he began to be in, or with the Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, but then he was, which denotes his being before the Beginning, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could preexiſt the beginning of the Creation, but God alone.</p>
                  <p>Secondly; They ſay, that the word [<hi>Beginning</hi>] is every where in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture referred to the ſubject Matter, which is here the Goſpel which <hi>John</hi> undertook to deſcribe, as will appear if you com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare this of <hi>John</hi> with <hi>Mark</hi> 1.1. <hi>Luke</hi> 1.2. <hi>chap.</hi> 3.23. where, according to the Greek, it ought to be rendred thus, <hi>And Jeſus was about thirty years of Age, when he began, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="102" facs="tcp:32445:57"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Firſt, <hi>Mark,</hi> in <hi>chap.</hi> 1.1. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares unto us, what he knew only from the beginning of the preaching of the Goſpel. 1ſt. Hinting to that of <hi>John's</hi> Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration, and then immediately comes to Chriſt, <hi>ver.</hi> 9.</p>
                  <p>Second, <hi>Luke</hi>'s beginning is ſaid in <hi>ver.</hi> 3. to be from the very firſt, and he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins higher than <hi>Mark</hi> did, and gives us an account of the Conception and Birth of <hi>John,</hi> and then of Chriſt, and after theſe, that at Chriſt's Baptiſm, he began to be about thirty years of Age, or (as they will have the Greek) that he was thirty years of Age when he began, <hi>viz.</hi> to preach the Goſpel, for ſo it muſt be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood; ſo that (as they ſay) Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning is to be referred to the ſubject Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter treated of: And therefore [<hi>Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi>] in <hi>John</hi> 1.1. muſt not be limited to either of theſe, but referred to its own proper ſubject Matter, as the others were to theirs. Now that this ſubject Matter, to which it muſt be referred, is not the Goſpel (as they affirm) doth appear, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is ſpeaking of the Creation of the World by the Word, which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed by them to be Jeſus Chriſt. But here (as they think) they have a Salvo;
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:32445:57"/>for though all Things are ſaid to be made by him in the Beginning, (yet they ſay it is not ſimply and abſolutely All, but all Things belonging to the Goſpel, like that in 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.17. <hi>All Things are become new.</hi>) And that the next words, <hi>Without Him was not any Thing made that was made,</hi> muſt be underſtood, that all Things were not [<hi>done</hi>] by him, for ſo the Greek will bear it, as they ſay: for though they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg, they were begun by him, yet they were not brought to an iſſue by himſelf, but by his Apoſtles in his Name, and by his Authority, and ſo not done without Him. And they further object, that it is not ſaid that the World was <hi>created,</hi> but <hi>made</hi> by him; not that he made it, but it was made by him, as the ſecond Cauſe, and that the word [<hi>World</hi>] doth not only denote the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth; but beſides other Signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications, deſigneth either Mankind, as the preſent place ſheweth, or the World to come, as appeareth by <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.6. which they draw from <hi>chap.</hi> 2.5. and by <hi>chap.</hi> 10.5. which alſo they affirm to be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, not of this World, but of that which is to come, ſince it's ſaid in <hi>chap.</hi> 8.4. For if he were on Earth, he would
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:32445:58"/>not ſo much as be a Prieſt. From all which they give us the ſenſe of the words two ways. Firſt, That Mankind was reformed, and as it were made again by Chriſt, becauſe he brought Life and Immortality to Men who were loſt, and ſubject to Eternal Death. 2<abbr>
                        <hi>d.</hi>
                     </abbr> The lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Senſe is, That the World to come which we expect by Chriſt, is by him made as to us, as the ſame is ſaid to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come in reſpect of us, although it be alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy preſent to Chriſt and the Angels.</p>
                  <p>To theſe I ſhall give particular Anſwers.</p>
                  <p>Firſt; All things that were made by Chriſt, cannot be here underſtood, of the <hi>all things</hi> of the Goſpel, but of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the World. And this I ſhall endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to demonſtrate, by ſhewing the great difference between the Text of <hi>John,</hi> and that of <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> and how little relation they have to each other.</p>
                  <p>In 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.17. <hi>Therefore if any Man be in Chriſt, he is a new Creature: Old things are paſt away; behold, all things are become new.</hi> The Words <hi>all things become new,</hi> muſt of neceſſity imply a Renovation; for tho the Graces of the Spirit are created in us, yet the Man is not created, but renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and reſtored by them.</p>
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:32445:58"/>
                  <p>So that in the ſame Senſe that the Man is a new Creature, all things may be ſaid to become, new; and this agrees with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Scriptures, as in <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.8, 9, 10. That which is ſaid to be by [Creation] in Chriſt Jeſus, is in <hi>Titus</hi> 3.5. by the [Renewings] of the Holy Ghoſt, but in <hi>John</hi> 1.3. it is ſaid that <hi>all Things were made by him:</hi> which is not only a different mode of Speech to that of <hi>Paul,</hi> but does imply a different thing; for, as I have ſhewed, the words of <hi>Paul</hi> import a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtauration or Renovation of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as they alſo do affirm, but this of <hi>John</hi> hath peculiar relation to the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the World.</p>
                  <p n="1">1ſt. Becauſe the words, <hi>All Things are made by him,</hi> are plain and poſitive, and therefore it is dangerous and preſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to reſtrain their Senſe to other Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, whoſe ſubject Matter is foreign to it, and to impoſe ſuch an uncouth Senſe, which cannot naturally be drawn from it, and which is incoherent with other Scriptures, that mutually concur with its plain and proper Senſe, as <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 1.16. to which place I may ſay ſomething here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</p>
                  <pb n="106" facs="tcp:32445:59"/>
                  <p n="2">2dly. Thoſe words, <hi>All Things were made by him,</hi> is meant of the Creation, and not of the Goſpel, appears from <hi>ver.</hi> 10, 11. <hi>He was in the World, and the World was made by him, and the World knew him not. He came unto his own, and his own received him not,</hi> &amp;c. Now to aſſert, as they do, That theſe words, <hi>The World was made by him,</hi> muſt be underſtood of Mankind that was reformed by Jeſus Chriſt, is a ſqueezing forth ſuch a Senſe, as they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not poſſibly bear, and it is unuſual and improper in ſuch a form of Words to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the Reformation of Mankind; and I do not know of any ſuch abſolute Text that aſſerts the new Creation, or Goſpel-Renovation, but that there is ſome ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junct to explain it from the Creation of the World, as to be <hi>created in Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus;</hi> to <hi>become new,</hi> or <hi>the new Man which is created,</hi> and the like: and therefore ſuch as force the Text, contrary to the genuine ſenſe of it, to comply with a Goſpel-Reformation, do greatly ſubvert the Word of God; nor is there any A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement in thoſe words to ſuch an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition: for the World was ſo far from being reformed by Chriſt, that it knew him not, and his own received him not,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:32445:59"/>
                     <hi>viz.</hi> his own Nation was not reformed by him.</p>
                  <p n="3">3dly. I ſhall make ſome reply to their latter Senſe of thoſe words, <hi>ver.</hi> 10. <hi>The World was made by him,</hi> which ſay they, is, That the World to come, which we expect by Chriſt, is by him made as to us; that is (if I miſtake them not) it is made by a partial Reformation; which if they would but ſpeak out, is not made, but only making. And they ſay further, that this World to come, is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready preſent to Chriſt and the Angels, that is (as I imagine to be their mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) it is fully come to them, by their pre-knowledg and aſſurance of it, having laid its Foundation. What elſe they ſhould intend by theſe and the like words, doth not at preſent occur to mind: But this is preſumptuouſly aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by them; for there is no mention made of the World to come, neither is there any thing in the Text that relates to it; neither is there any reaſon where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they ſhould go about to prove, that becauſe there is mention made of a World to come, in <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.5. therefore this in <hi>John</hi> 1.10. is of the World to come alſo. Nor do I yet perceive why <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.6.
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:32445:60"/>
                     <hi>chap.</hi> 10.5. and 8.4. ſhould be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of the World to come, or what ground they have to impoſe from thence, their Senſe on <hi>John</hi> 1.10. For though the Apoſtle ſpeaks of ſomething which relates to the World to come in <hi>Heb.</hi> 1. yet he doth not begin with it until <hi>ver.</hi> 8. and therefore as the matter in <hi>ver.</hi> 6. plainly ſhews, the World there, is not the World to come, but the preſent World: But if it were, yet <hi>John</hi> 1.10. muſt not be confined to this or any other Text a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny further than the concurrence of the Texts and Contexts, and the Significati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their words will bear. But now let us take notice how little difference the Socinians here make, between the time paſt, and the time to come. The World that was (with them) was the World to come; that was made, was yet to make. What a monſtrous way they have of expounding the Holy Scriptures! by <hi>all things,</hi> ſay they, is only meant Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel-things were made by Chriſt, the reſt were made by his Apoſtles, and that not in the beginning, as the Text aſſerts, but after even their own prefixt beginning. But if this may paſs for truth, at this rate
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:32445:60"/>'tis not to be found in the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. But theſe Exceptions are ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, and ſo are of no effect, to weaken the proof of the Deity of Jeſus Chriſt from this Scripture.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Objection</hi> to <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9.6. Where Chriſt is called, <hi>The everlaſting Father,</hi> or, <hi>Fa-Father of Eternity,</hi> as it is admitted by the Adverſaries, who nevertheleſs ſay, it quite ſubverteth the Common Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, by confounding the firſt and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Perſons of the Trinity. He is the Everlaſting Father, both becauſe he is the Author of eternal Life to them that obey him, and liveth for ever to ſhelter, and protect, and cheriſh Chriſtians who are elſewhere called his Seed, ſee <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.3, 10.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Firſt, The words in the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>the Father of Eternity,</hi> do not ſo much ſubvert the Common Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Trinity, or confound the Perſons, to underſtand them of the Divine Nature of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, than of him as only humane: For though Chriſt is ſaid to be the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of eternal Salvation, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.9. Yet it cannot be as Man only, either in the
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:32445:61"/>Miniſtration of it, or being the prime Author. For there being a Miniſtration of Salvation under the Old Teſtament, Chriſt as Man could not be the prime Author of it; but God, who elected and fore-ordained Chriſt, and us in him, unto Salvation before the Foundation of the World, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42.1. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.4. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.20.</p>
                  <p>So then as Chriſt did not then exiſt in his humane Nature, as Man he could not be the prime Author, or Adminiſtrator of eternal Salvation: And when he was come, conſidered as Man, he could only bear a greater Teſtimony of the purpoſe and good-Will of God towards us, than any of the Prophets did before him. But to acknowledg the Son of God to be of the ſame Divine Nature co-eſſential with the Father, makes the name <hi>Father of Eternity,</hi> to have relation to him not perſonally, but as he is eſſentially God; and his being called by it, is an evident Demonſtration of his Unity of Eſſence co-eternally with the Father, wherein only he can be the Author of eternal Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation to us his Spiritual Seed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Objection</hi> to <hi>John</hi> 17.5. <hi>And now, O Father glorify thou me with thy own ſelf,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:32445:61"/>with the Glory which I had with thee before the World was.</hi> Chriſt doth beg this Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Father which ſheweth, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he was formerly in actual Poſſeſſion thereof; for then he would have been in poſſeſſion of it ſtill; nor had a Divine Nature, for that would have ſupplied him with ſuch Glory as he wanted: wherefore the Senſe is, that Chriſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeches the Father to grant unto him that Glory which he had with him in his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree before the World was; As we are ſaid to be ſaved according to the Grace which was given us in Chriſt Jeſus before the World began.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwer,</hi> Firſt. The better to clear this Text from theſe Objections, I ſhall expound it. 1ſt. If it ſhould be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, that theſe words denote a Depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of Glory, yet it muſt not be abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely conſidered; for the Divine Nature of Chriſt, ever was, is, and ſhall be in it ſelf, infinitely Glorious without the leaſt Diminution, Alteration or Change. But we are to take it with reſpect to the great Humility and Condeſcenſion of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite glorious Nature, in uniting himſelf with our Nature. It is ſaid, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.6, 7, 8. <hi>Who being in the Form of God, thought it
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:32445:62"/>not Robbery to be equal with God, but made himſelf of no Reputation: — He humbled himſelf, and became obedient unto Death.</hi> The Divine Nature of Chriſt conſented to the expoſing of his humane Nature, that was in ſo great a Conjunction with it, to Sufferings as an ordinary Man. And if God is ſaid <hi>to humble himſelf to behold the things that are in Heaven, and in the Earth,</hi> Pſal. 113.5, 6. Then ſurely this muſt be a far greater piece of Condeſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, for the Son of God to diſrobe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf as it were of that Power and Majeſty which he had with the Father, in ſubject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his humane Nature to ſuffer the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilings and Scourgings of wicked Men, and to be put to Death by them. Now if the Text muſt be underſtood of a Deprivation of Chriſt's former Glory: then the meaning of Chriſt's Prayer is, that as his Condeſcenſion in taking our Nature, had been an Eclipſe of his Divine Glory, Power and Greatneſs, in laying it aſide, as it were to ſuffer in his humane Nature for our ſakes, that now the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would ſo tranſlate his humane Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture from that mean Eſtate and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, to one more glorious, that might better ſute with his infinite Perfection,
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:32445:62"/>and correſpond with it. But,</p>
                  <p>Secondly; This Text moſt properly (as it ſeems to me) ought to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood not of a Deprivation of Glory of the Divine Nature, but only of the Exalta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the humane Nature of Chriſt; as if Chriſt ſhould have ſaid, And now, O Father, glorify thou me in my humane Nature; or glorify my humane Nature, in taking of it into that Glory which my Divine Nature had with thee before the World was.</p>
                  <p>This I humbly conceive is meant by the words of our bleſſed Lord; but take it in either ſenſe, it agrees with the Deity of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>Secondly; I come more particularly to anſwer the ſaid Objections.</p>
                  <p n="1">1ſt, Though (as it is objected) it may be concluded from the Words, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Chriſt begs this Glory of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, therefore he had it not in actual Poſſeſſion before. Yet this is only reſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his humane Nature, which oppoſes not the Truth of his Deity; for though he was not yet ſupplied by it, or glorified, <hi>John</hi> 7.39. Yet he then had the Divine Nature, and was in Union with it.</p>
                  <pb n="114" facs="tcp:32445:63"/>
                  <p n="2">2dly; For any to ſay, that that Glory which Chriſt had before the World was, is only meant of God's Decree, is an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing on the Text that which it cannot bear, for it doth not run parallel with 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.9. becauſe it is one thing to ſay, that we are ſaved and called accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his own Purpoſe and Grace, which was given us in Chriſt before the World began; and another thing to have Glory before the World began: the one plainly ſhews that we were not actually called nor ſaved before the World was, but were then in the purpoſe of God only; and the other is poſitively ſpoken of the Glory that Chriſt had in actual Poſſeſſion, as the ſenſe of the words import. And I hope theſe are ſufficient Anſwers to clear the Text of theſe Objections.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Objection</hi> to <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 1.16. <hi>For by him were all things created that are in Heaven, and that are in Earth, viſible and inviſible, whether they be Thrones, or Dominions, or Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalities, or Powers, all things were created by him and for him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Firſt, They ſay, that this Scripture ſpeaketh of Chriſt as a ſecond or middle cauſe, that God created all things by Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.9.</p>
                  <pb n="115" facs="tcp:32445:63"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Firſt, I do acknowledg that Jeſus Chriſt is two ways to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered.</p>
                  <p n="1">1ſt, Eſſentially, as he is God, and ſo all things are of him and from him, and created by him, indifferently with other Divine Perſons.</p>
                  <p n="2">2dly, Perſonally, as he is the ſecond Perſon in the Godhead, and ſo is he alſo in the Works of Creation; for all things are of the Father by the Son, through the Spirit, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.6. <hi>John</hi> 1.3. <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.2. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104.30. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.18. For as the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is of himſelf a Divine Subſiſtent, ſo he worketh from himſelf; and as the Son is of the Father, ſo he worketh from the Father; and as the Holy Spirit is of the Father and the Son, ſo he worketh from them both, yet neither of them exiſt or work before each other in time, but do na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally and neceſſarily work together: for when we ſay the Son is the ſecond Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in the Deity, we grant the Father to be the firſt, (neither in time nor Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of Nature, to the other Divine Perſons) but in reſpect to Preheminence, according to his peculiar manner of Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence and incommunicable Property. So alſo the Divine Perſons have their Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:32445:64"/>or Preheminence of working accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their Order or Preheminence of Subſiſtence and incommunicable Property in the Divine Eſſence.</p>
                  <p>Secondly; They ſay that <hi>all things in the Heavens, and on the Earth,</hi> are not uſed for all things ſimply, and abſolutely, appeareth, becauſe the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>By him God hath reconciled all things in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and on Earth;</hi> and alſo in the words themſelves, it is not ſaid the Heavens and the Earth were created by Chriſt, but <hi>all things that are in the Heavens and on the Earth.</hi> And the Sum of what they underſtand by the Text, is, that after God had raiſed Chriſt from the dead, and had given Glory to him: all the things both in the Heavens and on the Earth were by him reformed and reduced to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother State and Condition, in that he became the head of Angels and Men, who before acknowledged God only for their Lord.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, To this I anſwer.</p>
                  <p n="1">1ſt, That if we can reconcile the word <hi>[Create]</hi> in <hi>ver.</hi> 16. ſo as that naturally its Signification doth import but one and the ſame thing with the word <hi>[Reconcile]</hi> in <hi>ver.</hi> 20. then indeed there is ſome rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:32445:64"/>to acquieſce with them in their ſenſe: But as the words have different Signifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, ſo they ſignify to us different things.</p>
                  <p n="2">2dly, Though <hi>reconciling all things to God by Jeſus Chriſt, whether in Heaven or in Earth,</hi> muſt be underſtood in a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited ſenſe; yet there is not the ſame, nor ſo good reaſon, for all things that were created by Jeſus Chriſt to be ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered: For thoſe <hi>all things</hi> that were reconciled, were all things that were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concileable by the Blood of the Croſs, whether in Heaven or in Earth, and not all things abſolutely in Heaven and in Earth; for the evil Angels are not recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilable: but in <hi>ver.</hi> 16. the caſe is much different, and is to be underſtood ſimply and abſolutely, that by Jeſus Chriſt all things were created: for the words are poſitive, <hi>By him were all things created that are in Heaven, and that are in Earth;</hi> and becauſe we ſhould not miſapprehend the Apoſtle's meaning, he explains himſelf more fully to us, that they were <hi>all things both viſible and inviſible, whether they be Thrones, or Dominions, or Principalities, or Powers:</hi> And ſurely this cannot be meant of a Reformation or Renovation of all
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:32445:65"/>things in Heaven and Earth, becauſe the good Angels never wanted ſuch Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; neither were all <hi>Thrones, or Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or Principalities, or Powers,</hi> either of evil Angels, that are inviſible, or of wicked Men on Earth, then renewed, or ſo reduced by Reformation, as that Chriſt became their Head, and was ſo acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged by them: For though Chriſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came the Head of his own Church, yet the World did not know him in ſuch a manner as to own him for their Soveraign Lord, and to yield true and ſincere Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to his Laws, for under the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of Satan, the Dragon Heathen Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire made head againſt Chriſt, and all that profeſſed his Holy Name. And tho ſomething may be ſaid, that in the Reign of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great there was a mighty Reformation made in the Empire of the World, yet this cannot anſwer the Import of the words, <hi>For by him were all things</hi> [already <hi>created</hi>] they were not to make in future times, but they were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready done before. So that I ſee not the leaſt grounds wherefore they ſhould impoſe ſuch an unnatural ſenſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the words, but that they muſt of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity be underſtood of the Creation of
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:32445:65"/>all things in Heaven and Earth by Jeſus Chriſt. And though they make this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, that it is not ſaid the Heavens and the Earth were created by him, but only the things contained in them; yet this omiſſion cannot be an Excluſion of them, nor hinder what is aſſerted in the Text, but that it remains a ſufficient proof of the Deity of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Objection</hi> to <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.10. This Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor (to the <hi>Hebrews</hi>) doth not refer the Creation of Heaven and Earth un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſt, but only the aboliſhing of them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Firſt, I do affirm that the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Heaven and Earth, muſt of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity be applied to Jeſus Chriſt; becauſe the word <hi>[and]</hi> in the beginning of the Verſe is a conjunctive word, that joins this Verſe to the Words going before, which relate to the Son of God, ſo that as in <hi>ver.</hi> 8. we read, <hi>But unto the Son he ſaith, Thy Throne, O God, is for ever and ever;</hi> So alſo by virtue of the Conjuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with <hi>ver.</hi> 10. it is proper to underſtand the Text, as if the Apoſtle ſhould inſtead of the word <hi>[and]</hi> have ſaid, But unto the Son he ſaid, <hi>Thou, Lord, in the Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:32445:66"/>haſt laid the Foundation of the Earth,</hi> &amp;c. And this Conjunction is put for the ſame purpoſe; for in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 102.25. from whence this Text is taken, there is none of it.</p>
                  <p>Secondly; There can be no reaſon aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned, wherefore the aboliſhing of the Heavens ſhould only be referred to Chriſt, when it is not by virtue of a Conjuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on immediately annexed, but of one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed to the Creation of them which doth preceed, and therefore that of the Creation is primarily to be referred to the Son of God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Objection</hi> to thoſe Scriptures wherein the Deity of Chriſt is proved from that Divine Worſhip and Adoration which is given to him. Foraſmuch as all the places that teſtify concerning Chriſt's di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Honour, do alſo teſtify that this Divine Honour was given to him at a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Time, and for a certain Cauſe; it is plain, that the Divine Nature of Chriſt cannot thence be collected. And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as it is ſaid, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42.8. <hi>I will not give my Glory to another,</hi> it is meant, as is preſently added, <hi>nor my Praiſe to graven Images,</hi> God ſpeaketh of them who have no Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:32445:66"/>with him, and to whom, if any Glory and Honour be aſcribed, it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dounded not to him. But he ſaith not, that he will not communicate his Glory with ſuch a one as Chriſt, which is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent of him, and ſubordinate to him, for by this means no Diminution of his Glory is made, ſince the whole is referred to him.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwer,</hi> Firſt; Though ſome places that teſtify concerning Chriſt's Honour, do alſo teſtify that this Honour was given to him as at the time of his Exaltation; and becauſe he had a Name given him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove every name, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.9, 10. Yet the Divine Nature of Chriſt may be collected from his Divine Honour and Worſhip given to him. For the time and cauſe of the Exaltation, and Honour of Chriſt's hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature by Donation, doth not hinder the truth of his Divine Eſſence, from the Divine Honour aſcribed to him; becauſe ſuch Honour and Worſhip is not, nor cannot be ſimply conferred on Chriſt as Man, but by virtue of his Divine Perſon: and this appears from what is already proved, that God only is to be worſhipped with Divine Worſhip, even Him only who is God by Nature.</p>
                  <pb n="122" facs="tcp:32445:67"/>
                  <p>Secondly, To <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42.8. they ſay, That God's not giving his Gloty to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, is an excluſion of Graven Images, but they will not allow it as a total Excluſion of all others.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwer.</hi> It's true that Graven Images are excluded, and ſo alſo are all others whatſoever that are created Beings; for the words themſelves import, that beſides Graven Images, he will not give his Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to another, <hi>viz.</hi> Nature nor Perſon: So that even the Son himſelf, if he had not an uncreated Exiſtence, ſubſiſting in the Nature of God, he would be excluded from Divine Glory, and therefore the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Glory aſcribed to him, proves him to be a Divine Perſon.</p>
                  <p>As to the reſt of thoſe Scriptures that I have cited, to prove the Deity of Jeſus Chriſt, by the Divine Honour and Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration given to him, I have not met with any that have aſſailed them, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I hope that no material Objection can be made againſt them.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="123" facs="tcp:32445:67"/>
                  <head>CHAP. II.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Wherein is anſwered ſome Objections that are inferred by our Adverſaries, from divers Texts of Scripture againſt the Deity of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>OBjection</hi> from <hi>Mark</hi> 13.32. <hi>But of that Day and that Hour knoweth no Man, no not the Angels which are in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, neither the Son, but the Father.</hi> From this Scripture ſome do conclude, that Chriſt is not God, becauſe he knew not all things.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwer.</hi> The Humanity of Chriſt might not know all things, until they were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed by his Divine Perſon, as it did not know of that Day nor Hour; for the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Perſon had not yet revealed it; and though the Humanity of Chriſt, which is not the Divine Perſon of the Son, but is only a part of Chriſt's Perſon, is here cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Son; yet this impedes not the Text of this Expoſition, for the Humani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Chriſt is ſometimes put for his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Nature, <hi>John</hi> 13.13.</p>
                  <pb n="124" facs="tcp:32445:68"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Objection</hi> from <hi>Acts</hi> 2.36. <hi>Therefore let all the Houſe of</hi> Iſrael <hi>know aſſuredly, that God hath made that ſame Jeſus, whom ye have crucified, both Lord and Chriſt.</hi> From whence is formed this Syllogiſm.</p>
                  <p>He that was made Lord by another; he, if he be a God, was alſo made a God by another.</p>
                  <p>But Jeſus, of whom it is certain that he is a God, was made Lord by God.</p>
                  <p>Therefore he was alſo made a God by him.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwer.</hi> This Syllogiſm may be confeſſed, as it is reconcileable to the Human Nature of Chriſt: for as he was Man, he had a Name given him above every Name, and a Lordſhip or Kingdom, and Authority to execute Judgment, and was called <hi>Lord, Phil.</hi> 2.8, 9. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.12. <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.27, 29. And ſo alſo as he did officially miniſter the Power of God, and was one to whom the Word of the Lord came, he may be called <hi>God, Joh.</hi> 10.35, 36. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.1. and in this Senſe he may be ſaid to be made a God by the Father: but as this is not the proper or ſupream Godhead and Lordſhip of Chriſt, becauſe it is not natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral nor eſſential, ſo doth it not oppoſe his
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:32445:68"/>natural, eſſential, and ſupream Godhead, and Lordſhip, as he was God from all Eternity.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Objection</hi> from <hi>Coloſſians</hi> 1.15. where Chriſt is ſaid to be <hi>the Firſt-born of every Creature.</hi> The Firſt-born muſt always be contained in the number of them, of whom, except the Parents, it is ſaid to be the Firſt-born; and conſequently Chriſt muſt be comprehended in the Number of Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, whoſe Firſt-born he is ſaid to be.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Chriſt's being the Firſt-born of every Creature, neither includes him to be only a Fellow-Creature with others, or excludes him from the Deity.</p>
                  <p>Firſt; Becauſe Chriſt cannot properly be ſaid to be the Firſt-born of every Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, by Creation; for then it could not be ſaid, That <hi>All things were made by him, and without him was not any thing made that was made,</hi> unleſs a Creature could preexiſt its own Creation, and give it ſelf a Being. <hi>John</hi> 1.3.</p>
                  <p>Secondly; Chriſt's being call'd the Firſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born of every Creature, cannot be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of the natural Birth of ſome kind of Creatures; not of Man, for there was none created before <hi>Adam,</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> was
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:32445:69"/>the Mother of all Mankind, and <hi>Cain</hi> was her firſt-born, not Chriſt; neither could he be the firſt-born of Angels, for they do not propagate their kind, <hi>Mark</hi> 12.25. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.15.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly; Chriſt cannot be the firſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born of every Creature in time, preceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all others in the new Creation by Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation, unleſs he had exiſted in his humane Nature, before the Patriarchs and Prophets of old, and all the holy Men from the Foundation of the World.</p>
                  <p>But having ſpoken in the Negative, I ſhall now endeavour to demonſtrate how Chriſt may be called the firſt-born of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Creature.</p>
                  <p n="1">1ſt. Chriſt may be ſaid to be the firſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born of every Creature from the Dead, in like manner as he is called the firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten of the Dead, and became the firſt Fruits of them that ſleep, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.20. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.5.</p>
                  <p n="2">2dly. Chriſt may alſo be called the firſt-born of every Creature, as preex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſting every Creature in his Divine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; like as the ſame Apoſtle expounds it in the following words, <hi>ver.</hi> 16, 17. <hi>For by him were all things created,—and he is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all things, and by him all things conſiſt.</hi>
                     <pb n="127" facs="tcp:32445:69"/>As if he ſhould ſay, the very reaſon wherefore I call him the firſt-born of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Creature, is (not becauſe of Creation or natural Birth, or ſpiritual by Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration) but becauſe he was before all things in reſpect of time, and Creator of them. So that it is clearly manifeſt there is no ground from this Text for any to believe that our Lord Jeſus Chriſt is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther excluded from the true Godhead, or included as a meer Creature amongſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, by his being called the firſt-born of every Creature.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Objection</hi> from <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.14. where Chriſt is called the beginning of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwer.</hi> This muſt not be underſtood as if Jeſus Chriſt were the firſt of God's Creatures, but that he was the firſt that gave being or beginning to the Creatures: <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.13. <hi>I am Alpha and Omega, the beginning and the end, the firſt and the laſt.</hi> Beginning here is the firſt by whom all things had their beginning, and not the firſt of Creatures that had its begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="128" facs="tcp:32445:70"/>
                  <head>CHAP. III.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Containeth Anſwers to divers of the Socinian Arguments againſt the Deity of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>OBjection.</hi> If the Divine Nature of Chriſt were God, one with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and the Spirit; then the Father and the Spirit would be incarnate.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwer.</hi> The Union of the Divine Perſons being in Nature and Eſſence, and not in Perſon, or perſonal Properties; one Perſon in the ſame Nature, may be ſaid more properly to be incarnate than another.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Objection.</hi> If Chriſt have two Natures, then not only that Perſon that did before exiſt is the Son of God, but the holy Iſſue of the Virgin alſo, ſo that that opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion would make two Sons of God, and conſequently two Perſons in one Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Although the Divine Nature of Chriſt which preexiſted his Incarnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, be the Son of God; yet the Iſſue of the Virgin coming out of the Loins of
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:32445:70"/>
                     <hi>David,</hi> and receiving its matter from Man, cannot be naturally the Son of God, but the Son of Man: ſo that as Chriſt with reſpect to his Divine Nature, is the natural Son of God; ſo likewiſe though he was not generated after the common way of Mankind, yet being deduced out of the ſame matter, ſo far he is naturally the Son of Man. But from hence I ſee no reaſon to conclude that there are two Sons of God, or that Chriſt is two Perſons: for though the matter of Chriſt's Huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity would have made a diſtinct Perſon, if it had been generated after the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon way; yet it was never ſo, becauſe it never had its Being but in Union with the Divine Nature, when the Perſon of the Son was united to it, and ſo together became the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> who <hi>was made a quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Spirit</hi> in the one Perſon of Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.45. So that the Humanity of Chriſt was but a part of his Perſon, and no diſtinct Perſon of it ſelf; for Chriſt took on him the form of a Servant only, and not the Perſon, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.7. The Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures declare no ſuch thing as two Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, but that he took our Nature, which became a Perſon in the Divine Subſiſtence of the Son: ſo that the Perſon of Chriſt
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:32445:71"/>was not a Compound of two diſtinct Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons together, but the one Perſon of the eternal Son of God, as it were clothed with Humanity; for the whole Perſon of Chriſt, (<hi>viz.</hi> the Word and Fleſh) is repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to us, as but one only begotten Son of God, <hi>John</hi> 1.14, 18.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Objection.</hi> Had Chriſt had a Divine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in being the eternal Son of God, he needed not the Aſſiſtance of the Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, to furniſh him with a humane Nature from a Virgin, being himſelf able to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce it of her, unleſs you will ſay that his own Divine Nature was in the mean while idle.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwer. Eſtwick</hi> on <hi>Biddle</hi> in page 208, 209. anſwers this Objection: he ſaith, <q>The Holy Ghoſt had no Efficiency or Caſualty in the Incarnation of our bleſſed Saviour, which was not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to the Trinity; for as Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt are inſeparable; touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Divine Eſſence and Power of working, ſo likewiſe are they inſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable in their Operations.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <q>'Tis a common Compariſon to il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrate this Truth: Three Virgins do jointly make up a Garment for one of
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:32445:71"/>them only to wear: ſo all the three Perſons as one Cauſe, did produce the humane Nature; yet was it taken on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly into the Perſon of the Son of God. Chriſt became Man, not in regard of the Divine Nature ſimply, which is common to Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, but as it ſubſiſts in the Son of God: 'Tis true, if we reſpect the
<note n="‖" place="margin">The word Original muſt here be underſtood ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Author's ſenſe of the perſonal Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heminence of the Father, according to his perſonal Subſiſtence in the Divine Nature, and not in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to Original of time.</note> O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal of working, there is a difference, the Father as he is of himſelf, and from no other; ſo doth he work from him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, not from the Son; and the Son as he is from the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſo doth he alſo work from the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: but becauſe there is no Diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Perſons, in regard of the formal eſſential Principle of working, it follows, there is no Diſtinction or Separation of the Divine Perſons in the work it ſelf. It was therefore both an abſurd and blaſphemous Inference, and that as you ſay, from our Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, either that it was needleſs for the Holy Ghoſt to frame the Body of our
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:32445:72"/>Lord, or elſe that the Divine Nature of the Son of God was idle. Will you grant then (which by this your Reaſon muſt needs follow) becauſe Chriſt was conceived by the Holy Ghoſt, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God the Father was idle, and not the prime Worker of this marvellous Conception.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>What is here cited out of this learned Man, ſufficiently ſhews the Weakneſs of this Objection againſt the Deity of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Wherein is anſwered ſome Objections againſt the Scriptures that prove the Deity of the Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>OBjection</hi> to <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19. <hi>Baptizing them in the Name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> It cannot be rightly inferred, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Holy Spirit is here ranked with the Father and the Son, therefore he is equal to them; by this account when the Apoſtle 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.21. ſaith, <hi>I charge thee</hi> (Gr. <hi>I obteſt</hi>) <hi>before God and the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:32445:72"/>Chriſt, and the elect Angels, that thou obſerve theſe things without Prejudice, doing nothing by Partiality;</hi> joyning the elect Angels with the Father and the Son: this would imply that the elect Angels are equal with the Father and the Son.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwer.</hi> There is not the ſame reaſon to imply from this of <hi>Timothy,</hi> that the elect Angels are equal to the Father and the Son, as there is for the Holy Spirit's Equality with them, from <hi>Matth.</hi> 28. For if we rightly conſider theſe two Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, we may eaſily ſee that they are not Parallels; but that the Holy Spirit, and the elect Angels, are joined together with the Father and the Son, upon far different accounts; the one are ranked together, not as Equals with the Father and the Son, but becauſe they are miniſtring Spirits that have their Eyes on the Church of God, and behold the Order and Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline of it, whoſe Work and Office is to attend upon it, and be familiar about it, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.10. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.7. Inſomuch that we ought to be very careful of ſpeaking or doing any unſeemly thing that might hinder the Miniſtration of thoſe bleſſed and Holy Spirits. Now for this cauſe <hi>Paul</hi> exhorteth <hi>Timothy</hi> to obſerve thoſe
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:32445:73"/>things, as in the Preſence of God, and of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and the Holy An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels; and therefore they are ranked toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and not as Equals in Nature and Divine Worſhip; for they refuſe to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume that Glory which is peculiarly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to God alone, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22. So that this Text relates to the Inſpection of Angels, into the Obedience of the Saints, in the way of which Protection is miniſtred to them by the Angels, who are ſaid to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camp round about thoſe that fear the Lord, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.7. Or elſe the Apoſtle ſhews, by ranking theſe three together, that the Angels are Witneſſes to this Charge, though in all things elſe they cannot be, unleſs they could ſearch the Heart, and try the Reins. And why may not the Apoſtle take them in as Witneſſes, as <hi>Moſes</hi> did, who called Heaven and Earth, <hi>viz.</hi> God, Angels, and Men, joining them as Witneſſes againſt <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that he had ſet before them <hi>Life and Death?</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Deut.</hi> 30.19. But the Holy Spirit, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28. is not ranked together with the Father and the Son, only as a miniſtring Spirit, or as one that beareth Witneſs together with them in any mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but to be equally honoured with them
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:32445:73"/>both: for in this Ordinance of Baptiſm, wherein we worſhip God, in acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what he hath done for us in order to Salvation, we are commanded to aſcribe it to the Father, Son, and Holy Spirit. And there is reaſon for it: For though the Father had accepted the Merits of his Son, on conditions of true Faith and Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; yet if the Holy Spirit had not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken to work theſe Conditions in us, we had been loſt; ſo that we are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged, both from the Work it ſelf, and the Command of God, to attribute the ſame Honour to the one as to the other: and herein chiefly lies the Difference of this Text from that of <hi>Timothy,</hi> becauſe this commands Divine Worſhip to be given to the Holy Ghoſt, together with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and the Son, which declares his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Nature.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Objection</hi> to <hi>Iſa.</hi> 6.9, 10. compared with <hi>Acts</hi> 28.25, 26, 27. To theſe two Scriptures I have met with <hi>Biddle's</hi> Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections, ſtated and anſwered ready to my Hand by Mr. <hi>Eſtwick</hi> in his Confuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Biddle</hi>'s Confeſſion of Faith, Page 307. whoſe Words I ſhall prefer rather than my own.</p>
                  <pb n="136" facs="tcp:32445:74"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Biddle;</hi> 
                     <q>In the one place <hi>the Lord ſaid,</hi> in the other <hi>the Holy Ghoſt;</hi> therefore the Adverſaries do conclude, the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit is the Lord. This arguing is very frivolous: for at this rate I may conclude that <hi>Moſes</hi> is the Lord; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.11. Iſraelites are called God's People, <hi>ver.</hi> 7. God calls them the People of <hi>Moſes:</hi> and <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65.1. <hi>I am found of them that ſought me not,</hi> Rom. 10.20. <hi>Iſaiah</hi> is more bold, and ſaith, <hi>I was found of them that asked not after me;</hi> therefore <hi>Iſaiah</hi> is the Lord. God is ſaid <hi>by his Power to ſave us,</hi> 2 Tim. 1.8, 9. <hi>Paul</hi> attributes the ſame to himſelf, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.22. and to <hi>Timothy,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.16. therefore <hi>Paul,</hi> yea <hi>Timothy,</hi> is God. If the Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries ſay theſe things are otherwiſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed unto the Lord, than to the Men aforeſaid: I anſwer, it is more than the Texts themſelves hold forth, which neither expreſs nor intimate any ſuch thing. If they ſay, that if not in theſe, yet other Texts, and the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the thing it ſelf doth ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly teach it: I reply, that I can make the ſame Anſwer, touching the Lord and his Holy Spirit; but it is well that
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:32445:74"/>there is ſuch an Intimation in the Texts themſelves; for in the one the Lord ſpake to <hi>Iſaiah</hi> in a Viſion; in the other, That the Holy Ghoſt ſpake them by <hi>Iſaiah</hi> to the Fathers. Theſe two are different, ſince <hi>Iſaiah</hi> only heard theſe Words in the Viſion; for had the Fathers been there, why ſhould God bid <hi>Iſaiah</hi> go, and tell them to the People; <hi>Paul</hi> aſcribes theſe Words to the Holy Ghoſt, to intimate only, that whatſoever was ſpoken in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, was recorded by the Inſpiration of the Holy Spirit, and ſo ſpoken by him.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwer.</hi> 
                     <q>Your Eluſions to avoid the ſtrength of the Argument are vain, and your Examples taken out of the Scriptures, are <hi>fallacia parium,</hi> are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like to this in hand. Sometimes an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument ſpeaks in the Name of the great God that ſent him. This is your Evaſion, therefore it muſt be ſo taken; <hi>Iſa.</hi> 6. compared with <hi>Acts</hi> 28. this is a plain Fallacy. <hi>Exod.</hi> 32. <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> calleth the Iſraelites <hi>God's People in Covenant with him;</hi> and God calls them <hi>the People of Moſes,</hi> being under the Curſe of the Law, by reaſon of their Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try;
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:32445:75"/>and becauſe he was God's Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to bring them out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and to conduct them in the Wilderneſs; it is apparent to every one, and the Text holds it forth, that they were otherwiſe God's People, and other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the People of <hi>Moſes,</hi> he being a finite, diſtinct and ſeparate Subſtance from the Lord God Almighty. We grant, that becauſe theſe are different, therefore it would be abſurd to infer, that <hi>Moſes</hi> is the Lord: where is the Holy Ghoſt called God's Servant, or God's Inſtrument?</q>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <p>The ſecond place, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65. 1. with <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.20. in the one place it is ſaid, <hi>I am found of thoſe that ſought me not;</hi> ſo ſaith God, in another place, <hi>Iſaiah ſaith the ſame Words;</hi> therefore <hi>Iſaiah</hi> is the Lord. It is clear, the Lord by <hi>Iſaiah</hi> foretold the Converſion of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and that he by his Grace mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved them to ſeek him, before they looked for Salvation by Chriſt. St. <hi>Paul</hi> relating the ſame Text, ſheweth that <hi>Iſaiah</hi> freely ſpake of the calling of the <hi>Gentiles.</hi> Who is ſo blind, as not to ſee clearly, that <hi>Iſaiah</hi> uſed thoſe Words, as God's Meſſenger in the
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:32445:75"/>Name of the Lord? and what is more uſual with the Prophets than to uſe ſuch Words, to gain due reſpect to their Words? <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord.</hi> This Example then is not parallel to that under Debate; it is not agreeable to the Scripture-Language for the Holy Ghoſt to ſpeak in the Name of the Lord.</p>
                     <p>The third, touching God's ſaving, and <hi>Paul's</hi> ſaving, is as unfit, and as far from the Mark, as the former; for evident it is, that <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf could not plant, except God gave the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and he always aſcribes Salvation to God, as the principal cauſe thereof, and confeſſeth that he is but God's In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument, by whoſe Miniſtry he ſaved much People. A Creature cannot be properly called God, nor doth any other Scripture, or the nature of the thing it ſelf teach any ſuch thing; nor doth the New Teſtament, unleſs by quoting Texts out of the old; Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows being gone, uſe ſuch. Expreſſions, leſt we ſhould conceive Gods ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate to the High God: This you grant, but you add withal, <hi>That you can make the ſame anſwer, touching the Lord and
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:32445:76"/>the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> You have the Face not to bluſh at ſtrange Anſwers: What is it that you cannot write? But if you ſhould be peremptory in ſuch an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, you cannot make it good. What Line in God's Words, yea, what proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility can you produce for this Parallel. It is great Reaſon that if a Man will forſake the Common Road, that he ſhould give a good account of his going into By-Ways, not trodden by Paſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers many hundred years together: It is well, that by your own Confeſſion, the other alledged-Scriptures, do clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſtinguiſh betwixt the principal Cauſe and Inſtrument; and it will be requiſite, if you look to be credited, that you demonſtrate by the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of the Text, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 6. or by ſome other convincing Proof, that the Holy Spirit is a created Angel; and that he is in a proper Notion God's Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor, and his Inſtrument to inſpire the Holy Prophets, to diſcharge their Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſy, which is a Task, I know, impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to be performed by you.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>There is</hi> (ſay you) <hi>an intimation in the Texts themſelves; for</hi> Iſaiah <hi>only heard the words in a Viſion, and was to tell them
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:32445:76"/>to the People not preſent with him:</hi> But <hi>Paul aſcribes them to the Holy Ghoſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe whatſoever was ſpoken in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, is recorded by the inſpiration of the Holy Ghoſt, and ſo ſpoken by him.</hi> This is then his meaning: Theſe Words were from the Lord as firſt delivered by him to <hi>Iſaiah;</hi> and from the Holy Ghoſt, as they were penn'd in the Scripture. This is a ſenſleſs and groundleſs Fig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as though the Holy Ghoſt ſpoke not as well to <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> in that Viſion to deliver his Meſſage to the People, as to inſpire him to write infallibly what he had heard in that Divine Viſion. Is there any intimation of difference in theſe to be diſtinguiſhed Actions? and as tho the Lord himſelf did not both? The Current of the Scripture is to this purpoſe, without a ſhadow of Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction. Take that one place, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.20, 21. <hi>No Prophecy of Scripture is of any private Interpretation.</hi> Prophets pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied not to their Auditors their own Senſe, but God's Mind: <hi>For Prophecy came not at any time by the Will of Man: but holy Men of God ſpake as they were moved by the Holy Ghost.</hi> So that they were acted by the Spirit, not only in
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:32445:77"/>writing, but in ſpeaking; yea, thoſe Prophets which were not God's Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, as <hi>Elias</hi> and <hi>Eliſha,</hi> yet were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired by the Holy Ghoſt: Such vain Fancies as yours are, Mr. <hi>Biddle,</hi> can pleaſe none but vain and unſetled Heads.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>To this I add, that the Lord's ſpeaking to <hi>Iſaiah</hi> in the Viſion <hi>chap.</hi> 6. and the Holy Ghoſt ſpeaking by him to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, <hi>Acts</hi> 28. cannot be underſtood, that at two different times the Lord and the Holy Ghoſt ſpeake to the Prophet. 1. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Holy Ghoſt did not only inſpire the Prophet afterwards to record in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his Meſſage to the Fathers, but by Word ſent the Prophet, ſaying, <hi>Go unto this People, and ſay, &amp;c.</hi> So that the Prophet was to ſay to the Fathers, what the Holy Ghoſt had ſaid by word to him in the Viſion. 2dly. Becauſe <hi>John</hi> tells us, <hi>Joh.</hi> 12.41. that <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſaid theſe things when he ſaw his Glory, and ſpake of him; whereby it is manifeſt, that the Prophet ſpake theſe things unto the Fathers from the Mouth of the Lord, and the Holy Ghoſt in the Viſion. And foraſmuch as the Apoſtle tells us, that it was the Holy Ghoſt which ſpake in that Viſion, it ſhews,
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:32445:77"/>that he is the ſame Lord and <hi>Jehovah</hi> that the <hi>Seraphims</hi> worſhipped.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Objection</hi> to 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.16. <hi>Know ye not that ye are the Temple of God, and that the Spirit of God dwelleth in you?</hi> It is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected by ſome from this place, that the Holy Spirit is God, in that our Body is ſaid to be his Temple. I anſwer, That it would follow, could it be proved, that our Body is ſo the Temple of the Holy Spirit, as to be his by the higheſt Intereſt, and primarily dedicated to his Honour — they are his by Inhabitation. The Spirit is diſpoſed of, and given by God to us, and conſequently he is ours by In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, not we his: And accordingly the Apoſtle concludeth from thence, that we ought with our Body to glorify not the Spirit, but God, who is openly diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed from the Spirit, and declared to be the Proprietor of our Body.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Firſt, They ſay indeed that our Body is not the Temple of the Holy Ghoſt by Intereſt, but they cannot prove it, for our being his by Inhabitation, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes not our being his by Intereſt, any more than God's dwelling in the Temple which <hi>Solomon</hi> built, did exclude his high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:32445:78"/>Intereſt to it, and its chief Dedicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to his Glory; but our being his firſt by Intereſt, makes us his by Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</p>
                  <p>Secondly; Though the Holy Spirit be given of God, and ſo by donation beco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth ours; yet neither doth this exclude us from being his by the higheſt Right; for the Holy Spirit's being ſent, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to us, ſheweth his Office and not his Eſſence, of which I ſhall ſpeak hereafter: and if his being ſent doth not diſprove his Divine Eſſence, it cannot diſprove us from being his by the higheſt Right, which is in effect the ſame.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly; Nor doth it thence follow, that becauſe the Apoſtle ſaith, we muſt glorify God in our Body, that therefore he (not the Spirit) is the Proprietor of our Bodies. For if the Holy Ghoſt had a leſſer Right to our Body, as a Creature only helping with us to worſhip God, our Body could not be properly ſaid to be his Temple; for no Temple beareth the Name of the Worſhippers (which then with us the Spirit would be) but of him that dwelleth therein, and is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped: and therefore ſeeing that our Body is the Temple of the Holy Ghoſt,
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:32445:78"/>and it conſequently follows, that he is to be glorified therein, it then agrees with the Apoſtle's words, <hi>Glorify God in your Body.</hi> And to ſay that the Holy Ghoſt inhabits the Temple of God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.16. and receives the ſame Worſhip, either defiles, and diſhonours his Temple, and gives his Glory to another, or acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth the Holy Spirit to be God: And therefore as we muſt not preſume to think that the Holy Apoſtle ſhould ſo diſhonour the Temple of God, and pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute his Holy Name, as to aſcribe the name of a Creature to it; So we may conclude, that our Body which is the Temple of God (as appears in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.16.) would not be aſſerted to be the Temple of the Holy Ghoſt, unleſs by his higheſt Intereſt as he is God. And though our Adverſaries would have the words [Glorify God in your Body] to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force the Senſe of the Text, in favour of their opinion; yet they have a far different Signification, than to bring in God as Proprietor of our Body, in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to the Holy Ghoſt's higheſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt to us: For the Apoſtle does not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend by theſe words either to exclude the Holy Spirit from the higheſt Intereſt
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:32445:79"/>to our Bodies, or to intimate to us, that God and the Holy Ghoſt are two dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Eſſences, but he rather deſigns, by the word <hi>God</hi> indefinitely ſpoken (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of the Holy Spirit before mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned) to include alſo the Father and the Son; that not only the Holy Ghoſt, but all three Divine Perſons ſhould be glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in our Body, and in our Spirit, which are God's. Now let us ſum up the whole, and ſee what our Adverſaries gain by theſe Objections. Firſt, I have ſhewed that our being his by Inhabitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, excludes not our being his by Intereſt. Nor, Secondly, does the Donation of the Holy Ghoſt, or his being ſent, exclude our being his by the higheſt Right. Nor yet, Thirdly, do theſe words <hi>Glorify God in your Body,</hi> deſtroy the primacy of the Holy Spirit, to our Bodies: And if neither of theſe diſprove that our Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is the Temple of the Holy Ghoſt by the higheſt Right, and as primarily dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to his Glory; then nothing yet they have ſaid, can diſprove his Deity from this Scripture: for, as it is confeſſed, that to prove the one is to prove the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; ſo not to diſprove the one, is not to diſprove the other.</p>
                  <pb n="147" facs="tcp:32445:79"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Objection</hi> to 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.17. <hi>Now the Lord is that Spirit: and where the Spirit of the Lord is, there is Liberty.</hi> By [that Spirit] is not here meant the third Perſon in the Holy Trinity; but the Expreſſion im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plieth the ſame Spirit that was before in the 6th Verſe, oppoſed to the Letter, and conſequently the Myſtery or hidden Senſe of the Law, denoted by the Letter; for thus the word <hi>Spirit</hi> is to be taken, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.29. <hi>Circumciſion is that of the Heart, in the Spirit, and not in the Letter.</hi> And <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.6. <hi>But now we are delivered from the Law, that being dead wherein we were held; that we ſhould ſerve in newneſs of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and not in the oldneſs of the Letter.</hi> And <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.8. where <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> is myſtically and ſpiritually called <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Egypt.</hi> Wherefore the Senſe of the Words of <hi>Paul</hi> is this, namely, That the Lord Chriſt is the Myſtery, Life, Scope and Kernel of the Law; as being both fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told therein, and prefigured by the Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies thereof.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwer,</hi> Firſt; As they ſay <hi>Spirit</hi> is not put for his <hi>Perſon,</hi> in <hi>ver.</hi> 6, 8. but for his Effects and Operations, or Goſpel-Miniſtration; however it cannot from
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:32445:80"/>thence follow, that <hi>Spirit</hi> in <hi>ver.</hi> 3, 17, 18. is put only for his Effects, and not his Perſon.</p>
                  <p n="1">1ſt. Becauſe the Effects of the Spirit, (<hi>viz.</hi> his Writing, and Goſpel-Liberty) is joined together with the Spirit; and therefore the Spirit here is not put for his Effects, but for Himſelf; and ſo it is in <hi>ver.</hi> 18. where it's ſaid, <hi>We are changed into the ſame Image, from glory to glory, even as by the Spirit of the Lord.</hi> [Margent, <hi>Of the Lord the Spirit.</hi>] Here alſo the effect of the Spirit, to wit, our change into the ſame Image of Chriſt's Glory, being joined to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the Spirit (there is a neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that by Spirit muſt be meant his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and not Effect.) And this is noted to us by the Tranſlators of our Bible, in writing [Spirit] with a great Letter, when for his Perſon, and with a little Letter, when the Spirit is put for his Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, which may be ſeen in this Chapter, where thrice <hi>ver.</hi> 3, 17, 18. the Perſon of the Spirit is underſtood, and thrice his Effects, <hi>ver.</hi> 6, 8.</p>
                  <p n="2">2dly. That the Lord Chriſt, is the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, Life, Scope, and Kernel of the Law, as being both foretold therein, and prefigured by the Ceremonies thereof,
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:32445:80"/>may be granted to them, but not that this is properly intended by thoſe Words, [<hi>The Lord is that Spirit</hi>] as pointing thereby only to his Effects in <hi>ver.</hi> 6, 8. 1ſt, Becauſe we may better refer thoſe Words to that Spirit, which is put for his Perſon in <hi>ver.</hi> 3. which, as it there ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, is the efficient cauſe of the Epiſtle of Chriſt written both in the Hearts of the Apoſtles, and of the Church of <hi>Corinth, ver.</hi> 2, 3. So that [<hi>that Spirit</hi>] is there firſt put for his Perſon, and the efficient cauſe of the Effects, for which it is put in <hi>ver.</hi> 6, 8. and afterwards in <hi>ver.</hi> 17, 18. being joined with his effects, and thereby differenc'd as the efficient cauſe and Perſon of the Spirit, is ſaid to be the Lord, or, as it is expreſt, the Lord is that Spirit: and therefore if they will have theſe words [that Spirit] <hi>ver.</hi> 17. to point at Spirit before mentioned in the Chapter, it muſt then be referred to <hi>Verſe</hi> 3d, Perſon to Perſon, and not Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to effect. 2dly, Nothing is more plain than that Spirit in <hi>ver.</hi> 17. muſt be taken for his Perſon, becauſe his Effects are ſo ſtrongly joined to him, <hi>viz.</hi> Liberty, which the Goſpel it ſelf, (<hi>viz.</hi> the Letter of it) does not give, but by the Power
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:32445:81"/>and Efficacy of the Holy Spirit. So that it's clear from the Text, that by theſe words, [the Lord is that Spirit] muſt be underſtood the Perſon of the Spirit in the Unity of Eſſence with the ſecond Perſon, the Son of God. 3dly, In Verſe 18. We are ſaid <hi>with open face to behold as in a Glaſs,</hi> (<hi>viz.</hi> of the Goſpel) <hi>the Glory of the Lord,</hi> by whom <hi>we are changed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſame Image from Glory to Glory, even as by the Spirit of the Lord,</hi> [or <hi>the Lord the Spirit.</hi>] Which whither it be meant of our being more and more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed in the Spirits of our Minds in this World, or, as I rather take it, from the Glory of the Lord, which we behold in the Glaſs of the Goſpel, to our eternal Glory; yet it is by the Lord the Spirit, the efficient Cauſe of this change, and therefore it is not the Effect, or Grace of the Spirit only, but his Perſon.</p>
                  <p n="4">4ly. The Dutch Tranſlators read <hi>ver.</hi> 17. The Lord is [the Spirit] and not [that Spirit] and ſo it does not point to Spirit before-named, but is to be underſtood as the Words lie in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; and thus it cuts off the Relation, and is not governed by what is meant by Spirit going before. So that I ſee no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:32445:81"/>wherefore theſe Objections ſhould weaken the Proof of the Deity of the Holy Spirit from this Scripture.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Objection</hi> to 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.7. <hi>For there are three that bear Record in Heaven, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the Word, and the Holy Ghoſt, and theſe three are one.</hi> The Sum of what is objected againſt this Scripture, being laid down, and learnedly as well as largely confuted by Mr. <hi>Francis Chinell</hi> in his Book of the Divine Trinunity, I ſhall make a Recital of his Words ſo far as it is needful to our purpoſe, from page 251, to Page 256. <q>It is objected by ſome, that the words, <hi>Theſe three are one,</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.7. are not to be found in ſome ancient Copies, and therefore it will not be ſafe to build a Point of ſuch Weight and Conſequence upon ſuch a weak Foundation.</q>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſwer.</hi> It is true that theſe Words are not to be
<note n="*" place="margin">
                           <hi>Si Syrum ceteroſque ſequimur, vel hiatus ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittitur, vel <gap reason="foreign">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap> quae imprimis elegans turbatur. Mihi qui ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem primò uſurparunt in ſacris licentiam <gap reason="foreign">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap> videntur.</hi> Heinſius, <hi>in locum.</hi>
                        </note> found in the Syriac Editi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but they who ſpeak moſt modeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, do acknowledg that <hi>the Syriac Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is not authentick.</hi>
                        <pb n="152" facs="tcp:32445:82"/>Learned <hi>Heinſius</hi> is much offended with that Edition, as appears by his Anno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations upon 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.7. And if we conſult the Scriptures, and compare this Text with the following Verſes, and with ſome other places of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which are more plain, and then add the Teſtimony and Interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the ancient and reverend Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors of the Church, concerning the Words in queſtion; we ſhall beable to paſs a right Judgment upon the point in hand.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Firſt,</hi> The Equality of the number of Witneſſes, ſutes very right, <hi>three</hi> Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes on Earth, and <hi>three</hi> in Heaven.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Secondly,</hi> The oppoſition between the Quality of the Witneſſes <hi>on Earth,</hi> and Witneſſes <hi>in Heaven;</hi> and yet their ſweet <hi>Harmony</hi> and Agreement in one Teſtimony; <hi>all ſix bear Witneſs to one and the ſame Truth.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The <hi>Diverſity</hi> of the very <hi>Nature</hi> of thoſe three who bear Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs on Earth, and the Unity of their Divine Nature, who bear Witneſs in Heaven, is very conſiderable, and it is excellently expreſſed in the Variation of the Phraſe; <hi>Theſe three are one,</hi> ver.
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:32445:82"/>7. and theſe three agree <hi>in one;</hi> name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in one Teſtimony, ver. 8. <hi>Though their Nature be different, yet their Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony is the ſame.</hi> But it is objected, that the <hi>Complutenſian</hi> Bible ſaith of the Heavenly Witneſſes, that <hi>theſe three agree in one,</hi> ver. 7. I humbly offer this Satisfaction to pious and learned Men; That we have good reaſon to believe, that there is an imprudent Addition in the <hi>Complutenſian</hi> Bible, rather than an Omiſſion of ſo many ancient and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved Bibles; and therefore it is fit that that Addition ſhould be expunged out of that one Copy, by the concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Teſtimony of ſo many Copies. Moreover, it is clear by the joint Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of other Copies, that the words <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> are omitted in <hi>ver.</hi> 7. and the words <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, belong to <hi>ver.</hi> 8. and therefore there is an inexcuſable Omiſſion, and an imprudent Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition in that cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt
<note n="†" place="margin">
                           <hi>Merces ſatis fallaces vendit officina Chr.</hi> Plantini Antverpiae <hi>in editione</hi> 1584. <hi>excuſa &amp; cum</hi> Bib. Ar. Mont. Vulgat. Joh. 8.17, 18.</note> Edition.</p>
                     <p>But then it is fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther objected, that theſe Words, <hi>Theſe three are one,</hi> are
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:32445:83"/>wanting in ſome other Greek Copies. For Anſwer I proceed in my Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Fourthly,</hi> If we look upon the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-Account in other places, we ſhall find it exactly agreeable to the Account in this place, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.7.</p>
                     <p>In <hi>John</hi> 8. our Saviour pleads that <hi>two Witneſſes in Law were ſufficient for the Proof of any Point,</hi> John 8.17. and in <hi>ver.</hi> 10. ſaith he, <hi>I am one, and my Father that ſent me is another;</hi> they are two Witneſſes, and yet but one God, <hi>I and my Father are one,</hi> John 10.30. <hi>One in Power, and therefore one in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: He ſpeaks not of the Spirit, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Chriſt was not yet glorified;</hi> nor was the Spirit yet manifeſted by that eminent and glorious Miſſion and Effu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, which was to follow after the Aſcenſion of our bleſſed Lord. <hi>But he did foretel that the third Witneſs was to be ſent from the Father by the Son,</hi> John 15.26. <hi>But when the Comforter is come whom I will ſend unto you from the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, even the Spirits of Truth,</hi> which proceedeth from the Father, <hi>He ſhall teſtify of me.</hi> I might add to theſe Teſtimonies all other places of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:32445:83"/>wherein all the three Witneſſes are named together, and then produce all the places which have been former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cited in this Book, to prove the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſential Trinunity of thoſe Heavenly Witneſſes.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Fifthly,</hi> The Copulative <hi>[and]</hi> in the beginning of the verſe, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.8. doth very fitly connect the whole ſeventh Verſe with the eight, as they are printed in our ordinary Tranſlation.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Sixthly, Hierom</hi> doth aſſure us that <hi>the Words in queſtion were expunged by the Arians, becauſe the few Words do hold forth an undeniable Proof of the Divine and Coeſſential Trinunity of thoſe Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Witneſſes.</hi> And divers other learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and judicious Men conceive that theſe Words were blotted out in the time of <hi>Conſtantius</hi> and <hi>Valens</hi> the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors, who were ſworn Enemies of the bleſſed Trinity, and profeſſed Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons of Arianiſm.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Seventhly,</hi> The Hereticks did blot out thoſe Words,
<note n="‖" place="margin">
                           <hi>Vide</hi> Ambroſ. <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>de ſpiritu ſancto. cap.</hi> 11. <hi>jurati verita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis hoſtes lucem banc non tulerunt ideoque eraſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt. Vide</hi> Heinſium <hi>in</hi> 1 <hi>Job.</hi> 5.7.</note> 
                        <hi>John</hi> 4.24. <hi>God is a Spirit,</hi> as <hi>Ambroſe</hi>
                        <pb n="156" facs="tcp:32445:84"/>aſſures us; and therefore this Practice of repugning ſuch Words in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as did refute their Errors, was too common amongſt the Hereticks of old, as we might prove by Witneſſes enough, if that were our Buſineſs.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Eighthly,</hi> Theſe Words, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.7. are to be found in Copies of great An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity and beſt Credit.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note n="*" place="margin">Athanaſ. <hi>Tom.</hi> 1. <hi>Pag.</hi> 91, 92, 93.</note> 
                        <hi>Ninthly,</hi> This Text is cited by the ancient Fathers, by <hi>Athanaſius</hi> in his Diſpute with <hi>Arius</hi> at the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> and <hi>Arius</hi> never denied it for to be Scripture, which certainly he would have done, if there had been any doubt made of it in the primitive times. It is cited by <hi>Cyprian</hi> in his Book <hi>de <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitate Eccleſiae. Paxillus</hi> in his Book <hi>de Monomachia,</hi> proves by an Induction of the learned Doctors of the Church, both before and ſince <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanaſius,</hi> that the Doctrine of the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſential Trinunity of theſe Heavenly Witneſſes, was generally received by all that were eſteemed orthodox and pious in the Church of Chriſt. <hi>Calo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vius</hi> alſo in his <hi>Fides patrum ante Concili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um
<pb n="257" facs="tcp:32445:84"/>Nicenum,</hi> gives in a Catalogue for the Satisfaction of all that deſire Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution in this weighty point. <hi>[See Mr.</hi> Eſtwick <hi>of the Godhead of the Holy Ghoſt. Dr.</hi> Alting <hi>his Vindication of this Text in his Confutation of the Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covian Catechiſm.</hi>]</p>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. V.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Wherein are anſwered ſome Objections infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by our Adverſaries from divers Texts of Scripture, to diſprove the Deity of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>OBjection</hi> from <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.27. <hi>All things are delivered unto me of my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and no Man knoweth the Son but the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; neither knoweth any Man the Father ſave the Son, and he to whomſoever the Son will reveal him.</hi> How could this be true, were the Holy Spirit a Divine Perſon diſtinct from the Father and the Son, and in all things equal unto both? for ſome other beſides the Father would have known the Son, and ſome other beſides the Son would have known the Father, namely the Holy Spirit.</p>
                  <pb n="158" facs="tcp:32445:85"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwer. Firſt,</hi> We muſt not underſtand this Text in the ſtricteſt ſenſe, as if Chriſt the Son of God was not known at that time by any beſides the Father.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. He was known as Man, <hi>John</hi> 7.27. <hi>We know this Man whence he is.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. He was known as the Son of God, <hi>John</hi> 1.41, 49. Said <hi>Andrew</hi> to <hi>Simon Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, We have found the Meſſias.</hi>—Natha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel <hi>anſwered and ſaid unto him, Rabbi, Thou art the Son of God, thou art the King of</hi> Iſrael. His Diſciples believed on him, <hi>chap.</hi> 2.11. and others, <hi>chap.</hi> 4.53.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> Neither is this Scripture to be conſidered, as though Chriſt's Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and others then had not ſome Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of God the Father; for in <hi>John</hi> 6.44, 45. it is ſaid, <hi>No Man can come to me, except the Father draw him.—Every Man therefore that hath heard, and hath learned of the Father, cometh unto me.</hi> So that no Man could come to Chriſt without ſome Knowledg and Teachings of God the Father.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thirdly,</hi> It then follows that if this Text is not to be underſtood totally to exclude all Men from ſome Knowledg of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and the Son, until afterwards they ſhould be revealed; then it intends only
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:32445:85"/>to exclude them from ſome ſpecial and peculiar Knowledg which they have, and in reference to their revealing of each other.</p>
                  <p>The Father knoweth the Son, and the Son the Father, in a different manner from all Creatures, in that they know each other perfectly of their own Self-Knowledg: Yet the Words of Chriſt are not to be taken ſimply of that peculiar Knowledg, but with reference to the Revelation which the Father makes of the Son, and Chriſt of the Father, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears in <hi>ver.</hi> 25. where Chriſt ſaith, <hi>I thank thee, O Father, Lord of Heaven and Earth, becauſe thou haſt hid theſe things from the Wiſe and Prudent, and haſt revealed them unto Babes.</hi> And now it follows that Chriſt tells us, <hi>No Man knoweth the Son [but] the Father; neither knoweth any Man the Father [ſave] the Son, and he to whom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever the Son will reveal him:</hi> As if he had ſaid, <hi>No Man knoweth the Son,</hi> ſo as to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal him ſavingly <hi>[but] the Father, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth any Man</hi> (after the ſame manner) <hi>know the Father [ſave] the Son only.</hi> And this ſuits with the following Invitation for burthened Souls to come to Chriſt, as to one that can reveal and open the Father's
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:32445:86"/>Heart, wherein they may (through him) have reſt for their weary Souls. <hi>ver.</hi> 28, &amp;c. <hi>chap.</hi> 1.18. <hi>ch.</hi> 6.41.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fourthly;</hi> Having opened the Text, and ſhewed that it muſt not be poſitively underſtood, I ſhall now anſwer directly to what is objected concerning the Holy Spirit. And,</p>
                  <p>Firſt, I ſhall note, that if Men who are named, (and only intended) are but in part excluded, then the Holy Ghoſt, who is not named (neither intended) cannot from theſe words be excluded from the knowledg of the Father and the Son.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, We muſt not conceive that the Holy Spirit is excluded from the Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip of this Knowledg which the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and the Son have of each other, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is not mentioned; for the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the Spirit was not yet come. I ſaid before that here we are not to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand Knowledg ſimply, but with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to Revelation; and this was now miniſtred by the Father and the Son more ſecretly through the Spirit, but apparently (to aſſure his Diſciples, and convince the Sons of Men that Jeſus was the Chriſt the Son of God, that was ſent forth from
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:32445:86"/>the Boſom of the Father, to declare his Will) by ſuch ſenſible, viſible and exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Teſtimonies, as would leave all Men without excuſe: The Father bearing witneſs to the Son, twice by a Voice from Heaven, and the Son by the mighty Works he wrought in the Father's Name, bore witneſs of him, and gave undeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able proof of his ſpecial Miſſion from God, and that he was the Meſſiah that was to come. <hi>John</hi> 1.18. <hi>chap.</hi> 5.17, 36, 43. <hi>chap.</hi> 14.10. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.17, 18. <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.17. And this was the very reaſon that ſo little mention was made of the Holy Ghoſt, the Myſtery of God being left more fully to be opened and revealed af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Chriſt's Aſcenſion, by that Divine Perſon, whoſe proper Work it was to confirm the Teſtimony of the Father and the Son, that went before. So that the Holy Ghoſt was not omitted by Chriſt, becauſe he was not in the Unity of that Knowledg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>; but becauſe the time for the great work of his miniſterial Revelation was not yet come. So that no Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on can be laid on this Scripture in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to the Deity of the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
                  <pb n="162" facs="tcp:32445:87"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Objection</hi> from 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.12. <hi>Now we have received not the Spirit of the World, but the Spirit which is of God.</hi> The Spirit which is of God is God's Effect, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends upon him, and ſo is inferiour to him.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwer.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.10, 11, 12. <hi>But God hath revealed them to us by his Spirit — For what Man knoweth the things of a Man ſave the Spirit of a Man which is in him? Even ſo the things of God knoweth no Man, but the Spirit of God. Now we have recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the Spirit which is of God, that we might know the things that are freely given to us of God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Firſt, The Apoſtle uſeth this Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon not to demonſtrate the Being of God, but to ſhew that we cannot know the things of God till the Spirit of God reveals them to us.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, They cannot from thence conclude that the Spirit of God is God's Effect, and ſo is inferiour to him, any more than that the Spirit of Man is alſo the Effect of Man, and ſo inferiour to Man: But if they will run the Compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to demonſtrate the Being of God, we muſt then conclude, that as the Spirit or
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:32445:87"/>Soul of Man (being the moſt excellent part of his Nature) is eſſential to his Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; ſo by this Rule is the Spirit of God alſo, which proves his Deity.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Objection</hi> from <hi>John</hi> 1.32. <hi>And</hi> John <hi>bare Record, ſaying, I ſaw the Spirit de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending from Heaven like a Dove, and it abode upon him.</hi> The Spirit is not God, becauſe he changed place, and deſcended in a bodily Shape.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Firſt, This Deſcenſion of the Holy Ghoſt diſproveth not his Deity, becauſe the like hath been ſaid of God, in <hi>Gen.</hi> 11.5. <hi>And the Lord came down to ſee the City and the Tower.</hi> And in <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.21. <hi>I will go down now, and ſee whether they have done altogether according to the cry of it. And the Lord deſcended on Mount</hi> Sinai, Exod. 34.5.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, Although the moſt High God hath no ſhape, yet he appeared to <hi>Abraham</hi> in the Shape of a Man, repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting his Aſſumption of that Nature, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.2, 22. <hi>chap.</hi> 19.1. and therefore this Objection againſt the Deity of the Holy Ghoſt is of no weight; and not only from the aforeſaid Example, but alſo becauſe we find, that when the Holy
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:32445:88"/>Ghoſt fell on the Diſciples, that there were cloven Tongues, which was an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and viſible ſign of the Gifts and O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration of the Holy Spirit, and did nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther betoken his corporal Subſtance, nor was a deſcription of his Shape. In like manner the Holy Spirit's deſcending in the bodily ſhape of a Dove, did neither betoken his corporal Subſtance nor change of place; but like <hi>Noah</hi>'s Dove, Peace and Glad-tidings towards Men. For <hi>Peter</hi> in his firſt Epiſtle, <hi>chap.</hi> 3.20, 21. makes the Waters of <hi>Noah</hi> a Type of Goſpel-Baptiſm; and then, as after <hi>Noah</hi>'s Ark did reſt upon dry Ground, a Dove was the miniſter of glad-tidings to him and all his Houſe: ſo God was pleaſed in anſwer to that Type (and as was fitteſt to repreſent the Innocency of Chriſt) after his Baptiſm and Salvation from the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, to ſend the Holy Ghoſt to him in the ſame ſhape: and afterwards to his Diſciples, to miniſter ſuch divine Power and Comfort as might ſtrengthen, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, and incourage them to that work which God had appointed for them: ſo that there is not the leaſt reaſon from this Scripture to deny the Deity of the Holy Spirit.</p>
                  <pb n="165" facs="tcp:32445:88"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Objection</hi> from <hi>John</hi> 16.13. <hi>Howbeit, when He the Spirit of Truth is come, he will guide you into all Truth: for he ſhall not ſpeak of himſelf; but whatſoever he ſhall hear, that ſhall he ſpeak, and he will ſhew you things to come.</hi> Ver. 14. <hi>He ſhall glorify me, for he ſhall receive of mine, and ſhall ſhew it unto you.</hi> Ver. 15. <hi>All things that the Father hath, are mine: therefore, ſaid I, that he ſhall take of mine, and ſhall ſhew it unto you.</hi> The Holy Spirit is here ſaid not to ſpeak of himſelf, but what he hears, which ſheweth that he receiveth thoſe things by Commiſſion from another, and therefore he is not God, for God can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſaid to receive any thing from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther which he had not before.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwer,</hi> Firſt, The Holy Spirit muſt be two ways conſidered.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Eſſentially, as he is eſſentially God.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Perſonally, as he is a Divine Perſon in the Godhead.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, As he is eſſentially God, he can neither receive Commiſſion, or be under the direction of any other of what he ſhould either do or ſpeak.</p>
                  <p n="2">2dly. As he is a Divine Perſon or Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent in the Godhead, and proceedeth
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:32445:89"/>from the Father and the Son, and hath his peculiar Office, he may be ſaid to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, to ſpeak, and be ſent by Comiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion from another; he may be inferiour in Office (though not in Nature) to the other Divine Perſons. And hence it is, that ſome times the Holy Ghoſt is ſaid to be ſent in another's Name, and given to us, <hi>John</hi> 14.26. and at other times it is ſpoken, as of his Power in himſelf to work according to his Will, <hi>John</hi> 16.7, 8. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.11. Now each of theſe are proper to the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>viz.</hi> to be given, ſent, to receive, and ſpeak from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, or to have Power in himſelf to work as he will. The firſt they reſpect his Office, according to his Perſonal Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence by proceſſion from the Father and the Son, (and not that he had not the Knowledg of thoſe things before;) and the other takes in the Divine Eſſence too.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, It may be further ſaid, That the Diſciples of our Lord, had much darkneſs on them, and were ignorant of many things contained in the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, till Chriſt did enlighten their Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings; and therefore they might not have fully underſtood, and digeſted
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:32445:89"/>this ſacred Truth; for we read of ſome which ſaid, <hi>We have not ſo much as heard whether there be any Holy Ghoſt, Luke</hi> 24.45. <hi>Acts</hi> 1.6. <hi>Acts.</hi> 19.2. This being premiſed, our Lord Jeſus might ſpeak this to aſſure them of the Holy Ghoſt's infallible Conduct into all Truth, not only becauſe he is the Spirit of Truth himſelf, which cannot err; but alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he ſhould not ſpeak only as a ſingle voluntary Act of his own, but with the mutual concurrence of the Father and the Son: So that whatſoever he ſhould hear actually interceded for by Chriſt, and aſſented to by God the Father, which ſhould be needful for us to know, that the Holy Spirit ſhould ſhew unto us. So that this Scripture wherein the Holy Ghoſt is ſaid not to ſpeak of himſelf, but what he hears, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> hath a peculiar relation unto his Miniſterial Office, which cannot be repugnant to his Divine Nature; for one Perſon may be inferiour to another in Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and yet of the ſame Nature, as hath been ſaid.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Objection</hi> from <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.1, 13. <hi>ch.</hi> 2.7. where it appears that the Spirit which the ſeven Churches of <hi>Aſia,</hi> were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:32445:90"/>to hearken unto, was none other but the Angel that was ſent to <hi>John,</hi> and did perſonate Jeſus Chriſt; and therefore the Holy Spirit cannot be God equal with the Father.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwer.</hi> The Angel that perſonated Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, the ſame bid the Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> to write to the ſeven Churches of <hi>Aſia:</hi> But in all the Epiſtles, he did not ſpeak to him in his own Name or firſt Perſon, nor dictate the Epiſtles as from himſelf, but from the Perſon of Jeſus Chriſt, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto <hi>John, Write theſe things,</hi> ſaith he, (<hi>viz.</hi> the Son of God)—<hi>the Firſt and the Laſt, which was Dead and is Alive,</hi> &amp;c. So that when the Angel in the concluſive part of the Epiſtles ſaith to <hi>John, He that hath an Ear, let him hear what the [Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit] ſaith to the Churches;</hi> he ſpeaks not of, and from himſelf, but of Jeſus Chriſt who is that Spirit whom they are bid to hear. And this agrees with 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.17. <hi>The Lord is that Spirit;</hi> and is farther con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed and laid as a Foundation-Truth, in the Beginning of this Viſion, <hi>viz.</hi> that what the Angel ſaid muſt be referred to the Almighty Lord, <hi>ver.</hi> 8. <hi>I am</hi> Alpha <hi>and</hi> Omega, <hi>the Beginning and the Ending, ſaith the Lord, which is, and which was,
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:32445:90"/>and which is to come, the Almighty.</hi> And therefore this Scripture is ſo far from proving this erronious opinion, touching the Holy Spirit, that it confirms his Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; for if Jeſus Chriſt be of the Divine Eſſence, and the Holy Spirit is ſaid to ſpeak or ſay when Chriſt ſaith, then it is evident that Chriſt and the Spirit are Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſential.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Wherein are anſwered three Texts of Scripture, from which our Adverſaries urge, that the Father only is God, in oppoſition to the Doctrine of the Holy Trinunity.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>OBjection</hi> from 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.6. <hi>But to us there is but one God the Father, of whom are all things, and we in him: and one Lord Jeſus Chriſt, by whom are all things, and we by him.</hi> Say they, It could no way come to paſs that <hi>Paul</hi> being about to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain who that <hi>one God</hi> is, ſhould menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Father only, omitting the other Perſons, if that one God were not the Father only, but alſo the Son and Holy Spirit, ſince thoſe two Perſons, beſides
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:32445:91"/>the Father, were as neceſſary to declare who that one God is, as the Father him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwer.</hi> It might come to paſs, that <hi>Paul</hi> ſhould call God Father, omitting the Names of the other Divine Perſons, and yet not exclude them from the Unity of the Godhead.</p>
                  <p>Firſt; He might call God Father, not ſimply reſpecting the Perſon of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but indefinitely as he is Creator, <hi>viz.</hi> Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, in oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to falſe Gods, <hi>ver.</hi> 5, 6. <hi>For though there be that are called Gods, whether in Heaven or in Earth (as there be Gods many, and Lords many:) But to us there is but one God the Father, of whom are all things</hi>— which is agreeable to <hi>Mal.</hi> 2.10. <hi>Have we not all one Father? Hath not one God cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated us?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly; It doth not from hence fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that becauſe the Son and the Holy Spirit are here omitted, and the Father only is called that one God; that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Father only is God: becauſe that ſuch omiſſion, is no denial nor excluſion. For the Father being in the Unity of Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence with the other Divine Perſons, muſt not be ſimply conſidered, when he is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:32445:91"/>by thoſe Names, as are common to all three Subliſtencies and the Deity, neither muſt the Son nor the Holy Spirit, unleſs the matter treated of confine us to the Perſon, which in the Text is reconcileable to the Divine Eſſence; for all things are of God indefinitely, Father, Son and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt: and therefore the Father may be called that one God eſſentially, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending the other Divine Perſons.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly; There is ſome reaſon that may be given, wherefore the Father is, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led God, and the Son and Holy Spirit are ſometimes omitted, and left to be included in that common Name, and that is becauſe of the preeminence that the Father hath among the Divine Perſons: For though in excellency of Nature, the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt are neither of them above each other, nor any one of theſe bleſſed Perſons before the other in Time, yet the Father hath a preeminence of Order and Subſiſtence according to his manner of ſelf-ſubſiſting in the Divine Eſſence. For the Father is named firſt, and then the Son and the Holy Spirit, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.7. <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.10. and that becauſe the Father is of none, the Son is of the Father, and the Holy Ghoſt is of them both. And from
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:32445:92"/>hence it is, that we worſhip the Father by the Son, and through the Spirit, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.8. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.18, 21. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.3. So then it is proper enough to call the Father that [<hi>one God</hi>] (eſſentially conſidered, as he is in the Unity of Eſſence with the other Divine Perſons) foraſmuch as he hath this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eminence of Order and Subſiſtence, and that the other two divine Subſiſtences are of and in the Father.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> they ſay, That if Chriſt and the Holy Spirit were God, it were as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to name theſe two Perſons as the Father, to declare who that one God is.</p>
                  <p>To this I anſwer, That if theſe Words <hi>One God the Father,</hi> are perſonally to be conſidered of the Father, yet there was no neceſſity to mention the Son and the Holy Ghoſt: For I hinted before, that when the Father is called that <hi>One God,</hi> the Son and the Holy Spirit muſt be included in that common Name, as being of and in the Father, who is eſſentially ſo called. Now the Apoſtle having told us who that one God is, by naming that Perſon, which moſt properly and ſignificantly includes the reſt, it is ſufficient, ſeeing that his deſign was more to tell us in oppoſition to thoſe many falſe Gods, That to us there
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:32445:92"/>is but one God, than to give a large De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of him. So then let the words <hi>One God the Father,</hi> be taken in either ſenſe as Creator, and ſo common to all three Subſiſtencies, in the Unity of the Godhead, or perſonally of the Father; yet they do neither exclude Jeſus Chriſt, nor the Holy Spirit from the Godhead.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thirdly,</hi> ſome do further add, that Chriſt is manifeſtly diſtinguiſhed from that one God, and ſo is demonſtrated not to be that one God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwer.</hi> It was neceſſary that Chriſt ſhould be diſtinguiſhed from that one God the Father, by thoſe Words, <hi>One Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> to betoken his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip by Donation, as he is Man or Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, becauſe it is different to his ſupream and eſſential Lordſhip; and therefore it requires a different Name to expreſs it by: But yet this does not exclude him from the Unity of Eſſence with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: But, as in <hi>ver.</hi> 5. it is ſaid, <hi>There were many Gods, and many Lords inferiour to thoſe Gods;</hi> So this is to ſhew, in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to them, that there is but one God to us Chriſtians, and but one Lord and Mediator, <hi>viz.</hi> Jeſus Chriſt, that conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered as Man was exalted to that Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:32445:93"/>and appointed by God to be our Lord.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Objection</hi> from <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.6. <hi>One God and Father of all, who is above all;</hi> leſt we ſhould underſtand the Trinity by the Name of that God who is called one; two Perſons of the Trinity were already mentioned, and diſtinguiſhed from that one God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwer.</hi> There cannot more be proved from this Scripture, than what is granted, to wit, that the Father hath ſome Prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence (though not in Nature nor Time) to the Son and Holy Spirit.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, In that he hath his Subſiſtence, neither by being generated, nor by Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, but is of himſelf a Divine Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent in the Divine Nature.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, The Father may be ſaid to be above all, and have the Preheminence with reſpect to the Work and Office of the other Divine Perſons, in bringing of us to God the Father, as the ultimate Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of our Faith and Worſhip, but yet not ſo as to exclude the Son and Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: For though we through the help of the Holy Spirit and Interceſſion of Chriſt, come to the Father who is above all their
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:32445:93"/>miniſterial Offices, and through them in us all, <hi>viz.</hi> the Saints; yet the Father, Son, and Spirit, either or all of them, eſſentially conſidered, may have equally the ſame Worſhip and Adoration given to them, but reſpecting the different Share, Work and Office, belonging to our Salvation, proper to each Divine Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, we ought in Divine Worſhip to make different Attributions accordingly thereunto.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, The Apoſtle's Deſign was not to make a full Deſcription of God unto us, but to ſhew the calling of the Church, that it was but one body in the Unity of one Spirit, in one Hope and Faith, in one Lord, unto one God and Father, who is above all the miniſterial Offices of Chriſt and the Holy Spirit, who work from him, and through them he is in us all. And therefore it was needful to uſe thoſe different Titles, otherwiſe the Union of the Church in one Spirit, with one Lord the Mediator, and head in our Nature, and Order of Faith and Worſhip, could not ſo diſtinctly be underſtood.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Objection</hi> from <hi>John</hi> 17.3. <hi>And this is Life eternal, that they might know thee the
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:32445:94"/>only true God, and Jeſus Chriſt whom thou haſt ſent.</hi> Since Chriſt ſo deſcribed the Father, as to call him the [<hi>only</hi>] <hi>true God,</hi> it is underſtood that only the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Chriſt is the moſt high God; to exclude them from the true Godhead, who were then falſly eſteemed and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped for Gods: and not only them, but all others alſo beſides the Father, from the moſt high Godhead; for the word [<hi>only</hi>] excludeth all others from the Communion of the Predicate, <hi>viz.</hi> the [<hi>true God</hi>] beſides him, <hi>viz.</hi> the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to whom it is applied, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently Chriſt and the Holy Spirit: For if the Gods of the Heathen are by thoſe words of Chriſt underſtood to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded from the true Godhead, becauſe it is apparent, that they are different from the Father; then it is neceſſary that all who are apparently different from the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Jeſus Chriſt, ſhould be excluded from that true Godhead; for otherwiſe the Argument which ſhould from theſe Words be drawn to exclude the Idols of the Heathen from the true Godhead, would be invalid.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwer.</hi> 1ſt. Chriſt ſo deſcribeth the Father, as the only true God, to exclude
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:32445:94"/>them from the true Godhead, who are falſly ſo eſteemed and worſhipped for Gods, and that are not God by Nature: But it is not to be underſtood as if the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Father only were the true God; for though they ſay that the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jective [<hi>only</hi>] as often as it is implied to exclude other Subjects from the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the Predicate, belongs to the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, not the Predicate, yet this muſt be only granted where the Subject is not in the Unity of the ſame Eſſence with other Subjects, but here it is; and therefore the word [<hi>only</hi>] belongs to the Predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, not the Subject. Now then the Queſtion will be, whether the word [<hi>on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi>] is here ſo uſed as to exclude others that are in the Unity of Eſſence with the Subject, from the Predicate or not. If it had been ſaid, that the Father only is the true God, it had excluded all others from the Unity of Eſſence with him, and conſequently Chriſt and the Holy Spirit. But the words are, <hi>That they might know thee, the only true God;</hi> and thus the word [<hi>only</hi>] doth not exclude ſuch from the Communion of the Predicate, <hi>viz. the true God,</hi> that are in the Community of the Subject, <hi>viz. the Father,</hi> as Chriſt
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:32445:95"/>and the Holy Spirit are, but thoſe only that are out of Community with him. So that they muſt firſt prove, that the Son and the Holy Spirit are not in the Unity of Eſſence, coeſſential with the Father, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this Argument can be of uſe to them.</p>
                  <p n="2">2dly. I ſhall note wherefore Chriſt did aſſert his Father's Deity more than his own, and that was to inform us what was Life eternal. For as the Knowledg of the Father as true God, yea, as the only true God, is eſſential to Salvation: ſo alſo is the Knowledg of the Son of God, as Mediator in both Natures: for to know and believe in the Son, as the only true God only, will not ſave us; but we muſt know him alſo as he is in our Nature, in which he purchaſed eternal Life, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.25. 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.3. <hi>John</hi> 6.53.</p>
                  <p>Now ſeeing that it was neceſſary to aſſert the Father to be <hi>the only true God,</hi> and to mention the Son, that we ſhould know him as Mediator in both Natures, as his Name Jeſus Chriſt ſutes unto, why then ſhould any imagine that this Text of Scripture oppoſes the Deity of Jeſus Chriſt?</p>
                  <p>To what is before objected concerning the Holy Spirit, I ſhall add what another
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:32445:95"/>of our Adverſaries ſaith on this Text, <hi>viz.</hi> That our Saviour Chriſt ſetting down thoſe Perſons, in the Knowledg of whom eternal Life conſiſteth, makes no mention of the Holy Spirit; whereas if he were God, the Knowledg of him would be as neceſſary for the Attainment of eternal Life, as that of the Father.</p>
                  <p>To this I anſwer.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, That here to omit the mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Holy Spirit, does not deny the Knowledg of him as God to be eſſential to Salvation.</p>
                  <p>For, as was ſaid, to know Jeſus Chriſt in both Natures, is eſſential to Salvation: for we find that eternal Liſe is entailed on the Son of God, <hi>John</hi> 3.18. <hi>viz.</hi> his Perſon in our Nature, and not in his human Nature alone, (for that is but an Appendent to his Perſon) and then the Holy Ghoſt being only omitted by Name, he muſt be included in the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of the Father and the Son, as being the Spirit of the Father and the Son, and perſonally proceeding from them both, and ſubſiſting coeſſentially in them: And therefore when the Father and the Son are mentioned, the Holy Spirit muſt be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded.</p>
                  <pb n="180" facs="tcp:32445:96"/>
                  <p>Secondly, All ſaving Knowledg or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation of God, depends upon God himſelf, who only can ſo reveal himſelf un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Creatures, <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.25, 27. <hi>I thank thee, O<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Father, becauſe thou haſt hid theſe things from the Wiſe and Prudent, and haſt revealed them unto Babes. — No Man knoweth the Son but the Father, neither know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth any Man the Father ſave the Son, and he to whomſoever the Son will reveal him.</hi> And <hi>John</hi> 16.15. <hi>All things that the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath are mine, therefore ſaid I, He (viz.</hi> the Spirit) <hi>ſhall take of mine, and ſhall ſhew it unto you.</hi> And 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.10, 11. <hi>But God hath revealed them to us by his Spirit.—For what Man knoweth the things of a Man, ſave the Spirit of Man which is in him, even ſo the things of God knoweth no Man, but the Spirit of God.</hi> From which Scriptures we find that the Revelation of the Knowledg of God is appropriated to the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and that none [<hi>but</hi>] the Father [<hi>ſave</hi>] the Son, and [<hi>but</hi>] the Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit can ſavingly reveal God, or each other perſonally and eſſentially unto us. And as we cannot exclude our Knowledg of the Father, and the Son from the Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Spirit, though it is appropri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:32445:96"/>to the Father and the Son by thoſe words [<hi>but the Father</hi>] and [<hi>ſave the Son</hi>] nor exclude our Knowledg of the Spirit from his ſelf Revelation to us, ſeeing all Revelation is by the Spirit; then ſurely there is no reaſon to exclude our Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of the Holy Spirit, as eſſential to Salvation, and conſequently his Deity, though he is not named with the Father and the Son. Beſides, if this ſhould be allowed to diſprove the Deity of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit, by the ſame Rule the Deity of the Father would be diſproved, when e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Life is appropriated to the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of the Son only, which is more the current of the New Teſtament, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.11, 12, 20. <hi>John</hi> 3.36. And therefore as all ſaving-Revelation both of the Father and the Son. is by the Holy Spirit, who proceedeth from them, and is coeſſential with them both, and as we cannot be ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of him who is ſo neceſſarily in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded in our Knowledg of the other two Divine Perſons; ſo it was not ſo neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry that he ſhould be named as it was for the Father and the Son, ſecing he is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded with them, as the Revealer of them both, <hi>John</hi> 16.15. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.10, 11, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So that from <hi>John</hi> 17.3.
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:32445:97"/>there is no reaſon to exclude either Jeſus Chriſt or the Holy Spirit from the Unity of the Supream Godhead.</p>
                  <p>There are other Objections urged a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this Doctrine, by our Adverſaries, which may ſeem to be very plauſible to thoſe that have not weighed them in the Ballance of the Sanctuary. Say they, how can three be one, and one be three? This is ſo abſurd and contrary to their Reaſon, as if one ſhould ſay, that three Men are one Man, and one Man is three: And how can the Son be begotten of the Father, and the Holy Spirit proceed from both, and yet both of them co-eſſential, and co-eternal with the Father.</p>
                  <p>To theſe and divers others of the like nature, I ſhall give a general Anſwer. May we not ſay, that theſe Men do ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of a <hi>Nicodemus</hi> Spirit; and therefore the Words of Chriſt to him may be allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to them, <hi>John</hi> 3.9, 10. Nicodemus <hi>ſaid, how can theſe things be?</hi> Jeſus an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, <hi>If I have told you Earthly things, and ye believe not, how ſhall ye believe if I tell you of Heavenly things?</hi> For thoſe would far more have exceeded his carnal Reaſon. And if we know not what is the way of the Spirit, nor how the Bones do
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:32445:97"/>grow in the Womb of her that is with Child, even ſo we know not the Works of God, who maketh all, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 11.5. and if our Faith be limited to carnal Reaſon, we cannot believe the Reſurrection of the Body; and if the Works of God are too high for us, and his Ways are paſt finding out, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.33. how much more impoſſible is it for finite Creatures to conceive the perfect manner of Exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence, and myſterious Subſiſtence of an infinite Being. We cannot by ſearching find out God, nor the Almighty unto Perfection, <hi>Job</hi> 11.7. God hath been graciouſly pleaſed to make known himſelf unto us in ſuch a manner as that we may rightly worſhip him, and as is ſufficient for our Support and Comfort in all our Afflictions here below, and perſeverance to Salvation: And there we muſt reſt; for as for thoſe ſecret things which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to God, we are not capable to comprehend them, <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.29. And therefore we do imbrace this myſterious Doctrine, becauſe it is revealed to us in the written Word of God: But they reject it as inconſiſtent with natural Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, foreing the Scriptures to comply with that, whereby they make it the Rule of
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:32445:98"/>Faith rather than to admit of that as a Myſtery which God hath declared to be a Myſtery, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1, 6. — <hi>Col.</hi> 2.2.</p>
                  <p>Moreover, we cannot conceive, that it could conſiſt with the faithful diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of that great Truſt which God had committed to his own Son, and Chriſt to his Holy Apoſtles: If while they were aſſerting ſo many things, that might give us to underſtand the ſupream Deity of the Son and Holy Spirit, that they did not intend nor believe the ſame them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; nor can it be imagined, that if they had taught the contrary Doctrine to the Deity of Chriſt and the Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that they ſhould deliver it in ſuch words, as that the Common uſe and ſenſe of them ſhould oppoſe and deſtroy their true meaning intended by thoſe Words.</p>
                  <p>But to conclude my Diſcourſe on this Subject, four Things are neceſſary to be conſidered in order to a right Judgment in this point of Doctrine.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, Conſider how firm a Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this Doctrine hath in the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, what Number of ſacred Texts there are, that plainly aſſert the Deity of Jeſus Chriſt and the Holy Spirit.</p>
                  <pb n="185" facs="tcp:32445:98"/>
                  <p n="2">2dly. Conſider what monſterous work the <hi>Socinians</hi> make, to eſcape the force of thoſe clear Scripture-Teſtimonies, that aſſert the Deity of Chriſt and the Holy Spirit; how abſurd they are in their Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, and the violence they uſe to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend their Hereſy, by wreſting, denying and abuſing the Holy Scriptures, may ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily be perceived; and what pains they take to ſqueez out of ſome few Texts, that which is not contained in them, and is repugnant to the current of ſacred Scripture.</p>
                  <p n="3">3dly. Conſider how fairly thoſe very Scriptures on which they build, are recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled to this Doctrine of the Holy Trinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and how our Expoſitions of them are coherent with it, and in themſelves, as is apparently manifeſt from what hath been ſaid in anſwer to them. So that their Doctrine is inconſiſtent with the Infallibility of the Word of God: for while they are not able to reconcile ſo great numbers of ſacred Texts (that aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert the Deity of Chriſt and the Holy Ghoſt) to their Opinion, they render it exceeding ambiguous, and full of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords. And therefore there is a neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that we acknowledg the Holy Trinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:32445:99"/>otherwiſe in effect we reject the Scriptures, as inſufficient to guide us into Truth and Righteouſneſs; and therefore ſeeing the Authority, and the ſweet Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of the Holy Scriptures depends on the truth of this Doctrine, and that the contrary Opinion deſtroys both, and leaves us deſtitute of a Rule of Faith and Obedience, it is the indiſpenſible Duty of every Chriſtian, to diſcard ſo great an Error, and to believe that there are three Divine Subſiſtencies in the Deity, and that theſe three, the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit, are but one God. To whom be Glory and Praiſe, now and for evermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:32445:99"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:32445:100"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:32445:100"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
